Hello and welcome to revolutions.
Episode 20, The Boston Tea Party.
In the seven years since the end of the French and Indian War, relations between Britain
and her colonies had gone through a few cycles of depressing antagonism.
Neither side really understanding what the other was up to or why.
But now that the fervor over the towns and axe was subsiding, both Britain and America
looked forward to the return of productive and profitable normalcy.
And for almost two years, it looked like the chaotic hostility of the 1760s would be
contained to the 1760s.
Parliament made no further provocative moves.
The radical colonial leaders went into political eclipse and British goods started
flowing back into the colonies in larger quantities than ever.
But the peace and prosperity would not last.
The first clue that neither side was done and hanging, rising, the other came in June
1772 when a customs ship called the Gas B ran aground while chasing suspected smugglers
off the coast of Rhode Island.
A local mob quickly descended on the beach.
Chip took it over by force and burned it.
Parliament was, of course, outraged and formed a commission to investigate the affair.
But this commission was stonewalled and blamed never could be properly assessed.
But informing the commission, parliament revealed that it still had a tin ear when it
came to colonial politics.
Because had anyone in Rhode Island been found culpable?
The commissioners were empowered to drag them back to Britain for trial, which to the
colonists made a mockery of the whole right to be tried by a jury of your peers thing.
You know, one of the bedrocks of English liberty.
Then over the summer, attentions in neighboring Massachusetts started to rise again over
the lingering issue of how to pay for the royal administration.
Though the Townsend duties had been mostly repealed, the right to pay the governor had
not been returned to the Massachusetts Assembly, and the remaining duty on tea now paid
Gov. Thomas Hutchinson salary in mid 1770 to the ministry, started making noises that
they wanted to extend this policy to include all the judges as well as swallowing the
governor's salary had been tough.
But the thought of the judiciary becoming a mere tool of the crown was too much to bear.
And committees of correspondence began to reappear in January 1773.
Governor Hutchinson then added fuel to the fire when he bluntly announced that the
committees were way out of line.
Parliament's authority was supreme, always had been and always would be.
And then he said no line can be drawn between the supreme authority of Parliament and the
total independence of the colonies.
His assumption here was that independence was so unthinkable that the answer must be
Parliament is in charge.
But unfortunately, that did not turn out to be an assumption that everyone shared.
But the real end to the uneasy calm that had prevailed in the colony since 1770 came in
May 1773 when parliament passed the Tea Act, the Tea Act has nothing to do with the duty
on tea left over from the towns and acts.
Now this is a whole new piece of tea based obnoxiousness.
The issue Parliament was trying to address is when I briefly mentioned last week the East
India Company was in a deplorable state of financial disrepair and needed a bailout.
Now, put simply, the East India Company was a private corporation that held a legal
monopoly on trade with India and China.
It had been chartered back in 16:00, was owned by a collection of rich traders and
well-connected aristocrats, and was, at this point in history, so corrupt and mismanaged
that it was about to implode.
Now, I'm going to oversimplify all of this so we don't have to talk about the crushingly
boring details of how T auctions work in London.
But the upshot of it all was that the Tea Act allowed the company to start importing its
tea directly into the colonies.
The point was to both find an outlet for the huge stockpiles of tea.
The company had accidentally built up and plug them into a stable new revenue stream.
The Tea Act looked like a pretty good deal to parliament, one that they hoped would go
over well in the colonies, where retail customers would now be able to buy tea at cut
rate prices. The only pushback was supposed to come from the few colonial middlemen who
made a living importing tea from London and of course, the smugglers who made a living
sneaking in duty free tea from the Netherlands.
But who cares about them? As it turned out, though, rage over the Tea Act was, as usual,
far more widespread than anyone in Parliament anticipated.
Things got off on the wrong foot right away when it was mistakenly rumoured that the
company tea would be exempt from Townsend tea duty, which, had it been true, would have
been quite a poke in the eye to the colonists.
But the real fear was that the company tea was just the beginning, and that if it all
worked out that soon other British companies would be allowed to sell directly into the
colonies too. And this might temporarily be good for the consumer, but it would be
devastating to the independent colonial economy and in effect, reduce them all to a bunch
of manual laborers producing raw materials for the home country and nothing more.
Into this. Governor Hutchinson once again added fuel to the fire, though, in his defense.
These letters were supposed to have been secret.
Back in the late 1760s, Hutchinson and a few conservative allies in Boston had written a
series of letters to a sub minister back in Britain 1772.
These letters were passed by some anonymous agent to Benjamin Franklin, who sent them
along to a friend back home.
They were supposed to remain under wraps, but after Franklin's friend sat on them for six
months, he agreed with Samuel Adams that it was too good of a hand not to play because
Wynne published these letters confirm the most paranoid radical fantasies about a
conspiracy to extinguish English liberty in the colonies.
Because Hutchinson explicitly recommends that the ministry suspend certain liberties in
the colonies. As the autumn of 1773 approached, opposition to the Tea Act spread up and
down the colonies, though this time the merchants of Philadelphia, far from dragging
their feet, led the way they were led by the credible voice of John Dickinson, who
remained for now on the leading edge of radical resistance, with seventy carrying ships
bound for Boston, New York, Philadelphia and Charleston already long.
The resurgent radical swore to stop the tea from being off loaded.
Now, this is probably a good time to point out that though there was a healthy public
consensus about this, there were definitely men and women who wanted nothing to do with
all of these non importation schemes.
Some because it hurt their bottom line, some because they were politically sympathetic to
parliament's claim of authority and some because they know less than the radicals just
didn't like being told what to do.
So when it came to making sure these various non importation and non consumption
agreements worked. Enforcement mechanisms were required.
The most basic tool of enforcement was social and economic isolation.
Names of merchants who defied the import bans were published in the papers and boycotts
of their businesses encouraged the incident just before the Boston massacre, for example,
the one when the kid got killed was started when enforcers hung an importer sign above a
man's house and a sympathetic neighbor tried to take it down.
But if social and economic coercion weren't enough, physical coercion was next up up to
and including the old tar and feathering routine, which was quite a bit more vicious a
practice than you might think.
To the more conservative merchants, the ones who will wind up loyalists when the war
breaks out. The hypocrisy of all this was galling.
I mean, how can you claim to be a defender of liberty when you won't even let me conduct
my business as I see fit?
But of course, there was a bigger picture to consider.
And since we're already wandering away from the story, this seems like a pretty good time
to peel off and consider the psychological framework within which the colonists were
operating. Try to understand why the ministry's policies the Stamp Act in the towns and
ACT and now the Tea Act were provoking so much resistance resistance that you might think
is just a wee bit out of proportion to the relatively light tax increases they
represented. So for this I'll be drawing from an absolute must read if you're into the
Revolution. The Ideological Origins of the American Revolution by Bernard Beilein.
I can only give you a superficial sketch of his argument here.
So if you're interested, I would encourage you to pick it up, because as it turns out,
the colonists were drawing from a very specific set of principles to help them interpret
the ministry's actions in the worst possible light.
After reviewing the contemporary political literature, that is all the pamphlets that
were flying off the presses, Balen identified five basic foundations for the American
argument against Parliament.
First, there was antiquity, mostly the example of Republican Rome and the fight against
the tyranny of the Caesars.
But Balen argues that while references to the ancient world are uniformly present, they
are also uniformly superficial and act more as rhetorical window dressing than anything
else. Second were the Enlightenment philosophers, most especially John Locke.
But those references are similarly superficial, with Locke in particular appealed to as a
universal authority trotted out to lend credibility to arguments that he never actually
made. Third were appeals to English Common Law, which had more weight and force behind
them and did solidly route the revolution in the British tradition.
Fourth was a dose of Puritan theology which infused the movement with a providential
sense of destiny that America truly had a special role to play in God's grand design.
But the Fifth Foundation, the one that tied the rest of it together, turns out to be a
collection of fringe politicians from the early seventeen hundreds who represented the,
quote, country party that was opposed to the, quote, Korte party.
These guys believed that history was little more than a running battle between power and
liberty. And they deployed this theory, most especially against their great enemy, Sir
Robert Walpole, who, as I mentioned, is regarded as the first prime minister and who
utterly dominated the British government from the seventeen twenties to the seventeen
forties. The specific way Walpole Consolidated Power, three patronage network that bound
men politically and financially to the crown, which our fringe theory saw as the utter
debasement and corruption of English liberty, and which our colonists kind of see
happening in their backyard.
But though these country party ideas never caught on at home, their tracks were widely
printed in the colonies and wound up taking deep root in the American political psyche,
which was from then on, always on guard against powers, endless attempt to subvert
liberty. So all the recent moves by Parliament taxes levied without representation.
The influx of new customs agents, the push to free colonial governors from the local
assemblies, the standing armies out on the western frontier and in the streets of Boston,
an attempt to set up a government backed trade monopoly.
This did not look to the colonists like a government honestly trying to deal with the
intricate problems of empire.
It looked like a genuine conspiracy to secure the final triumph of power over liberty in
the colonies and turn Americans into slaves.
But getting back to our story, Massachussets was actually lagging a bit behind on the
issue of the tea tax because Samuel Adams was too busy trying to destroy Thomas
Hutchinson to notice what was going on in the rest of the world.
But that said, when it came down to it, Boston once again took center stage in the
dramatic confrontations that accompanied the arrival of company tea in the colonies.
On November the twenty eighth, 1773, a merchant ship called the Dartmouth arrived in
Boston carrying, among other things, tea from the East India Company.
The Dartmouth was supposed to offload its cargo, take on some whale oil and then sail
away. But the Sons of Liberty were not going to let the tea off of the ship.
Over the next two days, there were huge public meetings in Boston with upwards of 5000 in
attendance. Under no circumstances was the Dartmouth to do anything but turn around and
take the tea back to Britain.
The ship was put under constant surveillance to make sure that happened.
Now you've got a feel for the poor owner of the ship.
An American, by the way, because he had loaded the T long before Boston decided they
weren't going to take it. Anxious to not have his cargo or, God forbid, his ship
destroyed. The owner requested permission from Hutchinson to leave, but Hutchinson
refused the request, saying the Dartmouth hadn't cleared customs yet.
And of course, the only way to clear customs is offload the cargo.
So, yeah, you gotta feel bad for this guy because the poor dude is just stuck.
I mean, he's perfectly willing to do anything anybody want.
Not to be caught in the middle of all this.
And both sides are telling him now we've decided you are the middle of this.
From the minute the Dartmouth dog.
The clock was ticking because the law further stipulated that if a ship remained in port
for 20 days without paying customs, that it would be seized by the customs agents and you
guessed it, have their cargo offloaded.
So everyone knew that when the 20 days wound up, something was going to happen.
Then just to make things more interesting, in the meantime, two additional ships carrying
Company T arrived.
When December the 16th, 1773, rolled around and the Dartmouth still hadn't offloaded her
cargo. Another public meeting was convened during this meeting.
Samuel Adams delivered his famous line about there being nothing more they could do to
save their country, which was supposed to be the signal for pre-selected members of the
Sons of Liberty to go dump the tea.
But it appears that that story, while not exactly apocryphal, is a little too neat and
tidy regardless.
The assembled crowd was soon marching down to the docks, where they cheered on the
somewhere between 50 and 100 men.
A handful of whom had donned Indian dress, who boarded all three tea bearing ships and
methodically dumped ninety thousand pounds of tea into the harbor.
As usual, this was a disciplined operation.
No other cargo was damaged and in a civilized touch when a padlock belonging to one of
the captains was broken, he found a new one delivered to him a few days later.
When word of the incident, now charmingly known as the Boston Tea Party reached Britain
in January, the ministry went into apoplectic convulsions with Lord North announcing that
this was no longer a fight about taxes, but, quote, whether we have or not any authority
in that country. They call Benjamin Franklin to appear before the Privy Council two days
later to explain the actions of the man he officially represented.
Franklin, as always, was prepared to do so.
But his interview with the Privy Council turned out to be a rage fuelled ambush.
Franklin, as I mentioned, was easily the most respected and influential American.
And with the ministry preparing to lay heavy reprisals on Massachusetts.
They thought it would be a good idea to demolish the credibility of Franklin so he would
be neutralized politically if he tried to rally support for his countrymen for an hour.
Franklin was berated in terms so severe that much of what was said was not even written
down. Most of this berating was over his dishonorable conduct in the scandal over
Hutchinson's letters.
Franklin, recognizing that he couldn't win, remained silent and simply laughed when the
ministers had blown all their gas.
Now, up until now, Franklin had been a proud and longstanding defender of the British
Empire, even if he disagreed with this or that policy.
From here on out, though, he will join Hutchinson in the belief that there was no longer
any middle ground. Either Parliament was supreme or the colonies must be independent, and
you can guess which one he now thought preferable.
The heavy reprisals the ministry had planned were delivered between March and May 1774 in
a set of four or five related bills that were called the Coercive Acts in Britain, but
which were quickly dubbed in America the Intolerable Acts.
The first was the Boston port bill, which closed the city to all trade but for a few
tightly controlled essentials.
The blockade would start June 15th and continue until the East India Company was
reimbursed for the Dump T, which was valued at about ten thousand pounds.
The second was the Massachusetts Regulatory Act, which more or less abolished
self-government in Massachusetts, making all offices governor appointed and severely
limiting legislative assemblies.
This was coupled with the Administration of Justice Act, which removed from local
jurisdiction any crimes committed by royal officials who would now be tried either in
another colony or, better yet, back in Britain.
The last of these strictly punitive measures was the Quartering Act, which gave far
greater power to the army when it came to securing lodgings.
A problem as we saw they ran into during the fight over the towns and acts.
And last, we have a bill that was passed at the same time and often gets lumped in with
the intolerable acts, but was disconnected from the rest.
And this was the Quip Back Act, which extended the territory of the province of Quebec on
a line running south west, effectively cutting off any claims the colonies had to land
west of the proclamation line, which was offensive both for obvious economic reasons and
for more emotional religious reasons because Quebec was Catholic.
If anyone still felt like missing the point about what was going on in Massachusetts on
May the 13th, a new governor showed up to replace Hutchinson General Thomas Gage, who had
served since 1763 as commander in chief of all British forces in North America.
Massachusetts was now, for all intents and purposes, under military occupation.
News of the Intolerable Act hit the rest of the colonies as a divisive bombshell, with
radicals demanding solidarity with their oppressed brothers and conservatives refusing to
get dragged down by the lunatics up in Boston.
But as the various colonies hashed out how best to respond to the crisis in
Massachusetts, they all started coming to the same conclusion that the colonies ought to
get together and talk about it collectively.
Radicals believed such an assembly would allow them to forge a powerful and united front
to oppose parliament's tyranny, while conservatives believed that by elevating the debate
to a higher plane that cooler heads would prevail.
Over the summer of 1774, the colonies each in their own way, selected delegates to meet
in Philadelphia in September.
The only colony not to send a delegation was Georgia, who, reeling from an uprising of
Creek Indians, would have gladly accepted all the troops.
Boston was trying to get rid of on September the 5th, 1774.
Fifty six men representing 12 colonies met in Carpenter's Hall in Philadelphia and
convened the first continental Congress as they began their session.
The Massachusetts delegation, which included both Sam and John Adams, made a concerted
effort to hold back.
They understood that it was kind of their fault.
Everyone was in this mess and knew that if the other delegates thought they were being
bullied or manipulated by the Boston radicals, that Massachusetts might find itself cut
loose. But luckily for them, it quickly became clear that the radicals outnumbered the
conservatives. And the list of delegates is just a list of Revolutionary War leaders.
The Adams is Patrick Henry, Richard, Henry Lee, George Washington, John Dickinson, Thomas
Mifflin, Silas Dean.
These guys were ready to act as the Continental Congress convened them up in
Massachusetts. A meeting of the various committees of correspondence would help define
what action the Congress ultimately decided to take, because the result of this meeting
was the Suffolk resolves Suffolk being the county within which Boston was located.
Written by Dr. Joseph Warren, who had taken control of the radicals with the Adams is in
Philadelphia. The Suffolk resolves unequivocally move the colony toward war.
Beyond the obvious economic boycotts, citizens were encouraged to simply ignore the
coercive acts, stop paying their taxes and most importantly, to take control of the local
militias and quote, do use their utmost diligence to acquaint themselves with the art of
war. As soon as possible.
And do for that purpose appear underarms at least once every week.
The results were passed on September the 9th and a draft was sent down to Philadelphia by
a guy who next week is going to make an even more famous ride.
Boston silversmith Paul Revere The Suffolk Resolves.
We're not just accepted by the Congress.
They were endorsed and destroyed whatever hope the conservatives had of controlling the
debate with the results in hand.
The delegates turned to what the colonies collectively ought to do about the intolerable
acts. Richard Henry Lee move that a national militia be formed.
But this was going too far, too fast.
And they settled on merely alerting the various colonies to take steps to make sure that
their local militias were trained.
Less controversial was agreeing not to import or consume British goods.
But now, on sure footing, the Massachusetts delegation decided to push for a further
step, one that would hurt the colonies but would hopefully hurt Britain even more non
exportation. Now, this was no small thing.
And even in this assembly of Patriots, it stirred heated debate.
The Massachusetts delegation was talking about severing all trade with Britain, which
everyone knew would be an economic disaster.
The Virginia delegation, for example, would only agree to non exportation if it did not
take effect until August 1775.
The wheels of the tobacco economy were already in motion and trying to stop it before the
next shipment in August 1775 would simply be asking too much.
After that, they could make plans to deal with the repercussions.
But before that, now we would all be destroyed.
Then the South Carolina delegation spoke up and said, well, we'll get on board with this,
but we'll need an exemption for Rice and Indigo.
Now, they took a beating for this and we're accused of trying to sell their vote.
But the men of South Carolina did have a point.
The other colonies could find foreign ports to dump their stuff.
But South Carolina rice and indigo ship exclusively to British ports.
Shutting down exports to Britain meant basically shutting down South Carolina completely,
something none of the other colonies faced.
After a great deal of wrangling, the two sides wound up splitting the difference.
Rice would be exempted.
Indigo would not then.
Surprisingly, the delegates managed to avoid any further special deals.
And by early October, the plan was struck.
Non consumption would begin immediately.
Non importation would begin December the 1st to allow for orders already on the way.
Non exportation would begin September the 10th, 1775 if you know nothing happened.
In the meantime. To enforce these boycotts, the Congress created what is known as the
Continental Association, or more often simply the association.
Local committees would be formed to police their neighbors and make sure that no one
cheated. And though they did not know it at the time, by creating the association,
Congress had actually just created the skeleton of the Revolutionary War effort.
Because when the fighting breaks out come the spring of 1775.
The committees that formed the association seamlessly transition from their original
purpose of enforcing a boycott to running all necessary wartime logistics at the local
level. Fundraising, troop raising, requisitioning supplies.
Intelligence gathering.
These committees soon became the backbone of the revolution after formally signing the
association. On October the 20th, the first Continental Congress disbanded on October
twenty sixth and sent their delegates home to gear up for the boycott, agreeing to
reconvene for a second Continental Congress on May the 10th, 1775.
As soon as the delegates arrived home, the various colonies got to work, setting up local
branches of the association and come December, the first enforcing the non importation
part of plan in this.
The association was an unqualified success.
The governor of Virginia, for example, complained that the citizens paid more heed to the
directives of the association and they did to the colonial government.
The response to all this back in Britain was harsh.
Lord North declared that if the colonies wouldn't trade with Britain, then they sure as
hell weren't going to trade with anyone else.
And he laid out a plan for a continental blockade.
Meanwhile, General Gage repeated warnings that the Intolerable Act were doing exactly the
opposite of what they were supposed to be doing.
They were supposed to be isolating Massachusetts and scaring everyone else into
submission. Instead, they were cementing colonial solidarity and intensifying resistance.
He asked for the ministry to withdraw the intolerable acts, and if not, then please send
twenty thousand troops because maybe then I'll be able to get a handle on things.
All this did was convince the ministry that General Gage probably wasn't the man for the
job. And they dispatched three generals to act as military advisors.
William, how Henry Clinton and John Bourgoyne.
Next week, everything will break down once and for all.
General gages attempt to lock up all the guns and powder in Massachusetts will lead to
armed confrontations with local militias in Lexington and Concord, where someone
somewhere fired the shot heard round the world.