Hello, and welcome to revolutions Episode 28 Yorktown.
Today we come to the end of the American War of Independence.
What had started in the 1760s as a political conflict over the place of the American colonies within
the British Empire, it turned into a military conflict that was now dragging into its sixth year.
During these years, the leaders of the American Revolution had been consumed almost entirely with the
task of running the war. But the victory Yorktown finally allowed them to return to the questions that
had roused them to action in the first place. What are the proper limits of government? What are the
rights of the citizens? How do we reconcile the forces of power and liberty so that we can preserve
freedom while maintaining stability? While the war was on these questions were mostly tabled in the interest
of maintaining a united Patriotic Front. When the war ended, it came time to figure out what it had
all been for. As we will see in the episodes to come, there would turn out to be surprisingly little
agreement about what the revolution was supposed to have meant.
Before we get into it, though, I need to make a few corrections that have been helpfully passed along.
listener Malcolm expressed some surprise that the British would put an 86 year old Admiral in charge
of its navy and he was of course, right. Admiral arbuthnott got the pronunciation now to was 68 years
old, not 86. I was just some accidental dyslexia on my part.
listener Dylan points out that Camden, South Carolina isn't really on the border between the Carolinas
and that's also true and was badly worded on my part.
It's down about 75 or 80 miles or so. So you know, it's near the border, but not on the border.
Finally, listener, Elizabeth reminds me that the quote about Philadelphia taking how rather than how
taking Philadelphia comes from Benjamin Franklin, not George Washington, which of course it does.
I don't know how I got that wrong, but I did. Especially since there's an old rhetorical trick where
if you don't know who said something, you can just attribute it to Benjamin Franklin or also Mark Twain,
and no one will ever call you out on it even works if you've got some pithy quote of your own, you want
to test out on your friends, you know, I believe it was Benjamin Franklin, who said never trust a man
who says that his favourite kind of music is whatever's on the radio.
So thank you guys for keeping me honest. Okay, so when we left off last time, in March 1781, Cornwallis
had just quote unquote, won the battle of Guildford courthouse.
The air quotes are there because the heavy casualties the British suffered not only further pinch, Cornwallis
has strategic options, but also badly eroded the morale of his men.
Even more than their commander the rank and file had been suffering through this year in the Carolinas
fighting battles that settled nothing, defending positions that controlled nothing.
And all the while getting jumped by guerrillas eating rotten food and contracting all manner of disease
was all turning out to be as deadly as it was pointless.
And now their only reward for having driven the Americans from the field at Guilford Courthouse was
to find that a quarter of their comrades were dead or wounded.
Are we any closer to securing the South than we were yesterday? No.
Are we in fact probably even further away than ever? sure looks like it.
On the other side of lines, General Nathaniel Greene was regrouping from the quote unquote loss at Guildford
courthouse by proposing a bold initiative to plunge into South Carolina and start attacking all those
little Garrison's Cornwallis had spread across the countryside in the previous year.
It was a good idea because it would put Cornwallis in a bind or so Greene thought.
The British General could either follow the American South and engage in more running battles that would
exhaust his been physically and emotionally or he could stay and try to consolidate his hold on North
Carolina, leaving green to have the run of South Carolinaon a post.
But his sound his greens reasoning seem to be Cornwallis already had a third option in mind.
Is he Cornwallis was just as discouraged as his men about their prospects in the Carolinas.
The strategy of systematically moving from south to north was proving to be a bust.
It had been entirely dependent on a partnership with a loyalist population that had turned out to be
neither as plentiful nor as helpful as the British assumed.
But even as the whole war now really started to slip away from the British for good.
Cornwallis dreamed up yet another grand strategy to try to salvage the situation.
In a letter to Clinton purportedly asking for instructions, Cornwallis laid out what he thought those
instructions ought to be. That Cornwallis should have been in the Carolinas move into Virginia, make
a base on the Chesapeake Bay. From that central pivot point.
They would then divide and conquer the rebel colonies once and for all.
And so when green plunged into South Carolina, and Cornwallis did not follow.
It wasn't because he was trying to hold North Carolina, but because he was trying to get out of there
as quickly as possible. In the middle of April 1781, Greene put his plan in motion and move first on
the 900 British steel garrison in Camden, South Carolina, under the command of Lord rondon, who was
left as the senior British officer in the state. When Cornwallis decided to march away to Virginia.
Green led a column of about 1500 directly to Camden, while smaller detachments were sent around to lock
up the countryside and cut off supplies and communication lines.
On April the 23rd, Francis Marion and light horse Harry Lee, famous cavalry Colonel and father of Robert
E. Lee, succeeded in capturing fort Watson just south of Camden, after they constructed a large tower
that allowed sharpshooters to fire inside the fort.
But Camden proved a tougher nut to crack. The British had built up the defense's since the Americans
had last been in the area. Unable to storm the steady right away, green pulled back about a mile to
an elevated position called hob Kirk's Hill, and could only hope to induce the British to come out and
fight. Luckily for green, Lord ridden was both nervous about what would happen when the forces under
Marion and Lee link back up with green. And he'd been tipped off by a desert that the Americans had
no artillery. So if he was going to stop the seed before it began, now was the time to do it.
So on the morning of April the 25th, he led his men out of Camden, skirting the edge of a swamp to hit
the hopefully unsuspecting Americans. The Americans were in fact caught by surprise, but the British
were then themselves surprised to find that the deserter had been wrong.
Green did have himself a nice little battery of artillery.
The British came up in a narrow line, so green ordered his now scrambling into line forces to envelop
them. While he pasted their centre with the heavy guns.
The British took a sharp and unexpected beating but managed to keep themselves composed.
Meanwhile, the American regiment supposedly enveloping the left flank, saw their commander get shot
down and then in a confused attempt to recruit round up easy prey for a hard charge by the British that
scattered them. Meanwhile, the American cavalry that had been sent around the other side got bogged
down taking some prisoners and never made it back around to the battle in time.
So Greene was forced to withdraw from the field. But as with Guildford courthouse, the Battle of hobb
Kirk's Hill was another Pyrrhic victory for the British, with 40 dead and over 200 wounded.
With the Americans controlling the surrounding area, Lord ridden recognise that Camden was a lost cause.
On May the 90 abandon the city and headed south for Charleston.
After breaking off a detachment to go capture Augusta, Georgia, a mission that went off without a hitch,
Greene took the rest of his forces west to drive off the 550 man garrison, mostly loyalists, the town
of 96, South Carolina Don't ask me why it's calledthat there's apparently a half dozen different legends
to explain it. Greene settled in outside the fortified village on May the 22nd with about 1000 men.
But the British fortifications again precluded an immediate attack so green had to lay siege.
But after a few weeks of digging trenches, news arrived that ridden was personally leading a 2000 man
relief army out of Charleston, having just been reinforced by the men he had sent to take Augusta green
decided to mountain attack on 96 on June 18, for the British reinforcements can show up.
The attack started well for the Americans. But as they pushed forward, their officers started getting
shot up under heavy fire and the men fell back to the safety of their trenches.
With ridden breathing down his neck green with drew back to the relative safety of Charlotte.
But as with Camden, the tactical defeat was a strategic victory as Ratan simply collected the loyalists
at 96 abandon the village and headed back to Charleston.
Now, the only spot left in South Carolina, the British still controlled it anyone personified the old
cliche of losing the battle, winning the war. It was Nathaniel Greene in the southern Theatre of the
American Revolutionary War. Backup in the north, the stalemate that had persisted for the last few years
was finally about to break loose, but not without some touching go trouble for General George Washington.
over the winter of 1780 1781, the inevitable finally occurred, mutiny in the continental ranks.
The amazing thing, of course, is that it had taken this long, the grievances of the soldiers were as
many as they were justified. They were badly fed, badly supplied, paid late, and then when they were
paid at all given worthless continental script. One of Washington's great accomplishments perhaps the
great accomplishment is that he exuded such a force of inspirational leadership that his men had endured,
without ever taking any fatal steps. Sure desertion was a daily problem, but not mutiny, never mutiny.
But on New Year's Day 1781 1200 men from the Pennsylvania line wintering in Morristown, New Jersey had
had enough. They revolted against their officers killing a few in the process.
And then they set out for Philadelphia to force the Congress to address their grievances.
Now, these guys were loyal patriots, and their rallying cry was actually we're not Arnold's but enough
was enough. Washington was concerned about confronting them personally fearful that his aura of authority
might be shattered if they did not submit. So he dispatched mad Anthony Wayne to nip it in the bud.
Wayne let the mutineers crossed the Delaware River, and then surrounded them.
Negotiations produced an agreement that half of these guys would be released from service altogether,
and the rest furloughed until spring. But Wayne did identify the ringleaders and ordered them shocked,
though he was forced to also threatened to shoot the assigned executioner's when they hesitated to fire
on their own comrades. Then, almost as soon as this crisis passed, another 200 men from the New Jersey
line mutinied. Washington again stayed away personally, but ordered this time that there'll be no negotiations
this had already gone too far. The 200 mutineers were surrounded and offered no terms they submitted,
and again, the ringleaders were shocked. With the benefit of hindsight, we also now know that these
two mutinies were merely prelude to the really big mutiny that will bubble up next week, a mutiny that
leads to one of the most dramatic single moments of the whole revolutionary era, the moment when the
Continental Army did not follow the example of the New Model Army, because Washington refused to be
cast as an American Cromwell. The mutinies though did highlight the pressing necessity for more loans
from the French. And over that same winter, Benjamin Franklin managed to not only secure more money,
but yet a deeper commitment for military assistance.
So to go back a little bit to catch up with the French.
After failing to take Savannah in 1779, the comp distain had sailed home, where he was understandably
replaced in the spring of 17. At a new fleet was dispatched carrying 7000 land forces that would join
with Washington's army. This army larger even than the one Washington himself.
Currently lead was commanded by the comp de roshambo.
This fleet landed in Newport, Rhode Island in July 1780.
Odd Did I mention the British pulled out of Newport at the end of 1779.
I didn't. Man there's a lot of moving pieces here.
The British moved out of Newport at the end of 1779.
So the French landed at Newport and the army disembarked, but then the British Navy promptly swung in
and blockaded a lot of them. With the Navy trapped roshambo refused to leave them unsupported to the
plan link up with Washington was delayed for the year.
Things might have gone on like that indefinitely, but in January 1781, a storm blew through New England
that drove the British blockade from its position outside Newport.
The French fleet was now free to manoeuvre, and the French army under roshambo was free to start making
plans for a joint operation with Washington, though both the French army and French Navy maintain their
base at Newport. The timing of the storm was fortuitous, because just a few weeks earlier, Henry Clinton
had decided to put the trader Benedict Arnold to good use, and put him in charge of about 1500 men in
late December 1780 aren't a lead these forces down on a rate of Virginia, surprising the local militias,
destroying the supply infrastructure and temporarily capturing Richmond the capital, but he didn't have
the manpower to hold it. So Arnold withdrew to the coastal city of Portsmouth, where he holed up and
waited for reinforcements. With the trader Arnold threatening his home state, Washington dispatch the
now trusted practically to the point of being a surrogate son, Marquis de Lafayette, down with 1200
men to shore up the defences. He also successfully convinced the newly freed French Navy to follow in
support. As they sail though, the Nao regrouped British fleet under 174 year old Admiral arbuthnott
followed, a brief skirmish ensued. On both fleets hit Virginia at just about the same time, the French
decided to withdraw back to Newport, leaving the British for the moment in control of Chesapeake Bay.
While all of this was going on in early 1781, another French fleet this one bound for the West Indies,
set sail under the command of Admiral to grace. The grace had served with distinction under sustained
during the first run through the Caribbean in 1779.
And it was expected that he would wage a more vigorous and cooperative campaign than his predecessor
had. This second French fleet say All the way from Europe without so much as a Hey, where are you going
from the British Navy. This was mostly because further French and American diplomacy had brought both
the Spanish and Dutch into the anti British Alliance.
Neither was technically declaring for the Americans, but they both declared against the British which
for the moment was just as good. These new threat to the home waters turned the British Ministry cross
eyed and upside down, so they failed to send any ships to America.
They might even the balance of power at sea when this second French fleet took off.
This meant that as soon as the grace sailed into the Caribbean in April 1781, the French and by extension
their American allies, now enjoyed a serious advantage at sea advantage, it was about to prove decisive.
As the end game approaches, the next major piece entered its final position when Clinton sent yet another
army into Virginia in April 1781 to continue the devastating rains.
After swinging through Portsmouth to pick up Benedict Arnold this for soon number just over 3000 Baron
von stuben and the local Virginia militia tried to hold their ground, but they were forced back to Richmond,
the British pursued, but Lafayette and his Continentals linked up with von stuben, just in the nick
of time. The British let them have Richmond and went back to writing all the while being reinforced until
they numbered close to 6000. When the British General in charge suddenly dropped dead in May, Arnold
found himself the senior officer in charge position he held for just about a week, because that's when
Cornwallis and his 1000 plus exhausted men dragged themselves into Petersburg, a strategically important
city located on a tributary of the James River. In leaving the Carolinas, Cornwallis was pretty much
disobeying orders,but he didn't really care Clinton was being in communicative and indecisive and obviously
failed to recognise just how much the situation in the south had changed.
Not that Clinton sought to discipline Cornwallis because for the moment, the commander in chief was
occupied with amping his vacillation up to dizzying speeds.
He ordered Cornwallis to pick a spot on Chesapeake Bay and fortify it for use as a permanent base of
operations. Okay, good. Check, I was already going to do that.
Then Clinton ordered him to break off whatever forces he didn't need and send them back up to New York.
Kay, but I don't really want to do that. But then the orders changed, and Cornwallis was to send these
troops to Pennsylvania, which that doesn't seem like but then the orders changed again, and it was no
On second thought do send them to New York. Cornwallis appears to have endured this vacillation by never
actually sending the troops Clinton demanded. He did however, follow the order to build a fortified
base, not necessarily where he would have liked, told by Clinton to fortify either Williamsburg or Yorktown.
Cornwallis selected Yorktown as the lesser of two evils.
It was a decision he would regret for the rest of his life.
But for the time being, the British were still mostly ascended in Virginia and continued their devastating
raids, including the famous moment when Bannister Carlton nearly captured Thomas Jefferson, who was
now governor of Virginia, missing him by just 15 minutes.
So we all know that the coming Siege of Yorktown will end the war.
And as Cornwallis settled into Virginia, various American and French leaders started to recognise that
he was offering them just such a golden opportunity.
But it would appear that the one guy who was absolutely not recognising this opportunity was George
Washington. From the earliest days of the war, Washington had been convinced that in the end, it would
all come down to New York City was one of the reasons he had maintained such a steadfast vigil all these
years. Since 1776, that had been a major base of operations for the British.
And since Clinton took over the central base of the British Army, capturing New York City was obviously
the thing. So after the French fleet was freed from Newport, it seemed to Washington like he was finally
circling the drain on this obsession, then roshambo told him that their second French fleet was down
in the West Indies, was probably about to come north and help so it's all falling into place, right.
But roshambo did not really like the look of trying to take New York City, nor did some of Washington
subordinates but the general was utterly fixated on the idea and kept pressing roshambo to mass the
French fleet to New York as soon as possible. In fine French diplomatic fashion, roshambo sues Washington
with carefully worded assurances, all the while, relaying messages to his French admirals that Cornwallis
was a sitting duck in Virginia, that that would be the target.
He just had to talk Washington into it. There has been some historical debate about this over the years,
but Ron Chernow, his recent biography of Washington makes it pretty clear that Washington Didn't get
religion on Yorktown until the very last minute. And once he got it he got it.
Especially after he was told that Yorktown was where Cornwallis was entrenching because he himself had
once warned a subordinate American officer earlier in the war, not to dig in at Yorktown because it
would be too easy to capture. Washington's fixation with New York though did pave the way to victory
at Yorktown in one important way. It convinced Henry Clinton not to send more reinforcements to Cornwallis
because he was convinced Washington was about to hit him now was because Washington was convinced Washington
was about to hit him, if that makes sense. In the end, the decision to pivot to Virginia appears to
have been presented to Washington as a fait accompli in mid August roshambo told Washington that 1000
apologies, but it seems that Admiral de grace has made up his mind to make for Chesapeake Bay.
I know, I know. But what can you do? Do his very great credit though.
Washington swallowed this and turned it into one of his great triumphs, the lightning march to Yorktown.
Just a few days after receiving the news, he sent parties out to start making it look for all the world
like he was about to launch an amphibious attack on Staten Island.
Then Washington broke his men into three columns and marched them at staggered intervals into New Jersey.
All of this further convinced Clinton and attack was coming.
And he did not realise until way too late that Washington wasn't coming back.
The Americans linked up with the French in Princeton, and we're through Philadelphia before Clinton
understood what was really going on. Over the next three weeks, Washington and his army managed to cover
450 miles of not especially easy terrain in some pretty rotten heat.
It was one of those astonishing bits of logistical genius that Washington seemed to deliver effortlessly,
and it gave the Allied American and French forces the Head Start they needed to squeeze Cornwallis before
Clinton could respond. By the time they were making their final approach.
The French fleets had mast at the mouth of Chesapeake Bay and run off the outnumbered British fleet
who said oh wow, there's a lot of UC later. Washington road ahead to meet with the grace and plan the
operation. It was somewhat chagrin that Doug Ross was only promising to stay until November the first
that turned out to be more than enough time. While Washington was on the road, and general green down
in South Carolina finally came down from the hills he had been camped in for the summer and made a march
of his own towards Charleston. He was now leading 2200 men, an equal mix of Continentals, militia man
irregular forces, and just you know guys with muskets.
On September the eighth, they surprise the British Field Army camped at Utah springs about 30 miles
northwest of Charleston. The surprise British were quickly pushed back and confusion.
But instead of holding together and finishing the fight, the Americans like I say a pretty uneven mix
of characters decided to plunder the British camp instead.
This allowed the British to regroup and come charging back in to drive off the mob of looters.
But now that he knew Greene's army was in the area, there was nothing for Lord rudden to do, but pull
his forces back into Charleston and wait for further orders.
He would still be waiting for those orders when he got the letter that the war was over.
Backup in Virginia, the combined French and American armies now numbering about 16,000 made the final
advance on Yorktown on September the 28th. Cornwallis initially had both an outer and inner line of
defence, but he quickly abandoned the outer line and pulled all the troops he had now somewhere around
8000. Inside the city, Washington quite rightly deferred to his French allies who were well trained
in the art of siege craft. Digging began immediately for the steady advance of parallels.
Through the first week of October, the Americans and French dug towards the city than the artillery
got set up and the shelling began making life absolutely miserable for everyone inside Yorktown.
During these days, Cornwallis seemed curiously inactive.
He had set up shopping a grotto that served as a natural bunker and was simply in during the shelling.
What was going through his mind we'll never know. But he might have been expecting reinforcements from
Clinton to come bail him out. But those reinforcements would never come.
On October the 14th, the second parallel was completed and the Americans launched a nitrate on some
British positions. morale inside Yorktown was now gone.
Cornwallis had one available option now, and that was to ferry his men across the James River and maybe
make a run for it. But after he put the first 1000 men across a storm kicked up and put a stop to it.
Or Wallace now saw the writing on the wall. And the next day he sent an emissary over to Washington
to talk terms or law was asked to be allowed to surrender with full military honours, but Washington
replied that the British would receive the same honours the American troops that Charleston had been
allowed, which is to say no honours at all. At 11am on the morning of October 19 1781 8000, British marched
out of Yorktown through a double line of American and French troops.
As the British March, they tried to focus all their attention on the French line, and pretend like the
Americans weren't even there, until the Continental band started playing Yankee Doodle Dandy to get
their attention. Then, in another calculated snub, Cornwallis himself refused to come in person, sending
a subordinate along to surrender his sword, recognising a slap in the face when he saw it, Washington
refused to take the sword, and directed one of his own subordinates to go pick it up.
It was a bitter piece that was made that day, but it was a piece.
Now, of course, the victory Yorktown did not necessarily have to end the war.
Clinton was still up in New York, the Navy was still out there.
And it was technically possible that the British could just send over more troops and more ships.
That certainly what King George the Third wanted to do.
But the reaction of Lord North the news of the surrender pretty much summed it up.
Oh, God, he said, it's all over. It was hopeless to try to carry on and everyone knew it.
The time had come to concede the war, settled the thing and move on.
Next week, we will discuss what it would mean to settle the thing.
A formal peace treaty would have to be brokered between Britain and her now former colonies, the last
of the British troops would have to be removed.And then of course, the Americans would have to figure
out what to do their newfound independence.