Hello and welcome to Revolutions.
Episode 21, The Guns of Ticonderoga.
So we left off last time with Britain and
her American colonies, more or less on the brink
of war and indeed over the winner of
seventeen seventy four, seventy five, there were
multiple opportunities for the
war to break out.
But being civilized 18th century gentleman, everyone
decided it was best to wait for
spring to really get down to business, the
various opportunities for the war to break out
and indeed the one that
finally did the trick.
We're all related to General Thomas Gages attempt to
bring all the guns and powder in New
England. Under his control town, militias would
often store their guns and ammunition in
collective caches.
And the winter of seventeen seventy four seventy
five was basically a race to see who
could withdraw the powder from those caches
first without provoking the other side to
start shooting. So prior to Lexington and Concord,
there were three big incidents of this
type, the first known as the powder
alarm, occurred on September the 1st.
Seventeen seventy four.
So this is actually just before the
first Continental Congress met, the British regulars
were able to secretly and peacefully secure what
was left in the Powder House northwest
of Boston the next day.
Thousands of militiamen turned out fueled on by
exaggerated rumors that the war was on.
But when the rumors didn't
pan out, they all dispersed.
The second incident, known as the
Portsmouth Alarm, involved the colonial militiamen
actively seizing the cache at Fort William and
Mary in mid-December with shots fired in
the process, arguably the first shots
fired in the Revolutionary War.
Finally, we have the Salem
alarm in February 17.
Seventy five, which ended when the British regiment
sent to lock up the sale and powder
ran into a wall of militia that
forced them to turn back empty handed.
Like I say, any one of these could have
turned ugly enough to have really marked the
beginning of the war. But in the
end, the peace held until April 17.
Seventy five when the conquered powder
was next on the list.
Which brings us to Lexington, Concord and the shot
heard round the world, which I am not
going to talk about right now.
As some of you know, in the interim, between
the end of the history of Rome and the
beginning of revolutions, I was in grad
school where I took a documentary filmmaking
class, the final project for which wound up
being a video about Lexington, Concord and
the shot heard round the world.
So in lieu of talking about it here,
I have embedded that video at Revolutions podcast,
Dotcom. But before you watch it, here
is what you need to know.
First, the video functions as a pilot episode
for a proposed series called Legend Has It
that compares historical myth
to historical reality.
So that's the thematic framework.
Second, it is in every way a student film.
The production values are low, particularly
when it comes to the audio.
Third, there are a few little flubs along the
way, like when at one point I accidentally
refer to Longfellow as Wadsworth Fourth.
As the sleep deprivation mounted,
the tone became increasingly silly.
And there will be, I'm sure, things that either
come too fast to be caught or just make
no sense at all. It will, for example,
help if you've seen the old nineteen seventies
Incredible Hulk series, and I'm not kidding
about that fifth, I think that's it.
So enjoy. That's all in good fun.
So let's say we don't take too critical a
sledgehammer to it, but that's where you need
to go. For all of the endlessly fascinating
details about Lexington, Concord and the shot
heard round the world. For our purposes right now,
though, what you need to know is that
the quote unquote battles at Lexington and
Concord marked the beginning of the American
Revolutionary War or if you prefer,
the American War of independence.
Now, these skirmishes were easily packaged
by colonial leaders as purely defensive
engagement, which was important to keep moderate
patriots from falling into the loyalist
camp. But unfortunately for those concerned with
such optics, the initiative taken by a
couple of hundred zealous militia men in upstate
New York could enjoy no such packaging.
I am talking here about Ethan Allen, Benedict
Arnold and the capture of Fort Ticonderoga.
Fort Ticonderoga had been built on the southwest
side of Lake Champlain by the French and
seventeen fifty five, but it was seized by
the British a few years later by seventeen
seventy five. The fort was in a
sorry state garrison by two officers.
Forty eight soldiers and
some dilapidated walls.
Early in May, the hulking, boisterous but
surprisingly intellectual Ethan Allen got it
into his head to make a play at the fort
as it lay on the most direct route for a
possible British invasion from Canada, or, conversely,
might serve as a useful staging
ground for any invasion by
the Americans into Canada.
Ethan Allen was originally from Connecticut, but
in the years before the revolution, he
had made a name for himself as the
leader of independent minded settlers in the New
Hampshire grant.
What is today in the state of Vermont?
New York claimed the territory, but the
settlers refused to recognize their authority.
Colonel Allen, as he was then popularly known,
actually carried a price on his head by
the government of New York for his work
leading the Green Mountain Boys, a well-organized
militia focused almost exclusively on convincing New
York that it wasn't worth the
trouble to try and govern them.
So when the fighting broke out down
in Massachusetts, the Green Mountain boys, though
small, were one of the most experienced
and disciplined of the colonial militias.
And Allen aimed to turn their
skills now against the British.
But Ethan Allen was not the only one who
had his eye on Ticonderoga, the other man who
was at that same moment itching to take
the fort was the now infamous Benedict Arnold.
Also originally from Connecticut, the 34 year
old Arnold came from wealthy Rhode Island
stock. He was athletic, charming and pretty
uniformly successful at whatever he put his
mind to. He was an early
and active supporter of colonial resistance.
And when the storm clouds really started
brewing, he was elected to the Connecticut
militia. In March 1775, after Lexington
and Concord, he approached the Massachusetts
Committee of Safety, which had been set up
as a sort of patriot shadow government and
asked for a commission to go organize
and capture Ticonderoga, a commission he was
granted. Arnold then struck north, and on May
the 10th he came across Ethan Allen and
Allen's two hundred odd troops
promptly declared himself in command.
Allen, of course, scoffed at this, but luckily
both men wanted the same thing and wanted
it as soon as possible.
So they agreed to
immediately attack the fort.
Now there is no such thing
as a Battle of Ticonderoga.
The garrison was literally surprised in their beds
and outnumbered four to one put up no
resistance. The garrison commander quickly negotiated
the surrender and safe passage for
his men and the twenty four
women and children living with them.
So without firing a shot, the fort was
secure, though its strategic value was never quite
what it might have been.
The capture of Ticonderoga was absolutely critical to
the early days of the war for one
very important reason.
When Allen and Arnold took stock, they
discovered that Ticonderoga held a fairly enormous
cache of artillery, including small four pound
guns, mortars, howitzers and huge twenty
four pound guns, plus ammunition
for all of it.
As we are about to see, these are the
guns that Washington will use to fortify Dorchester
and drive the British out of Boston.
Coincidentally enough, May the 10th also happened
to be the day that the Second
Continental Congress convened
in Philadelphia.
Now, as you will recall, the first Congress had
disbanded back in October, 1774, set on a
plan of economic resistance.
The second Congress was probably planned to do
nothing more than check back in and get
geared up for the non exportation phase of
the plan that would begin in September.
But of course, fate had now
dealt them a very different hand.
Many of the delegates at the second Congress
were holdovers from the first, but there
were now a few new faces, including
John Hancock, the recently returned to America,
Benjamin Franklin and before too long,
the young Virginia intellectual Thomas Jefferson.
This second, Congress had to deal first and
foremost with the question of how to respond
to the fighting in Massachusetts.
It was almost universally agreed that they should
help organize an armed defense of the
colonies. But to what end was now?
The great question is this merely to secure
a just reconciliation or are we embarked on
the road to independence?
This, for example, is where John Dickinson
morphs from radical to conservative, not
because he changed, but because the times changed
and he is about to become the leading
opponent of American independence.
The Congress spent the first few weeks of
its life debating what it meant by armed
defense, are we simply going to coordinate action by
the militias or are we going to form
an independent, let's call
it a continental army?
In the midst of this news from Ticonderoga
arrived, which made it harder to argue that
the colonies were just defending themselves
and helped introduce some friction as
Ticonderoga was in New York and no one from
New York had even been told about the
operation. That was, oh, by the way, led by a
man they were trying to throw in jail, but
they all mostly got over it.
And by the end of May, a consensus was
forming around the idea of creating and supplying
an independent continental army to first augment
and then hopefully supersede the local
militias. There were a few men present who
had their eye on commanding this new army,
most famously John Hancock.
But there wasn't really any question
who the commission would go to.
Absolutely had to be George Washington, who
knew enough about the role Providence had
ordained for him to show up at the
first session of Congress in full military uniform.
OK, so George Washington, George Washington was
born in Virginia in February 17, thirty
two into a gentry family of the middle tier
doing well, but not in that upper crust of
the Virginia planter aristocracy.
His father died when he was a teenager, so
it fell to his older brother, Lawrence, to
become his main guiding influence.
It was Lawrence's connection to the
enormously powerful Fairfax family that got
Washington his first job as a county
surveyor at the age of 17.
I must, of course, mention that, yes, this is
the same Fairfax family as our old friend,
Sir Thomas Fairfax, whose title had passed to
a cousin after his death in sixteen seventy
one. And then it was handed down to the
line to the sixth Earl of Fairfax, who pretty
much owned more land in Virginia than anyone.
This same Fairfax clan will also provide young
George with his first love, Sally Fairfax.
So connections between
our revolutions abound.
Anyway, when Lawrence died in 1752, George inherited
his estate, including a spot on the
Potomac called Mount Vernon.
Young George soon developed a passion for the
two things that would come to dominate his
life land speculation and military service, he finagled
a commission as a major in the
Virginia militia. And as tensions with France mounted,
he wound up being the guy assigned
to head a small expedition in 1753 into the
Ohio Valley to politely tell the French to
get the hell out. The next year, he
was ordered back into the valley with vague
instructions to defend the frontier, and he
wound up encountering and getting whipped
pretty badly by a mix of French and
Indians, the small but thoroughly, let's call it
instructive battle of Fort Necessity.
When the French and Indian War finally broke
out, Washington was present at but managed
to survive Braddock's disastrous march in 1755,
despite the bullets flying every which
way, a lucky habit Washington
would enjoy his entire life.
Tales of his various adventures, though they
were not all that successful, circulated
through the colonies and Washington became the
closest thing America had to a military
hero. This earned him a commission as a
colonel, though critically, this was all still
within the ranks of the
militia, not the regular army.
And it was around this point that he
really started to chafe under the presumed
superiority of regular officers, like when, for
example, some captain tried to give him
orders. He spent the rest of the war
leading a thousand militiamen defending the Virginia
frontier, a period during which he developed
his rather intent loathing of militiamen who
he would forever consider unreliable,
undisciplined, insubordinate and cowardly because
he spent as much time tracking down
deserters as he did fighting the French.
After the war, the Washington Mary, the
enormously wealthy widow, Martha Costus, which is
how he pole vaulted from the middling rank to
one of the richest men in the American
colonies and how he became the owner
of well over two hundred slaves.
As the prerevolutionary pressure built in Washington
was focused mainly on running his
estates, acquiring new property and
keeping his creditors at bay.
Because, like all good Virginia planters,
he ran on borrowed money.
He also took up his place in the
Virginia House of Burgesses and long dissatisfied with
British arrogance, both
militarily and economically.
He soon fell in with
the more radically inclined leaders.
And as you'll recall, he was a prime
mover behind the non importation response to the
Townsend acts as the crisis
reached its boiling point.
He was appalled by the intolerable acts, was
a delegate to the first Continental Congress
and is now a delegate to the Second
Continental Congress, though he will soon be leaving
for Boston as the Congress duly bestowed upon
America's most famous soldier the title of
commander in chief of all colonial forces.
In the meantime, the so-called triumvirate of
reputation had already arrived in Boston.
The three men who will wind up
leading the British campaigns during the Revolutionary
War, generals William Henry Clinton and John Burgoyne,
who we will deal with in turn as
they each move to center stage.
For the moment, however, General Thomas
Gage is still in charge.
And after Lexington and Concord, Gaige, in
consultation with his new military advisers,
had studied the options and by the end
of May determined they would fortify the heights
around Boston and plan to
begin in earnest in mid-June.
But word soon leaked to the Committee of
Safety, and they ordered Artemus Ward, farmer and
veteran of the French and Indian War and
the man now leading the combined New England
militia stationed in Cambridge to go occupy
Bunker Hill and Dorchester Heights, which
command of the north and
south of Boston, respectively.
There is a map of colonial Boston posted
at Revolutions podcast Dotcom, so you can follow
along at home, not Dorchester Heights will
remain for the moment off the board.
But on June 16th, Ward ordered William Prescott
to take just over a thousand men from
Cambridge over to occupy Bunker Hill, which, if you
don't have the map in front of you,
was located on a peninsula that hangs out
over Boston that also contains the now empty
city of Charlestown.
The men weren't ready to go until nine p.m.
And so this all winds up being a night
operation when they got out to the peninsula.
Prescott decided to fortify
Breed's Hill instead.
It was slightly lower, but better
situated to repel a British advance.
The men spent all night digging, and when Dawn
broke, they had a pretty nice redoubt in
place. When the British Navy caught sight
of the rebel fortifications the next morning,
they opened fire. But the angle was
all wrong and they did minimal damage.
That said, by noon on June the 17th,
the militiamen were exhausted and discouraged that
they had not been relieved yet.
And despite their good work on Breed's
Hill, all likely flanking routes were still
perilously unguarded.
And Prescott begged Ward to send more men.
Meanwhile, General Gage, awoken by the Navy
blasts, selected the east side of the
peninsula as the best place to land,
which was all well and good.
Except that meant waiting for the tide.
And the fifteen hundred regulars led by William
Howe, didn't put to shore until around
one o'clock. More shelling of the rebels
followed, as did further reinforcements for both
sides. How then divided his troops, now
numbering over 2000 into three columns designed
to envelop the defences on Breed's Hill, with
the left serving as a diversion to allow
the main flanking move to
come over from the right.
But unfortunately for the British, not only was
the ground more difficult than they were
prepared for, but the two hundred militiamen
guarding the hastily fortified fence line,
guarding the right, waited until the approaching
regulars were just 50 yards away and
then started blasting, killing at least
a hundred pretty much instantly.
And the British were forced to fall back.
And this would be where I mention the most
famous order given in the battle of the
militiamen, not fire until you can see the
whites of their eyes to protect their limited
ammunition. But this order has been
variously attributed to different officers at
different points in the battle and was
probably never even set at all.
So they're. A second attempt soon followed,
again, aiming simultaneously at the fence line
and the redoubt, but again, the approaching
regulars marching smartly were wide open
targets for the colonials as how elected not to
go by the book and attack in a narrow
column because this is not supposed
to be that hard anyway.
The second attempt also failed, but by now,
Prescott and his men were basically out of
ammunition. So a half an hour
later, reinforced by another 400 men.
How ordered the 3rd assault?
No more messing around.
Just a strong push right up Breed's Hill.
It was a grisly business, but it did
the trick, especially since the Americans were now
officially out of ammunition.
The regulars poured into the redoubt and the
militiamen scrambled back to Bunker Hill to
regroup as the redoubt was taken.
The revolution gets its first
martyred war hero as Dr.
Joseph Warren, author of The Suffolk Resolves and
serving as a common soldier because his
officers commission hadn't come through
yet, was shot and killed.
Unfortunately, again, for the British, the taking
of the redoubt had broken up their
ranks, and by the time they were organized
enough to press on, the remaining militiamen
had elected to withdraw from the peninsula
altogether, which meant that the British won
the battle always and forever, erroneously
called the battle of Bunker Hill.
But the body count soon told a somber story.
Two hundred regulars killed
with another 800 wounded.
Henry Clinton noted wryly in his diary that
a few more such victories would have surely
put an end to British Dominion in America.
After the battle, the two sides settled back
into their respective positions a few weeks
later, July the 2nd, to be exact.
Washington arrived to take on overall command
of the army, which now numbered about
16000, though only about fourteen
thousand were fit for duty.
The British, meanwhile, now have at the moment
about six thousand in Boston, a number
that could grow to nine
thousand by early 1776.
But although the colonial turnout was pretty
good, it was also composed entirely of
Washington's arch enemy, the
local militia company.
These guys were just generally
disrespectful of normal army life.
They came and went as they please,
and they elected their own officers.
So good luck keeping anyone in line.
The irony, of course, is that these guys
pretty much embodied the kind of freedom and
liberty the war was supposed to be about.
And Washington had no time or
patience for any of it.
He started issuing all kinds of orders
against things like drinking and gambling and
swearing. And any officer or enlisted man who
failed to live up to his standards was
simply summarily dismissed as he
beat this army into shape.
I mean, literally beat slashings
were an everyday occurrence.
Washington also strengthen the fortifications around
Boston, which were at that point
frankly embarrassing as Washington got to work up
a New England led Congress down in
Philadelphia, continued work on building a
justification for their actions, though they
sent out somewhat mixed messages despite the fact
that they were drafted by the same two
men, John Dickinson and the
newly arrived Thomas Jefferson.
Passed it almost the same time we have on
the one hand, the olive branch petition, a last
attempt at peacefully negotiating away the
economic underpinnings of the conflict.
And on the other, we have the declaration of
the causes and necessity of taking up arms,
which is hopefully pretty self-explanatory.
In the former, Jefferson's draft was softened by
Dickinson, who still clung to the dream
of reconciliation, while in the latter,
Dickinson actually made Jefferson's draft blunter
and more direct because he may have been worried
he was about to lose all influence if he
didn't do something to prove that his
heart was still in this thing.
And he did technically believe that the
colonists were right to defend themselves, just
not the independent was the aim.
But whatever hope of
negotiated reconciliation still lingered.
Died when King George refused to even
receive the olive branch petition and parliament
officially declared the
colonies in rebellion.
Back up in Boston by now, both sides were
well dug in and both firmly under the command
of their new respective leaders, General Washington
for the Americans and William Howard
for the British, who took over from the
now thoroughly discredited General Gage in late
September 1775.
Now, William Howe is
a pretty interesting dude.
He was one of three brothers, all
of whom had distinguished military careers.
And indeed, his older brother is Admiral Richard
Howe, who will serve as the supreme
naval commander during the war.
So really, for the next couple of years, the
British war effort is in the hands of the
Howe brothers and the Howe brothers were wait
for it entirely sympathetic to the American
colonies. They were pretty staunch Whigs who
opposed most of the ministry's policies in
America and really super
oppose the intolerable acts.
In fact, Admiral Richard Howe had initiated
last minute back channel dealings with
Benjamin Franklin to try to avert war.
But when war came, neither could refuse
the service they had been called to.
And so when William Howe took over for
Gaige, his aim was to win the war.
But as we will see, there will be more
than a few missed opportunities along the way,
which some have attributed to House preference
for comfortable in action, some to his
unwillingness to waste troops, especially after
what he saw at Bunker Hill.
But what I sometimes suspect is that there was a
desire and how not just to win the war,
but also the peace that would
follow the inevitable British victory.
And waging two brutal war would unjustly punish
the colonists for defending a cause that
Howe himself was entirely sympathetic to.
As the autumn of seventeen seventy five set
in, everyone was still staring at each other
and occasionally chatting with each other across
the lines, but by now, Washington faced
the great problem that would plague
him for the entire war.
All those militia enlistments that were due
to expire on January the 1st.
And none of those guys had even
hinted that they planned to stick around.
The general feeling being that we've done our
bit, now it's time for somebody else to
take over. So as he's trying to hold the
siege together, Washington is also about to have
to completely swap out his army and, of
course, lose whatever training may have sunk in
with all those lashings.
As the commander in chief stared down this
problem, one of his new subordinates was
staring down a problem of his own, one that
would be just as critical to winning Boston
as the problem of
refilling the American ranks.
And November 17, seventy five, Washington sent
the let's call him plump Henry Knox,
twenty five year old bookseller, but now
self-taught artillery expert up to Fort
Ticonderoga to figure out how to move the
guns to Boston, a problem made nearly
unsolvable because of the fact that there
were no roads linking the two.
But on December the 5th, Knox set off
into the snowy wilderness with forty four guns,
both light and heavy, 14 mortars, one howitzer
and all the ammunition to run them,
totaling some 60 tons of material.
It has gone down in history
as the noble train of artillery.
And over the next ten weeks, Knox's men used
first barges and then oxen pulled sleds to
literally drag the guns.
S finally arriving in the American
camp on January the 27th.
It was a bona fide miracle.
In the meantime, Washington was busy reforming his
army spirits were still pretty high at
this point, and the militias had managed to
recruit and or retain 7000 men, while the
first batch of official continental soldiers showed
up totaling some 9000 men, which was
good, though it fell well
short of the target.
Twenty thousand. Washington was utterly sick to death
of the siege at this point and soon
proposed an audacious attack
on the unsuspecting British.
But his war council talked him down
and suggested instead tightening the noose by
fortifying Dorchester Heights with the
recently arrived guns because inexplicably,
neither side yet controlled this
all important high ground.
But trying to occupy the heights
was not without its own risks.
The job would have to be done silently and
all in one night, or the Americans would be
wide open for an attack by the British.
Not only that, but the ground
was too frozen to dig into.
So how would they even defend
themselves once they got there?
After working through the logistics of the
thing, Washington and his officers finally
determined that, yes, it was doable and yes,
they were going to go for it.
On the night of March the 2nd, 1776, they
let fly a short bombardment to give the British
something to think about. The next night,
both sides started shelling each other.
And the night after that March the 4th,
the shelling went into overdrive, just as
Washington hoped, because as this artillery
skirmish was playing out, twelve hundred
workmen and eight hundred infantrymen hurried up
the heights and got to work.
Now, they had already constructed above
ground fortifications and worked furiously but
silently through the night, successfully constructing
two redoubts and mounting the
biggest guns before dawn, according
to the old legend.
When how woke up the next morning, he was
amazed and said, My God, these fellows have
done more in one night than I could
make my army do in three months.
And it's doubtful that he actually said it.
But the sentiment feels about right.
With the American artillery looming over them,
the British position in Boston became
untenable, but in the end, this was all
possibly more embarrassing and annoying to now
than it was a devastating strategic blow.
And many historians suspect that he
had already decided to evacuate Boston.
So what the fortification of Dorchester Heights really
meant was that he could no longer
leave on his own terms.
Indeed, how now concluded that he couldn't leave
without a fight and he planned a full
scale assault of the American
position on the right.
But a debilitating blizzard cancelled the
operation at the last minute.
And how took the hint.
On March 17th, all the British troops were
out of Boston and loaded on to their
transport, where they sailed
away for Halifax.
Washington led a triumphal procession into the
city to wild jubilation in the streets.
So all things considered, it had been a
pretty great year for the American patriots, they
had proven their resolve at Lexington and
Concord, proving their courage at Bunker Hill
and now force the British
out of Boston completely.
But of course, 1776 will not prove nearly
so glorious, nor was 1775 so uniformly
successful. So next week, we will backtrack a
little and cover the debacle that was the
invasion of Canada and then head into the
auspicious year of 1776, which will see the
colonies boldly declare independence and then
get trounced repeatedly in the field,
making some doubt whether they could
back up their lofty rhetoric.