This week's episode is brought to you by audible. Audible is the internet's leading provider of audio
entertainment with over 150,000 titles to choose from.
So when you're done with this episode, go to audible podcast.com forward slash revolutions, that again,
audible podcast.com forward slash revolutions. By going to that address, you qualify for a free book
download when you sign up for a 30 day trial membership, there is no obligation to continue the service
and you can cancel anytime and keep the free book.
You can also keep going with one of the monthly subscription options and get great deals on all future
audio book purchases. And this time, I'm going to stray a bit off topic because as you history buffs
know, we are at this moment in the middle of the 100th anniversary of the beginning of World War One.
So I cannot let the opportunity pass, recommend the greatness that is the guns of August by Barbara
Tuchman. It's just the best book on the beginning of World War One.
And since we are in this Centennial moment, it's a good time to finally pick it up.
So when you're done with this episode, go to audible podcast.com Ford slash revolutions, so that they
know who sent you.Hello, and welcome to revolutions Episode 3.1, the three estates we come now to the
greatest revolution of them all, the French Revolution, the standard by which all other revolutions
are measured. It was one of the most important events in the history of the world, and is widely pointed
to as marking the beginning of the modern era. Since its passing, it has also become one of the most
bought over pieces of intellectual real estate among scholars of all disciplines.
History, obviously, but also economics and sociology and philosophy and political science.
Everyone has something to say about the French Revolution.
And just to keep things interesting, there is almost no agreement about what its causes were, what its
consequences were nor even what actually happened.
Probably the most influential grand theory of the French Revolution came from the Marxists, who painted
a deliciously plausible theory that during the 1700s, the pro capitalist French bourgeoisie acquired
a majority share of the nation's wealth, while simultaneously being denied access to political power
within an archaic feudal system later dubbed the Austrian regime.
So the turbulence of the revolution was simply the obsolete political structure being forced into alignment
with the modern economic structure in Marxist history, the French Revolution is the great bourgeois
revolution that both destroyed the feudalism of the past and set the stage for the socialism of the future.
Like I say, this is a deliciously plausible theory, easy to hold in your head.
And in broad terms, it looks an awful lot like what happened.
But while Marxist theory thrives in the big picture, it usually gets beaten up pretty bad when the details
are scrutinised. That's when we find out that big chunks of the nobility were involved in various modernising
and capitalist enterprises. And far from wanting to tear down the feudal apparatus members of the bourgeoisie
turned out to be some of the fiercest defenders of seigneury, all dues and noble privileges, because
they had just purchased access to those senatorial dues and noble privileges, and wanted to protect
their investments. Not all of them did this mind you, but some of them did.
Certainly enough to make the story of a battle between one class representing the old ways, and another
class representing the new ways fall apart, which is kind of a pity because it's a great theory.
But after all, the revisionism and post revisionism and repost revisionism revolution has been stripped
of all order, and frankly returned to its native state of pure chaos.
But before we can get into the endlessly fascinating and occasionally terrifying march of the French
Revolution, we must as usual lay our groundwork. So the rest of this week's episode will be taken up
with a rundown of the people who made up pre revolutionary France, taking as our framework the famous
three estates. We'll start with the lowly peasant, and wind up with the allegedly absolute monarch of
this allegedly absolute monarchy, King Louie the 16th.
The next week, we will walk through the mess of political, economic, cultural and religious problems
that the Austrian regime was facing. When Comptroller General cologne told the king in August 1786,
that unless drastic financial reforms were initiated, a monarchy was going to go broke.
On the eve of the Revolution, the population of France was somewhere around 27 million.
So right away, it's worth noting just in terms of scale, we are an order of magnitude beyond the English
and American Revolutions, both of which involve millions of people, rather than 10s of millions of people.
These 10s of millions mostly lived in rural areas and were tied to the land.
The rest lived in small towns, a few larger provincial cities.
And then of course, Paris, which was not just the preeminent city in France, but was in many ways the
preeminent city in Europe. Regardless of where they live, though, the French people were divided up
into the famous three estates, the division still lingering from the old mediaeval days when society
could be separated into those who prayed, those who fought and those who worked.
The first estate, those who prayed was the clergy.
Second estate, those who fought was the nobility. And the third estate, those who worked was everyone
else. That is to say something like 95% of the population.
The vast majority of the third estate, and about four fifths of the total population of France were
peasants. These peasants can be divided up into three basic subgroups at the bottom where your landless
peasants are forced to become migrant workers or day labourers to stay alive.
In many areas, these landless peasants could pick up work and say textile manufacturing, as pre industrial
France relied on accumulating the products of 1000s of individual homes rather than consolidating workers
in a single factory. But as we'll discuss a bit next week, on the eve of the revolution, these pitiful
folks were dealing with the terrible conundrum of price inflation that was not being matched by wage
increases, so even those who found work can often not afford the most basic necessities of life.
They might then turn to professional begging, petty theft, and outright banditry as circumstances dictated.
Above the landless peasants, you had peasants who owned or leased a little land of their own.
But one of the problems of French agriculture was that the land was divided up into these little tiny
plots that could barely sustain a family, let alone produce a surplus for market.
Numerous foreign observers passing through 18th century France commented on just how backward and inefficient
French agriculture was, but the North was starting to get into larger scale production.
The dream of the small holding peasants was to rise up into the ranks of the third and smallest of the
peasant subgroups. Independent farmers, who own not only enough land to sustain themselves, but also
provide jobs for the rural workers and loan out equipment to their poor neighbours.
These operators were generally loathed and envied by the lower order peasants, who lived in fear of
seeing their own precious holdings gobbled up if they ever fell behind on alone.
while simultaneously aspiring to join the ranks of the independent farmers they feared.
Leaving behind the peasants in the countryside, the remainder of the three estates lived in urban areas,
though calling them urban is not quite right, as most held less than 2000 people, and only a few cities
exceeded 50,000, like Leone in the east, or say down along the Mediterranean, or Bordeaux on the Atlantic
coast, another 650,000 jam themselves into Paris. Inside the towns and cities, we first find the corollary
of the poor peasant in the poor, unskilled labour.
These folks are the ones who make getting an accurate gauge on just how many peasants there were difficult,
as they were often seasonal migrants from the countryside or relatives of poor agricultural workers
looking for a better or at least a different opportunity in the towns.
The best job these poor unskilled workers could hope for would be as a servant in the homes of the better
off families. But barring that, they were forced to rely on the uncertainties of day labour and temporary
work projects. They crammed into terrible housing, and often wound up in line for charity from local
religious orders. Above the unskilled workers, we find not surprisingly the skilled workers.
The organisation of the skilled workers was itself one of the little tributaries feeding into the great
river that is the causes of the French Revolution.
Because the guild system in all of its restrictive glory, was still in full effect.
apprentices were a little more than indentured servants forced to serve some specified time say seven
years before they were allowed to become journeyman.
At which point they often took to the road to ply their trade and get into nasty fights with local competitors
or other journeymen they happen to run across. After whatever arbitrary time was up, they were allowed
to become masters buying their way into the club and settling down to set up a permanent shop, taking
on apprentices and starting the whole cycle over again.
The Guild system was a source of constant frustration for those not directly profiting from it.
And as the 1700s progressed, an economic theory turned to free trade.
The continued existence of the mediaeval guild system was an affront to thinking men everywhere.
It is also worth mentioning that it will be from the ranks of these urban workers both skilled and unskilled
that the famous son que la will come storming out of as the revolution picks up steam on cue lot, meaning
those who did not wear the silk knee breeches favoured by the upper classes.
Above the skilled workers, we move into the ranks of the secure urban elite, the guys who did favour
silk knee breeches, known to us as the bourgeoisie.
Now, bourgeoisie is a pretty nebulous concept. And in strict Marxist terminology, they are simply the
owners of the means of production, that is the merchants and industrialists and bankers.
But in a broader sense, the bourgeoisie also included the middle class professionals, lawyers and doctors
and men of letters. Collectively, they were one of the fastest growing demographic groups in 18th century
France, and now held a large portion of the nation's wealth.
But critically, since we are still living in the Austrian regime, if you were ambitious, you generally
did not funnel your money back into the trades that had enriched you.
Instead, you aimed at buying your way into the nobility.
So you transfer the money you made in the grubby business of trade into land on the one hand, or venal
office on the other. land has, of course been the great marker of wealth and status for, let's say,
the entire history of civilization. So I don't think that needs much explanation side for mentioning
that when the up and coming bourgeoisie bought the land, they were quite a bit more diligent about enforcing
whatever feudal claims could be made on the tenants claims that the former noble owners had often long
since forgotten about. And in many provinces, complaints about the new bourgeois landlords far outnumbered
complaints about the old aristocratic landlords. The other great investment opportunity was venal office,
and venal office is simply a government office that is purchased rather than appointed.
They were dreamed up first by Louis the 14th, but then massively expanded by his successor, Louie the
15th. As an easy way to generate revenue for the state without forcing the Royal ministry to levy new
taxes which the nobility would no doubt resist. the eve of the revolution nearly every one of the 70,000
offices of government was a venal office, most of them actually did tie into a real job.
But some of the most coveted like that of King secretary was simply an empty title that carried with
it certain privileges, all kinds of privileges. Well, many of them came with a promise of ennoblement.
Most had to be held for a few successive generations for the nobleman to kick in, but some including
the aforementioned Office of King secretary, brought in nobleman immediately.
These offices also usually carried packs exemptions of various shapes and sizes, because as we'll discuss
a bit more next week, pre revolutionary France operated on the rather upside down principle that the
better off you were, the less you paid in taxes. Over the years, these offices became a form of property
in themselves. And as the ranks of the bourgeoisie expanded, the prices of the vino offices Rose with
demand. By the late 1780, something close to a billion lever was tied up in venal office.
And yes, that is an insane amount of money. At the very tippy top of the third estate was a little group
who quote, lived nobley that is they no longer even worked at a profession, but instead lived off land
rents or other investments. The reason this group was so small, was because if you had acquired the
means to live nobley, you were probably in the process of buying your way into the nobility, that is
the second estate and leaving the ranks of the third estate behind for good.
So with the help of some venal office, it's time to move up into the second estate, the nobility.
By this point, the population of the nobility was somewhere between 120,400 1000 Records being patchy
and often unreliable, since there were more than a few forge claims out there.
This little click and we're talking no more than one to 2% of the population owned outright a quarter
to a third of all the land in France, and held feudal rights over the rest that is the right to collect
certain taxes the right to force tenants to use your mills and wine presses at whatever arbitrary price
you've set. They also openly owned a controlling interest in almost all the non trading commercial pursuits
like mining and metallurgy and less openly owned a controlling interest in most of the trading industry.
Using surrogates in the third estate to skirt prohibitions on the nobles engaging in trade.
So far from resisting the evolution from feudalism to capitalism.
The nobility was right in the middle of it, at least some of them were because the nobility was not
at all one unified. Call. Last. For starters, as you can imagine the old nobility, the ones who could
trace their lineage back 700 years did not think much of the new nobility, you know the textile merchants
who just bought his title last Thursday. These two types were described as the sword nobility and the
road nobility. The former owe their status to their mediaeval ancestors having fought alongside the
king, the ladder to some recently acquired venal office, and by recent, the old nobility meant anything
less than about four generations. So the sword nobility generally turned up their noses at the robe,
nobility, or the robe, nobility were ticked off that having climbed into the ranks of the second estate,
they were still being treated as commoners. It also did not help that because of the way French inheritance
laws worked the fortunes of the old nobility and generally eroded to almost nothing.
So most of the wealth of the second estate was held by these former shopkeepers who didn't even know
what fork to use at dinner. Not that the cultivated old nobles were at all opposed to marrying their
sons to the daughters of these barbaric new nobles.
At the very top rung of the nobility, though, were those who both held ancient lineages, and had managed
to keep their fortunes intact, or had successfully gilded their arms as the same went by a fortuitous
marriage or two along the way. These guys were the ones who were still able to afford to live with the
king at Versailles. And they dominated all the major positions in the Royal ministry, the military,
the judiciary in the church. This group, as you can imagine, tended to be rather conservative, but it
is also from these ranks that we find some of the key members of the liberal nobility who will be so
essential to the first stage of the revolution. For example, our old friend, the Marquis de Lafayette.
So that brings us to the first estate, the church, there were about 130,000 members of the French clergy,
and collectively, the church owned about 10% of all the land in France.
But as the great historian George Lefevre noted in his compact but highly influential coming of the
French Revolution, when you talk about the three states of the osteon regime, you're really only talking
about two estates, the nobility and the comments, because the church was really just a microcosm of
the kingdom at large. Way back in 1516, the pope had conceded to the King of France The right to appoint
all the bishops and abbots of the French church. Not surprisingly, these top level jobs which carried
with them massive salaries, but right to collect tithes and control of all those church held lands,
became dominated by the younger sons of the French nobility.
Meanwhile, the vast majority of the 130,000 clergy were parish priests, recruited from the ranks of
the third estate. And usually the lower rungs of the third estate at that not the lowest lowest rungs
into your family still had to buy you some kind of rudimentary education.
But there was still a massive gulf between the noble ecclesiastical authorities on the one hand, and
the common rank and file priesthood on the other. This will become a point of major importance with
new states general get called because the parish priests who had thus far no say in how church wealth
was distributed, and who always seem to see none of the type of money that is supposed to be you know,
maintaining our parishes, will finally get to voice their displeasure of the fat cat Archbishop's and
parasitic monastic orders, who were giving the church a bad name.
So finally, we come to the top of every pyramid, the centre of every circle, the King of France.
And we'll end today with a brief history of the bourbon dynasty, down to the man who finally landed
on the whammy. King Louie the 16th. So in 1268, a daughter and heir to the state of bourbon, married
a younger son of King Louie the ninth St. Louis to his friends.
This Borbon branch of the royal family plugged along for nine generations, becoming the kings of tiny
Navarre in the Pyrenees along the way until some nasty business in the 1580s known as the War of the
three Henry's broke out, during which the Borbon Henry of Navarre ascended to the throne when the sitting
King Henry the third was assassinated in 1589. But this was pretty awkward, because Henry of Navarre
was a Protestant, and he found himself unable, for example, to enter fiercely Catholic Paris.
But the now King Henry the fourth was a practical guide, so he converted to Catholicism to consolidate
his hold on the kingdom, though he did also promulgate the famous Edict of not, which granted religious
toleration if not religious freedom.In 1610, Henry the fourth was assassinated, and he was succeeded
by his 10 year old son Louis the 13th. And the early years of Louie the 13th reign was dominated by
his mother Marie Domenici and featured among other things, the last calling of these Dates general and
1614. That is the assembly of the three estates. When Louie the 13th came of age, though power passed
into the hands of his principal minister Cardinal Richelieu, who we all know is the villain from The
Three Musketeers, but who also steered France through the 30 Years War, and who began the process of
tightening royal authority over the often rebellious nobles out in the provinces.
Both Louie the 13th and Cardinal Richelieu died within about a year of each other.
And four year old Louie the 14th, ascended to the throne in 1643.
Now, as most of you know, Louie The 14th is a pretty big deal.
He would go on to rule for 72 years, the longest reign in the history of Europe, becoming along the
way, the greatest King in the history of France, you know, the Sun King, more than anyone else, it was
Louie the 14th, who created the final form of the osteon regime against which the revolution was eventually
waged. During his minority, there was a fairly massive noble revolt called the frond, which the Kings
forces managed to win. But when Louis the 14th began to rule in his own name, he accelerated the process
of political centralization started by recently, culminating most famously with his conversion of a
royal hunting lodge outside of Paris, into the Palace of Versailles.
The idea behind this new palace was to both physically project the image of royal power, but more importantly,
to force all those nobles who had been causing him trouble from their home provinces to come to Versailles
and attend to him cut off from their natural basis, and plied with lavish gifts and favours.
Louie the 14th completely domesticated the aristocracy, who now jostled over seats at the theatre, undermine
each other with petty gossip, and agonised over who would get to stand where, when the king woke up
in the morning. Over his long reign, Louie the 14th spent money without restraint at home, off simultaneously
immersing France in a series of war abroad. So it's clear that the origins of the persistent royal deficits
that would dog and then consume his successors got going during the heady days of the Sun King.
But that said, When Louie the 14th, died in 1715, France was basically now the foremost Kingdom in Europe
was cultural and political influence was second to none.
This is when practically every court in Europe starts speaking the French language, adopting French
fashions, and following French artistic and architectural tastes.
Louis the 14th live so long that he outlasted not only his son but his grandson.
And so it fell to his five year old great grandson Louie the 15th to succeed him.
And yes, that is the third time in a row, the French crown has fallen to some little kid.
As Louie the 15th grew up, it became clear that not only did he not have much interest in being king,
but he wasn't very good at it either. For our purposes, his main achievement was to form an alliance
with France his longtime nemesis, the Austrians in 1756.
This Alliance led to the Seven Years War, a war in which France paid through the nose for the privilege
of getting kicked around by the British. And as if that wasn't bad enough.
When the French came out the other side of this expensive debacle, they found themselves still tied
to the hated Austrians, which will become an important bone of contention when the revolution gets going.
Generally speaking, the nearly 60 year long reign of Louis the 15th was marked by political and economic
malaise. There were problems that needed answers, policies that needed reforming and courses that needed
correcting and basically nothing was done. But the reign of Louis the 15th, was also marked by the full
flowering of the French enlightenment, and a fantastic explosion of philosophy and literature and science.
And we'll talk about these duelling trends of political stagnation and intellectual vigour next week
when we start laying the groundwork for the looming, but not at all inevitable French Revolution.
So that brings us finally to our man Louie the 16th, the grandson of Louie the 15th.
He ascended the throne in May 1774, at the age of 19.
still young, but he did manage to break the streak of five year olds ruling friends.
Though pretty much everyone agrees that his heart was in the right place, and he genuinely wanted to
do right by his people.He was ill prepared for the role of king.
He was bright and athletic, at least in his youth, but he was also shy and uncomfortable in the spotlight.
Unfortunately for him, the system set up by Louie the 14th basically created the brightest spotlight
imaginable for him to step into. His father had died when he was 11, which left him the heir to the
throne. And though he received a standard upper class education in the humanities, he was for whatever
reason, not given much instruction in the practical Business of how to effectively rule a giant kingdom.
When he was 15 he was married to the 14 year old Austrian archduchess.
Marie Antoinette, repairing that for a good long time was uncomfortable socially, emotionally and physically.
And it was genuinely unpopular and the source of great public and private mockery didn't help.
Marie Antoinette was an Austrian. And by the time they were married in 1770, every Frenchman with an
ounce of patriotism wanted to run the Austrians through with a hot poker, not marry their daughters.
Now, as I said, When Louie the 16th, ascended to the throne in 1774, he was an amiable if hesitant Prince,
who was not opposed at all to trying to solve some of the problems that had built up over the last century.
But as we will see, one of the biggest obstacles to reform was that as much as pre revolutionary France
is depicted as an absolute monarchy, it was in fact, not that at all, and everywhere you turn, there
were entrenched interests, ready to fight for their ancient privileges, whatever those interests and
privileges turned out to be. That resistance to change only exacerbated all the other issues facing
the new king. Next week, we will methodically walk through the list the completely backward tax structure,
the endemic social inequality, a judicial system that price privilege over justice, administrative jurisdictions
that overlapped haphazardly, a church that gobbled up money and seemed to give nothing back an outmoded
and inadequate agricultural economy. An educated class steeped in enlightenment ideals, who could see
what needed to be done, and then watched in frustration as nothing got done.
At least until it was revealed that the monarchy was on the brink of financial ruin.