Hello, and welcome to revolutions Episode 26. Turning south.
Okay, so last time we ended with the newly minted British commander in chief Henry Clinton, fending
off the American attack at Monmouth courthouse and escaping with his army up to New York City.
Just barely unable to rent this escape. George Washington then led his own forces north, eventually
making a headquarters on the Hudson River. The exile of the Continental Congress, meanwhile, finally
ended and the delegates returned to Philadelphia, which was now under the military governorship of Benedict
Arnold, who was given the command in part because the injuries he sustained at Saratoga concluded a
field command. Now one crucial factor in Washington's decision to attack Clinton that I did not talk
about last week was the imminent arrival of the French fleet.
It was due to arrive literally any day now. And Washington hoped that if he could tie the British up
long enough that the French might appear and block any possible escape by sea for the British, and it
almost worked. After breaking out of Monmouth courthouse, Clinton did indeed run North East for Sandy
Hook, a spit that juts North out of New Jersey. From there, he put his men on boats to complete the
journey to New York City. The French fleet finally arrived as this varying operation was underway, but
they were unable to cross the sandbar that makes entering New York harbour somewhat treacherous, and
Clinton was able to make good his escape and holed up in New York City, with all but impossible to attack.
But though New York could not be gotten the fact that Washington now had an allied Navy greatly expanded
his strategic options. So if the big fish could not be fried, then best turn to the littler fish.
And so Washington and the Admiral of the French fleet, the comp distain, coordinated on a plan to go
up and retake Newport, Rhode Island, which was occupied by the British with a garrison of about 3000
men. So at the end of July 1778, the French sailed north, or the Americans started funnelling troops
both local militia and a strong contingent of Continentals underneath Daniel green in the Marquis de
Lafayette into Rhode Island, and soon they would total about 10,000 men.
spies quickly revealed to Henry Clinton what the Americans were up to, and he scrambled to provide Newport
relief, first 20 ships under Admiral Howe, and then as soon as the weather permitted a convoy of about
4000 regular troops. Now, unfortunately for the Americans, and all the coming attack on Newport did
was prove that the alliance between the French and Americans was great in theory, but would take some
time to really work in practice. The man running the show up in Newport, was Brigadier General john
Sullivan. Solomon was the son of Irish immigrants to America.
So as you can imagine, for him, this war was as much about an intense loading of the British as any
noble fight for freedom and liberty. But his lower class Irish upbringing, did not leave him with much
love for French aristocrats either. And for their part, those French aristocrats weren't much for low
born Irish revolutionaries. right from the get go, and coordinating the attack on Newport was rough
going, as Solomon attempted to simply issue orders to distain, which distain was not super interested
in obeying. But despite the friction, the plans for a joint operation finally came together, and the
attack was set to launch August the 10th 1778.A new port is located on the southwest tip of a skinny
island that ran north south off the mainland. The plan was for the Americans to move down and trap the
British inside the city. While the French landed 4000 men of their own on the western shore, and then
arrayed their ships in a tight blockade. The combined land and sea attack was sure to break the British
garrison in no time. But on August the ninth, the day before, this was all supposed to happen, Sullivan
spied an opportunity to get the jump on the British and he moved down early, which only confirmed the
French opinion that these Americans weren't disciplined enough to really count on I mean, right off
the bat, they're jumping the gun. Then the 20 British ships under Admiral how appeared on the horizon
to sane decided that there was no sense getting trapped with only the American rebel to support him.
So instead of landing the French troops he pulled out of the harbour completely.
For two days the French and British fleets manoeuvred around each other until an intense Gale ravaged
them both the British wound up so bad off that Howe had to simply pull out of the area completely.
The French Meanwhile, were scattered all over the place.
But despite the sudden French withdrawn, General Sullivan pressed on, he was still running 10,000 men
against just 3000 inside the city and those are pretty good numbers.
By August the 15th. He was digging fortifications to carry on with the siege Over the next couple of
days, the battered French ships started to return back to port.
But the stain had seemed quite not Thank you very much.
When as much of the fleet as possible had regrouped, he announced that he was sailing his fleet up to
Boston for repairs, taking with him and he real chance of capturing Newport.
When the French sailed away, the American militia forces were like, okay, we're done here, and they
started heading home. So I will then tried to carry on through these obviously, Operation killing setbacks,
Lafayette raced up to Boston to try to convince the state to change his mind.
But by the end of the month, Sullivan finally admitted that if he didn't retreat, his force of now just
5000 men would soon be trapped. So he started to pull off the island, which the British garrison in
Newport took as the perfect opportunity to strike and the retreating Americans were forced to turn and
fight a day's worth of battle exhausted both sides.
But in the end, Solomon was able to complete his withdraw just in time to the very next day those additional
4000 regular sent by Clinton delayed by the same bad weather that had crippled the British and French
Navy's finally arrived. So the Battle of Rhode Island went down merely as an awkward first date for
the French and Americans, rather than a relationship ending catastrophe.
With Newport now strengthened in New York City all but unapproachable, both George Washington and Henry
Clinton settled into an unsatisfying stalemate. Neither were happy about it.
But it appears that of the two Clinton was actually even less happy than Washington.
He was not enthusiastic about the ministry's plan to turn the war south, especially after he received
orders to send 3500 men down to Georgia, and another 5000 down to the West Indies.
That would leave him with just enough troops to hold what he had and maybe right around a little bit,
but not much more, which is just about all the ministry wanted him to do anyway.
After reluctantly dispatching these forces in November in December 1778, the miserable Clinton sent
a letter of resignation back to London in early 1779.
But despite his pleading, it was rejected. King George declared Clinton the only man left who could
pull off a win in North America, Clinton, no doubt sunk even further into his chair after receiving this
glowing vote of confidence. So unfortunately for everyone, US included 1779 turned out to be as fragmented
as it was inconclusive. There were engagements all over the place, but none were really decisive nor
super important to the outcome of the war. For simplicity's sake, we're going to stick with Clinton
and Washington for now as they skirmish around each other in New York.
Then we will double back and follow distain and his fleet as they make a run through the Caribbean.
And then we'll double back again for the British capture of Savannah, Georgia, the failed attempt by
the French and Americans to retake Savannah, Georgia, before finally depositing ourselves in 1780, with
Henry Clinton's invasion of South Carolina, and the capture of Charleston, ready to dry and follow a
bunch of random roads that wind up leading nowhere.
Awesome, let's do it. After his resignation was rejected, Henry Clinton emerged from winter and did
his best to follow orders, which included using the Navy to raid coastal communities to disrupt rebel
trade, a strategy that the ministry now loved when he personally loathed.
raids of Connecticut and the Chesapeake Bay were successful.
Stores public buildings and supply houses were easily destroyed, but not too much long term strategic
effect. The only real engagement of the year which similarly did not have much long term strategic effect
was the Battle of Stoney point, fought over a fortified spirit that jetted out into the Hudson River
about 30 miles north of New York City, and that commanded an important river crossing.
In late May, Clinton personally led his reduced army up the Hudson.
He easily took Stony Point hoping that this would merely be the first move any longer range campaign
to disrupt the American supply lines enough to force them to come down from their fortified positions
and fight a real bout. He had been promised reinforcements from Britain.
But the ships crossing the Atlantic were soon long overdue, and Clinton was forced to withdraw back
to New York City, leaving a garrison of about 750 in control of Stoney point.
After Clinton fell back down the Hudson, Washington ordered general Anthony Wayne, who is about to become
known to history as mad Anthony Wayne for his conduct in the battle to take 1500 men and go retake Stoney
point. working under guidelines laid out by Washington, Wayne led what looked an awful lot like a suicide
mission when he stormed the British position from three directions in the middle of the night using
only band nets. Amazingly, it took Wayne's men just 30 minutes to capture the British position while
suffering almost no casualties. It was a sad mall but morale boosting victory for the Americans who hadn't
really had much to cheer about since Saratoga as per Washington's instructions, when then destroyed
the fortifications, hauled off the cannons and abandoned the site.
Clinton eventually sent a man up to retake it later in the summer.
By then the British commander in chief was deep into planning the invasion of South Carolina, and the
whole back and forth over Stony Point, wound up being a pointless dead end for everyone.
Further to the west out on the New York frontier in general john Sullivan, he of the siege of Newport
was dispatched on a not particularly glorious campaign to exact revenge on loyalists in upstate New
York, and particularly their Iroquois allies. The Patriot presses had been inflamed in 1778 by Indian
attacks on settlers in the Wyoming Valley out on the New York frontier, and then somewhat closer in
at cherry Valley A few months later. In both cases, non combatants were specifically targeted and killed.
So over the summer, 1779, Sullivan ran around with about 4000 men on a deliberate scorched earth campaign
that saw them burn or destroy some 40 Indian villages, killing who they could and driving off the rest.
It wasn't pretty, but it did help the American solidify control the North, which they would not relinquish
for the rest of the war. So that 1779 as far as Clinton and Washington are concerned, all pretty much
much ado about nothing. While this nothing much was playing out in New York, a similar bout of nothing
much was playing out down south. And by down south, I don't mean Georgia, which we'll get to in a minute.
I mean, the West Indies. Now, I don't want to get too much into it because it carries us a bit far afield.
But we need to at least touch on events in the West Indies so we can understand where the French have
gotten off to, and why Clinton has to peel off men he really doesn't have to spare from a war he was
having a really hard time winning. When we last left, the comp disdain and his fleet.
They had sailed away for Boston. after refusing Lafayette police to come back to Newport.
distain repaired his battered fleet and then announced that he had decided to go down and attack British
positions in the Caribbean. His broad mandate gave him all the authority he needed to turn a deaf ear
to American please to stay, pole anchor and just sail away in November 1778.
Coincidentally enough, the French sailed on the same day as the 5000 men, the ministry ordered Clinton
to send down to the West Indies, put out to sea. When these two fleets arrived in the Caribbean, they
found their Conrad's already going at it, with each side having seized an island from the other.
With everyone now reinforced. A couple of indecisive naval battles were fought in December 1778.
But after that, both the French and British decided to just sort of keep an eye on each other for the
next six months. In June 1779, though, the British concentrated forces to protect a crucial convoy and
distain struck at the under defended British colonies of St.
Vincent and Granada. The British Fleet Commander, Admiral john Byron, who is the grandfather of Lord
Byron, by the way, rushed out to confront the French, but he rushed into quickly believing he had superior
numbers, which boy, he really did not.Though he didn't lose any ships, and Byron's fleet was beat to
a pulp and basically knocked out of commission. And a mysterious bit of I don't even know what distain
decided to follow up his decimation of the British fleet by doing nothing.
He quietly returned to French ports and repaired his fleet and took no further action.
When Byron sailed back to Britain in August, the stain decided to finally succumb to the endless pleading
by the Americans to come back up and for God's sakes help us disdains failure to capitalise on the sizeable
naval advantage he now enjoyed. Method 1779 was nothing but a huge missed opportunity for the French,
but at least the stain can make up for his lacklustre performance in the West Indies by helping the
Americans retake Savannah. Right. So rewinding the clock again, shortly after Henry Clinton sent off
the 5000 men he didn't want to send to the West Indies down to the West Indies.
He sent the 3500 men he didn't want to send down to Georgia down to Georgia.
This mixed force of British regulars and hessians landed just south of Savannah two days before Christmas
1778 the only real city to speak of in Georgia. The British expedition arrived at the outskirts of town
a week later and found it to be easy pickings. There were few fortifications to speak of and the 850
Americans guarding the city were totally outnumbered and outgunned.
Then they got badly flung When a slave led a British column through the swamps west of town, in the
brief, practically no more than a skirmish that followed, the Americans bolted in panic, and the British
took the city after losing just three men. Then they marched up and took a gusta The only other thing
that could possibly call a city in Georgia, and they spent the summer of 1779, extending their control
across the whole rest of the state, coordinating with local loyalists of whom there were many was remembered
this was the one colony that had not sent a delegation to the first Continental Congress.
After the capture of Savannah, the American patriots in the south brace for more, but luckily for them
more was not yet on the way as Clinton was busy skirmishing around Stoney point and had not yet headed
south. So the American forces tried to consolidate and maybe put together a plan to march down and reassert
control over Georgia. The American general now in charge of the Southern department was a man named
Benjamin Lincoln, who had been sent out to recuperate after being wounded at Saratoga.
It was quickly apparent to him that any plan to retake Savannah was going to require an assist from
the French Navy, who were unfortunately, currently running around doing not much of anything in the West
Indies. So almost all of 1779 passed before any action could be taken with Lincoln headquartered in
Charleston. But then, kind of out of the blue, a few friendships arrived bearing the incredible news
that distain was on his way to Savannah with 25 gunships and 4000 soldiers.
Lincoln dropped what he was doing in lead 2000 men south.
Hopefully, this second joint American French operation would go better than Newport.
The French landed south of Savannah in mid September 1779, and Lincoln showed up shortly thereafter.
Initially, distain who personally led the French ground forces refused to directly attack the city.
Instead, he set up artillery to bomb the British into submission.
The Americans and French wound up shelling the city for almost a week straight.
Before distain decided that this wasn't going fast enough, and finally agreed to a frontal assault.
Georgia was not treating his men well, and he frankly wanted to get the hell out of there as soon as
possible. So on October the ninth 1779, the French and Americans attacked, and it quickly turned into
a bloody fiasco. The main attack was supposed to be surprise, launch in darkness and covered by diversionary
attacks to confuse the British garrison. But the main allied column got lost in some heavy fog as they
pick their way through a swamp. So the attack didn't start until after sunup, so see you later element
of surprise. Then it turned out that the spot that the stain had selected to hit because it was the
weakest part of the defences turned out to be one of the strongest parts of the defences.
So the assault was quickly stopped dead in its tracks, and then turned into a bloodbath.
The stain was himself wounded twice, and the battered American and French were forced to retreat after
taking heavy losses. Totally whipped. Lincoln and distain officially agreed to call the siege just over
a week later, Savannah would remain in British hands until the end of the war.
There's one last little interesting note about the siege of Savannah I want to mention, because it will
be of interest to us not in our next revolution, the French Revolution, but in the one after that, the
Haitian Revolution. Because when distain came north, he brought with him about 500 Haitian fighters,
many of whom would help form the officer corps of the revolutionary armies who will battle it out after
the slave revolt of 1791. So let's watch out for those guys and hack before we move on.
I may as well mentioned that distain will meet his end in our next revolution, the French Revolution,
because he was closely connected to the royal family and standing by Marie Antoinette right to the bitter
end, and he will be marched to the guillotine in 1794.
Okay, so that brings us to the end of 1779 that fractured and inconclusive year of fractured in conclusiveness.
And it brings us Finally, after all the talk to Henry Clinton's invasion of South Carolina, leaving
behind an adequate garrison in New York City under the command of a Hessian general Clinton wind up leading
about 10,000 men south where they would link up with loyalist militias, and already on the scene regulars
form an army of about 14,000 men to go take Charleston.
Once that was done, reasserting British control of the Carolinas would be an easy warm up for the tougher
challenges that would face them ahead in Virginia.
Clinton's army spent a rotten four weeks at sea being battered by storms before they finally put in
near the mouth of the Savannah River where they picked up some additional forces.
The resting for a bit the British put back out to sea, finally arriving just south of Charleston in
February 1780. Now though, the coming Siege of Charleston turned out to be a nice win for Clinton, getting
there was not in fact, half the fun is first headache came in the form of an 86 year old at Bromley
Marriott. Arbuthnot, think I'm getting that name right.
He says it turns out Clinton and arbuthnott were actually equal in rank, British incoherent once again,
rearing its ugly head. So when they started disagreeing over strategy, and tactics are, let's say something
as simple as where to land the army. There wasn't a final decision maker to say we're going to land
here. Then during the siege itself, arbuthnott tended to alternate between the extremes of lethargy and
recklessness, with the flips seemingly designed to frustrate Clinton as much as possible.
Clinton second headache came in the form of his old comrade and now second in command, Lord Cornwallis,
who was now officially sick of being anyone's second in command.
He thought he had done enough to merit an independent army and wasn't happy about being stuck under
clinton. The two would begin feuding almost at once.
And pretty soon we'd be talking only through letters and vague passive aggressive tones that served
the British or effort not even a little bit. After finally landing his forces where he wanted to land
them, Clinton's set out through the South Carolina swamp to try to get around behind Charleston.
And if slogging through the South Carolina swamp doesn't count as a third major headache.
I don't know what does. Now all of these headaches are somewhat relieved by the fact that the American
fortifications at Charleston we're not in fact going to prove particularly formidable.
Charleston is located at the bottom of a peninsula surrounded on three sides by water.
Benjamin Lincoln long since returned from Savannah, just assumed outright that any attack was going
to come from the sea. So the land facing fortifications were utterly neglected, consisting of a few redoubts
that were not even connected to each other. On the sea side where Lincoln expected the attack, he had
two forts that were just now being worked back into shape.
All Lincoln is roughly 3000 men and the citizens of Charleston really had going for them was the fact
that a sandbar that ran just under the surface of the water, would make it really hard for arbuthnott
to bring his heavy ships into the harbour. By the end of March, and Clinton was finally able to swing
his way around, then come at the unsuspecting Americans from above, and on April the first, he and his
army were camped just 1000 yards from Charleston, Lincoln and the American garrison scramble to prevent
an instantaneous collapse of the line. And though the fortifications would ultimately prove inadequate,
for the moment, they did give Clinton pause about a full scale assault.
With Charleston now surrounded though time and resources were on the British side.
So Clinton commenced with a traditional European approach to siege craft, which involves digging out
an entrenchment, running parallel to the enemy fortifications, and then when that one was complete,
digging forward and starting another parallel line, slowly cutting off the ground between procedure and
besieged. All through April, the British steadily advanced through random and sporadic American shelling.
By the end of April, Clinton had completed his third parallel, and was trying to get Admiral Arbuthnot,
who had been putting ships across the sandbar to sail up the Copper River to help close the noose once
and for all. But Arbuthnot, of course, stalled and made excuses and never did go up the river.
But even with this strategic bickering getting in the way, inside the city, Benjamin Lincoln could see
that the situation was hopeless, and against the begging and pleading of the citizens of Charleston.
He attempted to surrender on April the 21st, hoping to get Clinton to let him March out with his men
in exchange for the city. But Clinton turned him down flat.
The creeping British kept creeping until the second week of May, when a sharp artillery battle broke
out, wound up setting fire to the wood homes inside the city, forcing the residents to admit that it
was time to give up good terms, bad terms, whatever, we just need to give up.
So on May the 12th 17 at the American surrendered Charleston to the British officers and militiamen
were paroled on the promise that they would not rejoin the fight.
While the regular continental soldiers were taken as prisoners of war.
The Siege of Charleston had taken its toll on the already disenchanted Henry Clinton.
His lot in life had come down to feuding with a curmudgeon of an admiral and bickering with an ambitious
and self possessed second in command. On June the first, Clinton issued what he thought would be the
foundation of the British recovery of South Carolina all rebels who lay down their arms would be given
clemency. But the announcement had zero impact on the Patriot partisans who weren't about to just give
up. while simultaneously annoying the loyalist partisans who were frankly offended, the British would
even consider offering clemency to these damned rebel dogs.
frustrated and annoyed, Clinton elected to give Cornwallis the independent command he had been angling
for. A week after issuing his proclamation, Clinton took 4000 men and returned to New York City where
he could stew in peace. Cornwallis was left with the rest of the army and orders to subdue South Carolina,
then make his way through North Carolina into Virginia.
Next week, we will stay in the south with Cornwallis as he finally gets to enjoy the independent command
he had sought for so long. But Cornwallis would soon learn what engage and how and we're going and Clinton
had all learned before him. The Americans just did not understand how wars were supposed to be won.
And when you are beaten, and beaten and beaten again, you're supposed to give up.
Cornwallis will wind up just as bitter and frustrated as every other British General Who would ever
set foot on American soil. We're gonna leave off today though, with a short programming note that next
week, and then again in May, I'll be leading with an ad for our good friends at Harry's razors.
If you listen to other podcasts, you probably know about them already.
But now you'll get to know about them from me too.