Hello and welcome to Revolutions.
Episode 23, Crossing the Delaware.
So I want to start this week with a brief
note about Thomas Paine, common sense
helpfully provided in the comments by
listener T.
Scott Johnson. It would appear that a recent
book called The Republic in Print has pretty
effectively debunked the myth that common
sense reached anywhere near one hundred
thousand printed copies, which I'm glad to
hear because, as I said, one hundred thousand
copies was an impossibly huge number.
And it turns out that I was right about
that.
So thank you to Scott Johnson and good luck
with the Ph.D..
Last week, we left General Washington and
his boys at a low point, having spent their
first campaign season being beaten,
outmaneuvered and run off by early December
17. Seventy six.
The only thing Washington can point to as a
success was that his army was still in the
field at all. But in a few weeks, even that
small consolation might evaporate.
Washington had escaped across the Delaware
River with three thousand men, half of whom
had enlistment that were due to expire
December the 31st.
And that was on top of the two thousand men
who had already gone home when their
enlistment ran out November 30 with nothing
going for the American Army at all.
What was to stop it from simply melting
away?
Washington had managed to escape the
clutches of Gen.
Howe, but could he escape the clutches of
crushingly low morale?
The answer turned out to be yes.
Yes, he could. As you will recall, when
General Howe opted to put his men into winter
quarters, he left the Haitians to guard the
frontier of the Delaware River, which marked
the border between New Jersey to the east
and Pennsylvania to the west.
The Haitians and a string of garrisons up
and down the river, including the city of
Trenton, which was right smack dab in the
middle of that border.
I actually managed to put a map up this week
and managed to do one for the New York
campaigns from last week that I couldn't get
to.
These Haitian garrisons provided a desperate
Washington with one last chance to steal a
victory before the year was up and his
entire army went home.
Now, incredibly, as Washington got to
planning his operation, he received no
reinforcements from the army he had left
back up in New York.
You remember them? The fifty five hundred
men commanded by General Charles Lee.
Despite Washington's repeated pleas to send
troops, Lee just didn't do it, mostly because
Lee was busy waiting for the Congress to
come to its senses, ditch Washington and put
him in charge of the Continental Army.
And though Lee's belligerent ego was mostly
what was at work here on paper, he kind of
had a point. Charles Lee was born in England
in February 17.
Thirty two. So just a few weeks before
Washington himself, the son of a major, he
entered the regular army as a junior officer
at the age of 15 and never looked back.
He served throughout the French and Indian
war, taking an American Indian wife in the
process. Then he returned to Europe, served
in Portugal, and then when his regiment was
disbanded after peace with France, he went
off to serve as a mercenary in Poland.
Returning to Britain, he found himself so
sympathetic to the American cause that he
emigrated to Virginia in seventeen seventy
three, and when war broke out, he immediately
volunteered for service.
Now, given his record, he had little doubt
Congress would appoint him commander in
chief. But of course, there is also the
matter of Charles Lee's personality.
He was ill tempered, foul mouthed, slovenly
and followed everywhere by a loyal pack of
dogs who were really his only friends.
But probably the thing that really sunk him
was that he demanded pay pay that George
Washington announced would be beneath his
own dignity to accept.
So Lee wound up instead being given command
of the Southern Department.
And in mid seventeen seventy six, he
received credit for helping Ward off an
attack on Charleston, although that warding
off was only accomplished after Lee's own
expert advice was ignored.
After Lee was transferred back up to New
York, Washington did everything he could to
placate Lee's ego because Washington was
himself always entranced by the European way
of war, a way that Lee knew better than
anyone.
It was indeed likely an overdose of respect
that led Washington to merely encourage,
rather than explicitly order, Lee to march
from New York down to Pennsylvania.
But Lee did not reciprocate this respect at
all and wasn't going to lift a finger to help
Washington because Lee was busy telling
everyone who would listen, including the
Congress and a steady stream of letters that
Washington was in way over his head and
basically losing the war.
As Washington's encouragement became less
and less veiled, Lee slowly, ever so slowly
got moving. But then comes the hilarious bit
on the road commander in chief.
In his own mind, Lee decided to spend the
night in a tavern while removed from the rest
of his army. The next morning, a mounted
British patrol surrounded the house and
captured Lee, who happened to be stark naked
at the time.
WAPs Lee would spend the next six months in
British custody before being exchanged for a
captured British general.
Given his conduct at Monmouth Courthouse, it
probably would have been better for the
Americans to exchange the captured British
general or a sack of potatoes.
So without further reinforcements, Washington
was forced to draw up a plan to attack
Trenton with what men he had on hand and oh,
what a plan it was.
Because as much as Washington was the master
of the flawless retreat, he was also the
master of the insanely complicated battle
plan.
And he was always coming up with these
schemes that involve twenty seven different
moving parts that needed to work in perfect
synchronization.
And his plan for Trenton was classic
Washington.
It was laid out in three phases.
First, seven hundred men would silently
cross the Delaware River and seize a key
bridge south of Trenton.
Then another fifteen hundred militia men
would cross even further south and launch a
diversionary attack on the garrison at
Bordentown.
Then Washington and his main force of twenty
four hundred men would cross the Delaware
themselves at midnight, divide into two
columns and take separate roads the nine
miles to Trenton. Then they would all
simultaneously be in position to strike the
city no later than five a.m..
So what we've got here is four different
columns that will be moving in different
directions at different times.
In the middle of the night, in the dead of
winter, all without tipping off the Hessians
and oh, by the way, if this doesn't work,
that's the end of the war.
Needless to say, this did not all unfold the
way Washington planned.
And it's frankly a wonder it all turned out
as well as it did.
The first two phases of the operation, for
example, failed immediately as neither the
advanced unit nor the diversionary force had
been able to cross at their assigned
locations due to the icy conditions of the
Delaware River FACT's Washington did not
learn until well after the battle was over.
Then those same icy conditions destroyed his
own timetable.
And though everyone worked as fast and as
well as they could, Washington's army wasn't
even ready to start marching until four a.m.
and according to the plan, they were already
supposed to be at Trenton by now.
But Washington pressed on, I mean, what else
could he do?
He divided his twenty four hundred men into
the two columns, one that would approach
Trenton from the north and one that would
come up and around from the south.
Amazingly, both these columns hit their
marks at almost the same time, just about
8:00 a.m.. As Washington led the final
approach, though, he ran into a small,
independent company of about 50 Americans
who knew nothing about the planned attack and
were returning from a little raid on Trenton
of their own.
A raid that had seen them exchange gunfire
with Heshan sentries.
Washington was mortified and thought his
entire operation was now exposed.
But it's possible that this raid actually
put the Hashim's mind at ease.
Is he? The Heshan colonel in charge of
Trenton had been tipped off a few days
earlier to watch out for a possible attack,
and he had kept his men on high alert and
running frequent patrols.
When this little raiding party came and
went, they thought the quote unquote attack
had now come and gone and relaxed because it
went without saying that in this crappy
weather, nothing more could be expected from
the Americans.
And that brings us to the myth of the drunk
and or hungover Hessians.
Unfortunately, for those of us who like a
good story, the myth is just that, a myth.
And eyewitnesses report that the Hessians,
though, caught off guard because they were
really not expecting a major attack given
the rotten weather.
They were stone sober before, during and
after the battle.
As Washington led his column to the north
side of Trenton, they skirmished with an
outpost about a mile outside the city,
forcing the Heshan guards into a fighting
retreat that alerted the rest of the
garrison in Trenton that something much
bigger was on the way.
But the Americans were able to place their
artillery in time.
One battery, which was commanded by a young
artillery captain named Alexander Hamilton as
the Hessians tried to form up for battle.
They were blasted into a chaotic mess.
The Heshan colonel rushed around, reforming
his men for a counterattack, but wound up
mortally wounded for his trouble.
By now, the Hessians were squeezed between
the advancing enemy on both sides.
And within an hour, the Battle of Trenton
was over.
Twenty two Haitians lay dead.
Another eighty four were wounded and almost
a thousand captured, along with a bounty of
musket bayonet cannons and provisions.
The Americans suffered just two combat
deaths and a few light wounds.
It was exactly the kind of unambiguous,
absolutely clear cut victory that Washington
and the Americans needed.
The whole thing had been an enormous gamble.
And had it failed, who knows whether the
American rebellion would have gone down as
little more than a historical footnote?
Now, Washington's original plan was as
ambitious as it was complicated, and he hoped
to use the momentum from Trenton to
immediately push on to Princeton.
But the night's delays, coupled with
exhaustion, coupled with the news that the
other advanced units never had crossed the
river, led Washington to call it good right
there. And he led his men and prisoners back
across the Delaware away from easy British
retaliation. The next day, though,
Washington and his war council learned that
the militiamen that were supposed to have
been running the diversion down south and now
operating independently had elected to cross
the Delaware.
With this force already on the other side,
Washington decided to follow them back into
New Jersey. So on December the twenty ninth,
Washington sent his men back across the river
to occupy Trenton, which had the added
benefit of making it just a little bit harder
for those men who plan to ditch out on
January the 1st to do so.
When that fateful day did arrive, Washington
gave impassioned addresses and offered
bounties were just six more weeks service.
And of the roughly five thousand now had on
hand, he was able to hold three thousand, at
least for the time being joined by the
militiamen who had crossed further south.
Washington now had five or six thousand men
under his immediate command.
Meanwhile, General Howe was not going to
take the attack on Trenton lying down.
Well, maybe he would, but his army sure
wouldn't.
And he dispatched 8000 men under Lord
Cornwallis to stamp out this burgeoning
American resilience.
Cornwallis marched through Princeton,
dropped off a garrison, and then headed down
to Trenton with fifty five hundred men.
He was harassed the entire way by American
Forward Unit, whose sole job was to make him
and his men hate their rotten luck for being
stuck on this assignment.
When Cornwallis got to Trenton, he found the
Americans drawn up on a ridge south of town
with a creek between them and the
approaching British.
Cornwallis tried three times to cross the
bridge, but when each attempt failed, he
decided to halt for the day and resume the
attack in the morning because from where he
was sitting, Washington and his men were
basically trapped up on that ridge.
But local knowledge can be a powerful weapon.
And during the night, leaving a few men
behind to tend the line of fires and shoot
random cannon shots, Washington led his army
down back roads that weren't on any map.
When dawn broke on January the 2nd, Cornwall
was found, the ridge empty and the British
garrison left at Princeton found itself
under attack.
The garrison was already on their way to
join Cornwallis for the final assault on the
ridge when they were hit by the army that
was supposed to be trapped up on that ridge
and the initial fighting, the Americans were
driven back and started to run for it.
But Washington himself soon appeared on
horseback, rerouted the fleeing men and
pointed them back in the right direction.
In the midst of all this, there was a moment
when Washington was riding around between the
two lines, shouting encouragement to his men
when both sides started firing at once.
Absolutely inexplicably, when the smoke
cleared, Washington was still just riding
around. Not dead, not even hit.
Following this miracle, the bulk of the
British forces were able to push through and
run south for Trenton while the rest were
pushed back and captured in Princeton with
yet another victory in hand and Cornwall is
bearing down on him.
Washington decided that it really was time to
call it quits for the year, and he led his
men into winter quarters in Morristown, New
Jersey.
Morristown was about 25 miles west of New
York City and well situated to stymie the
British, if they got it in their heads to
move on Philadelphia or move up the Hudson
River. Now, as we will see, winter was a
dreadful time to be a soldier in the
Continental Army. We're talking no clothes,
no food, only super rudimentary shelter.
There was disease.
It was just the pits.
But we'll talk more about it when we get to
the famously hard winter next year at Valley
Forge. And then a bit more when we talk
about the less famously but even harder
winter back in Morristown.
The year after that, these conditions made
retaining soldiers so difficult that the fact
that anyone stayed at all is positively
miraculous.
Washington's whole army was down to just
three thousand men by March with expiring
terms, desertion and smallpox taking their
heavy toll.
As spring came, recruiters for the
Continental Army did their best and the total
was back up to nine thousand.
But these recruiters were stymied by
Washington's old nemesis, the colonial
militias who offered higher bounties, better
pay and better terms of service.
Begging, pleading and demanding that local
leaders stop poaching able bodied men would
be a constant refrain from Washington all
through the war.
But at least for the moment, his other bouts
of begging, pleading and demanding for guns
and supplies got a little boost when
American agents in France were able to set up
back channel supply lines from the French
government run through a front company in
Paris. The French were obviously interested
in seeing the colonials take it to their
British enemies, but throwing in with the
Americans completely was still out of the
question. So at this point, we're going to
separate the two great threads that define
the war in 1777.
Today, we're going to stick with General
Washington as he fails to keep the British
out of Philadelphia and then fails to knock
them out after they seize the capital.
That will take us all the way to the end of
the year.
But of course, as this is unfolding in
Pennsylvania, the turning point of the war is
unfolding in upstate New York.
And we will talk about that next week
because otherwise it'll just be too much
hopping around as everything is happening
simultaneously in September and October 17.
Seventy seven. So sticking with Washington,
the campaign season of seventy seven did not
get going until mid-June when General Howe
decided it was high time.
He set out on that one more year of good
campaigning to finish off the rebellion on
June 17th. How moved a large force off
Staten Island and flashed them around New
Jersey, hoping to lure Washington into a
decisive battle.
But Washington did not take the bait a week
later.
How maneuvered around again trying to draw
out the Americans.
But Washington managed to squeeze his men
out of a trap in the nick of time.
These ploys having failed how elected to
abandon New Jersey and then pull off the
mainland completely.
A stunt like this for the great reason why
the Americans were doomed without foreign
assistance, because without an enemy navy to
stop him, how could do things like put
eighteen thousand men on transport ships,
set out onto the high seas and then put them
back in wherever he wanted, which is exactly
what he did in the summer of 1777.
I mean, you could guess where his army was
going to suddenly reappear, but there was no
way of knowing for sure.
And it understandably became Washington's
great obsession over the summer.
The available options, though, were
basically three fold.
Go after Philadelphia from some angle or
another, head north to link up with the
Bourgoyne expedition coming down from
Canada.
That's what we're going to talk about next
week or transfer the whole focus of the war
and head down to like Charleston, South
Carolina.
Now, from everyone's point of view, it is
the British ministry, the American War
Council, the unanimous judgment of history.
What how needed to do was go link up with
begoing, but for a variety of reasons.
We'll talk about next week.
That did not happen.
And from at least April forward, how had his
eye on taking the rebel capital in
Philadelphia once he put out to sea?
The only question in his own mind was where
exactly and when exactly he would land to
make that attempt.
The endlessly and helplessly frustrating
days of speculation and inactivity finally
ended for Washington at the end of August,
when Howe put into Chesapeake Bay, about 50
miles southwest of Philadelphia, while Howe
let his men recuperate, the month at sea had
been pretty awful.
Washington got his army marching south,
picking up militia companies along the way
until he commanded nearly twenty thousand
men on the way to the confrontation with the
British. The American army entered and then
marched as smartly as they could through the
streets of Philadelphia.
Washington tried to put on as good a show as
he could, but even a casual observer could
tell that these boys did not step as lively
nor look as sharp as a professional army
ought to step and look.
Meanwhile, how was now on his way north with
15000 men harassed, as he was now the custom
by small detachments of American forces?
Washington move west out of Philadelphia,
and on September the 10th, he decided to drop
a line of about fourteen thousand
Continentals and militiamen at Brandywine
Creek. There were only a few places the
British army could afford the river and the
Americans work to cover those spots and make
the main road into Philadelphia impregnable,
unfortunately, as had been the case at Long
Island.
The Americans left open a pair of Fords on
the very far right of their line, possibly
because they just did not know they were
there, how they found out about these open
Fords. So this time it was the British
rather than the Americans who enjoyed that
all powerful weapon, local knowledge.
At four a.m. on September the 11th, how sent
forward a detachment of five thousand men
under one of the Heshan commanders to feign
a frontal attack while he and Cornwallis led
the rest of the army on a wide flanking
maneuver across those unguarded forts.
Now, one of the questions looming over the
Battle of Brandywine is that it appears
Washington heard that something was up on
his far right as early as nine thirty a.m.,
but he did not act and no one really knows
why.
But it was possibly just because he didn't
believe the report.
But by 2:00 in the afternoon, the bulk of
the British forces were across the creek and
threatening the utterly exposed American
right flank.
Quickly, the American forces reformed a line
to stop them, and they were given a little
breathing room because how in Cornwall took
their sweet time forming up for the attack.
By four o'clock, though, that attack came
and it quickly became apparent that b
scrambling Americans had left a hole in
their hastily reformed lines.
The British poured through that home and no
American reinforcements showed up and brought
everyone some time. The fighting descended
into brutal, ugly chaos, and the Americans
broke and ran, not in any kind of classic
Washington led order.
This was panicked flight.
Meanwhile, back where Washington had thought
the battle was going to take place, the
Heshan commander had waited for the sound of
house attack to press right up the middle.
They fought their way across the creek and
engaged in fierce close quarters combat.
But the fighting had started so late in the
day that darkness soon forced both sides to
pull back. Washington wasted no time
catching his breath.
He and his men were beaten and beaten bad,
and they had to get the hell out of there and
regroup. So while the British did take a
breather, the Americans spent the night in
full retreat. The Battle of Brandywine was
yet another clear cut victory for how over
Washington, though somehow the American army
still stood between the British and
Philadelphia. A week and a half later,
though, how maneuvered around and trick the
battered Americans into following him away
is up the Schoolkid River before doubling
back and crossing at a lower Ford that left
the way to Philadelphia wide open on
September 18th. The delegates of the Second
Continental Congress learning that they were
exposed, booked it eventually New York,
Pennsylvania, where they would remain in
exile for the next year.
But when the British marched into
Philadelphia on the 26th, looking every bit,
the professional army, the Continentals had
just shown themselves not to be.
It wasn't the decisive blow Howe had hoped
it would be.
I mean, hello, I just took the capital.
That means it's time to surrender.
Hello. You guys even know how to play this
game?
But the Americans did not know how to play
that game, and Washington and his men
retreated twenty five miles outside of the
city to plan their next move.
Once in Philadelphia, how had to scatter his
forces so they wouldn't trip over each other
trying to sleep and eat.
But knowing that the American army was still
out in the neighborhood, he concentrated nine
thousand men at Germantown, about five miles
north of the city, Washington and his
officers decided that taking the forces at
Germantown was risky but too juicy to pass up
because for the moment, the Americans would
actually outnumber the British there.
And if it went totally right, a victory at
Germantown, along with the utterly astounding
American victory up at Saratoga, might just
be enough to win the war.
I mean, seriously, despite everything, the
Americans were in a really good position to
win the Revolutionary War right there in the
fall of 1777.
As with Trenton, Washington's battle plan
for Germantown was a perfect work of art,
just as long as it didn't try to, like,
leave the tent.
It involved four columns setting out on a
night marches so that they could
simultaneously attack Germantown from four
different directions at dawn, which is all
well and good except that it's night.
The terrain is difficult and some of the
columns have much farther to March than
others. Oh, also a heavy fog is about to set
in.
It would be hard enough to pull off
Washington's plan for Germantown with modern
communications without them.
Well, good luck, everybody.
They did at least think to stick a piece of
white paper in everyone's hat so that they
could tell their friend from their enemy
when they all got to the other side.
A force marched through the night of October
the 3rd and 4th, put the various columns
close to Germantown without yet being
detected, but only one of the flanking
columns reached tended position when Dawn
came.
Finally, around 5:00 a.m., the American
column that was aiming right at the heart of
town came rolling in and kicked off the
battle by firing on British guards who
sounded the alarm. At this point, General
Howe actually came riding out personally to
convince these guards to hold firm, since
they were only facing a few obnoxious
raiders. When the American cannons started
going off, though, how pulled back and his
men quickly followed him.
This was no party of raiders.
This was a full scale attack.
But then the Americans started making
mistakes instead of driving forward, they got
bogged down at a stone house on the edge of
town fortified by the British.
Washington's options were either bypass it or
try to take it.
He almost elected to bypass it.
But Henry Knox convinced him that the oldest
war manuals in the world said never leave a
strong point in your rear and promised that
his artillery boys could take it.
But after an hour of banging cannonballs off
the side of the house, it turned out that
Knox's artillery boys could not, in fact,
take it.
And they were just wasting time, ammunition
and more than a few men.
Meanwhile, the other American, Collum,
started pouring into town from their
different directions, but the heavy fog made
everything super confusing.
One unit fell back because they thought they
were exposed when they really weren't.
Another detachment coming in from the flank
took a wrong turn and wound up banging into
those retreating guys, and they all started
firing at each other.
Meanwhile, the last column to arrive, led by
Nathaniel Green, pushed into the mix and his
advanced companies managed to actually
capture a bunch of prisoners.
But then those advanced units were
themselves surrounded, believing the rest of
the army in retreat, green, too, withdrew,
realizing that this had all gone awry.
Washington ordered a full retreat and his
army was chased for nearly 10 miles before
Greene's forces were able to buy the rest
time to get away completely.
The battle of Germantown was yet another
defeat for the Americans, but oddly enough,
it actually helped Benjamin Franklin make
the all important case he was currently
making to the French, because despite it all
ending in failure, European observers in
America were impressed by the sophistication
of the plan, the bravery of the troops.
And as always, the disciplined retreat.
It had all gone haywire in the fog, but you
really can't blame them for that.
And one or two breaks and Germantown would
have been a smashing American success.
So it was clear by the end of seventeen
seventy seven that the Continental Army had
shaped up to be a real army, not just some
pretend mob of hooligans, but this was little
comfort for Washington himself as he and his
army settled into their famously hard winter
at Valley Forge because he was forced to
dwell on the defeats at Brandywine in
Germantown and question his own ability to
win the war.
And he was not the only one asking those
questions.
Next week, though, we are going to go back
in time to the spring of 1777 and run through
the Saratoga campaigns up in the north,
which started with British General John
Burgoyne setting out on what he thought was
some kind of luxurious triumphal parade and
ended with him handing over his sword.