This week's episode is brought to you by Harry's razors.
So you go to the drugstore to pick up some razors.
First, you have to find the guy who can open the case, then you have to wait around while he finds the
keys to the case. And then when the case finally gets open, your reward is paying 25 bucks for four
blades and some shaving cream. You leave muttering obscenities about the waste of time and money.
Such was the last straw for Andy, one of the co founders of Harry's razors, who was convinced that there
had to be a better way and there was focused on providing guys a great shaving experience where a fraction
of the price of the competition Harry's razors offers high quality blades engineered in their very own
German factory. Order online, it gets shipped to your home.
It's simple. I've got my own kit working for me as we speak, the blades are sharp, the razor design
is clean, which I like. And the cream is exactly what I need it to be no cuts, no irritation, it's great.
And plus, I don't have to wait around for the guy with the keys just to pay way too much for it all.
So stop overpaying for a good shave and go to harrys.com use the promo code revolutions say $5 off your
first purchase at again harrys.com promo code revolutionsHello, and welcome to revolutions.
Episode 27 Carlton's corner. Last week, the British turned the focus of the Revolutionary War South
first capturing Savannah, Georgia in 1779 and then taking Charleston, South Carolina in May 1780.
After taking these two key ports, the plan was to extend British influence inland and then move like
a wave up through North Carolina into Virginia, clearing out patriots and putting loyalists back in
charge. Now finally, in control of his own army, British General Charles Cornwallis was sure he could
take the Carolinas without too much difficulty. And according to the conventions of European war, his
campaign got off to a nearly flawless start. His forces quickly controlled a network of strategic strong
points across South Carolina, and then those we're about to see, he went the Continental armies and
to stop him without breaking a sweat. But despite these early successes, Cornwallis soon discovered that
these ignorant American rustics not having been educated properly at Oxford could not even do simple
math. triumph in the field plus control of all strong points is supposed to equal conquest.
Instead, the smart alec Americans had answered the triumph in the field plus control of all strong points
equals permanent ulcer. One of the big factors that led Cornwallis to develop this permanent ulcer was
the terrible paradox implicit in using force to put down a rebellion, because brute force only tends
to make more rebels. So defeating these rebels militarily and winning them over politically, were all
but mutually exclusive goals. He also had to deal with a loyalist population strong enough to hold the
tone in a bitter civil war that was breaking out in the Carolinas Civil War defined by small scale raid,
torching of houses, murders, run ins between neighbours, brutal skirmishes without quarter, there was
just no opportunity for Cornwallis to play the benevolent conqueror even if he had wanted to.
Both the Patriots and the loyalists were pretty well past being able to go back to the way things were
before the war. This little Civil War only picked up heat after the siege of Charleston, which put the
loyalists back in power and drove the Patriots to ground where they launched a guerrilla campaign that
did nothing but stymie, frustrate and ultimately undo the British dream of controlling the South.
On the Patriot side, the most famous leader of these irregular guerrilla forces was of course, Francis
Marion, the Swamp Fox. Many of you out there will remember that Disney produced a TV series about the
Swamp Fox back in the 1960s that is revered among Revolutionary War historians for its painstakingly
accurate portrayal Marian and his campaigns, I am sometimes told my humour is too dry, but I'll leave
it to you to judge. Marian was in his mid 40s, and then had learned his trade battling, often brutally.
So Cherokee Indians during the French and Indian War, slave owner like most of the other southern officers,
he joined the South Carolina regiment of the Continental Army as a captain 1775 and will soon promoted
to Colonel.Hewas present for the disastrous attempt to retake Savannah in 1779.
And only miss being captured at Charleston because he had left the city to recuperate from a broken
ankle. When the last of the Continentals were pushed out of South Carolina in May, which we'll talk about
in a second. Marian was practically the only officer left in the state, and he organised a small force
of no more than 100 volunteers to carry on the fight for how long and to what end they did not yet know
On the loyal aside, the most famous unit was the British Legion, a unit composed entirely of American
volunteers under the command of British Colonel Bannister.
tarlton. Carlton's Raiders as they were informally known were a ruthless and effective arm of the British
regular army, earning instant infamy in the Patriot presses for their conduct during the Battle of whack
saws, which soon became known as the waxhaw massacre, bought at the end of Maine near the North Carolina
border. The small battle ended with the Americans first refusing to surrender but then throwing down
their arms after being charged by Carlton's cavalry.
The gist of what follows is that the Americans offer the white flag Carlton's horse was shot out from
under him. And then Tarleton men started mowing down the surrendering Americans and methodically killing
wounded men as they lay prone in the field. accounts of the massacre, why it unfolded and to what extent
it was, in fact, a massacre are of course, all contradictory.
But the upshot was that the Legion became particularly feared and hated, and led American irregulars
to start offering the British what they like to call Carlton's quarter.
That is no quarter at all. The Battle of wax off and push the last of the Continentals out of South
Carolina, forcing the Continental Congress to scramble a response to stop the British before they could
spread further north. Who to put in charge of this response seemed like an easy choice.
Oh, the Conway cabal had failed to oust Washington.
The sentiment still persisted that the war would be one only of Horatio gates, the hero of Saratoga,
led the waysays there was no question that Washington had to stay outside of New York City.
Gates, his allies in Congress found little opposition to putting their man in charge of the Southern
department. Even as Washington himself recommended Nathaniel Greene.
Gates was given his orders in May 17. At And off he went, it would take just under three months for
everyone to realise what a terrible mistake they had just made.
Before Charleston fell in Congress had dispatched two regiments of Continentals from Maryland and Delaware
to go relieve the besieged city. But these forces had not made it in time.
So this group of about 1400 wind up forming the Corps of gates his new army, and he linked up with them
in Hillsboro, North Carolina at the end of July 1780.
what he found was not a pretty sight, these guys were worn out, badly supplied and poorly armed.
Even the camp itself was a mess of crude disorganised huts.
So it was clear, the first order of business would be resting these men and organising a proper supply
train because they were for the moment in no shape to be fighting, which is why the minute he showed
up, gates first forced the men to turn out for parade and then ordered them to march toward the city
of Camden, South Carolina, one of those strategic strong points the British control on the border between
the Carolinas. Nearly every officer present begged him not to do it.
But gates believed Camden was held by just 700 men, it could be taken easily so off this bedraggled
army went and just to make sure that things went from bad to worse, gates ordered them all down a road
flank on both sides by swamp land, cutting off access to any supplies.
Not that there was much to be had anyway, given the loyalist leanings of the local population.
So it was a sick, tired and hungry mob who shuffled toward Camden in the brutal summer heat of 1780.
Oh, did I mention they also don't have any artillery or cavalry? Yeah, there's that too.
It was not all bad news, though. As gate marked, his army was reinforced by companies of North Carolina
and Virginia militia. They all neared Camden on August the seventh the nominal strength of the Americans
was up to about 4000. Though sickness and malnutrition left this number deceptively inflated.
Incredibly, though, Gates was totally ignorant about his own strength when he believed he commanded
some 7000 men. With this number lodged in his head, he was supremely confident that he could take camp
and even if it was reinforced, which, oh, by the way, Cornwallis was personally rushing to do after
loyal supplies tipped him off to Gates's movements.
Cornwallis was soon in Camden with about 2000 able bodied men.
As the Americans made their final approach a week later, Gates was alerted that an official headcount
put his numbers at something like half of what he fought, but already committed to the battle in his
heart. Gates just let this revelation pass without changing his plans.
At 10pm, on the night of August the 15th 17th, at both Cornwallis AND gates put their armies in motion,
Gates was still under the impression he was on his way to envelop a much smaller British force inside
the city, and had no idea that he was about to run smack into a British army roughly the same size as
his own. But at about 230 in the morning, that's exactly what happened was the advanced guard to both
armies bang right into each other. Both generals called an alarm halt when the sun rose gates and Cornwallis
Not only were they can't just 300 yards apart, but also that the numbers were far more even than either
had previously suspected. Because Cornwallis no less than gates thought the Americans would have a big
numerical advantage. I mean, why else would gates be rushing into battle? gates did have more troops,
but most of the militiamen from Virginia and North Carolina had never even sniffed a battle.
So to put it bluntly, the Battle of Camden was not a battle gates should have been fighting.
But now he was here, and there was nowhere else to go.
With this strategic blunder in place, gates then started making tactical blunders.
He lined up the untested Virginia militia against what he thought was the loyalist militia, but which
turned out to be the best regular troops Cornwallis hat.
Then when gates spied those best regular troops, Cornwallis had futzing around and still forming up
he ordered the Virginia militia to advance except the movements that gates spied.
Were not the British warming up at all, but the British preparing to advance, so they were more than
ready to square off against the approaching Virginians.
A sharp Mali stopped the Virginia militia in its tracks, and the British fixed bayonets and chargedwith
no bayonets of their own, The Virginian simply turned in ran.
Most never even fired a shot. The Panic of the Virginians quickly spread to the North Carolina men who
had been nervously holding the line beside them, but who were now often running to the whole left flank
collapsed in a matter of minutes. On the right, the Delaware and Maryland regimens held their ground
and even managed to charge but they were now badly outnumbered and when Cornwallis ordered Tarleton
to take in the cavalry and clear out the Americans, it didn't take much convincing to force them all
into a chaotic retreat. Meanwhile, General gates had pulled back about a quarter of a mile to stand resolute
as the rallying point for his panicked and beaten men, proving once again the American ability to maintain
coherence and dignity even after a crushing defeat.
Haha, just kidding. When the Virginia militia ran gates bolted by nightfall, he was 60 miles north.
A few days later, he was back in Hillsborough, another 120 miles further up the road.
He left behind 900 killed and wounded, another 1000 captured and a beleaguered remnant that didn't know
what they were supposed to do now and so most just went home.
Battle of Camden was in every way a crushing defeat.
It was pretty much the end of her ratio gates. He would survive the call for an inquiry of his conduct,
and later even wound up on Washington staff. But his reputation died on the battlefield.
Along with so many of his men, he was never again given a field command.
On the other side, Cornwallis bask in the glow of this decisive victory, victory that had the added
bonus of avenging British honour by crushing Horatio gates.
But that glow soon dimmed under the realisation that it seemed to change the political situation in
the Carolinas not a bit. The raids and skirmishes and guerrilla attacks between loyalists and patriots
continued as if nothing had happened. And the Continental Congress simply got to work organising another
army. The Battle of Camden was a great triumph for Cornwallis, but in the end, practically nothing came
of it. But that said, the things in South Carolina were looking good enough for the moment for Cornwallis
to start making plans to move up into North Carolina.
But this is where the relationship breakdown between Cornwallis and Henry Clinton starts getting in
the way. As I mentioned, the two were now reduced to exchanging passive aggressive letters.
Cornwallis wanted Clinton to launch a diversionary campaign to make sure North Carolina didn't receive
much in the way of continental reinforcements. Clinton was happy to do it, but only after Cornwallis
hit the road. But Cornwallis didn't want to hit the road until after he was assured the diversion had
been launched. This petty little back and forth ended when Cornwallis decided to just move up to North
Carolina. He was over the border in Charlotte by the end of September 17.
At but would find that North Carolina was not as hospitable nor South Carolina as pacified, as he had
previously believed. As it turned out, the grand strategy to choke off the rebellion from the south
was not the Sure thing. Everyone in the ministry had desperately convinced themselves that it would be.
But before we go on in the south, where Nathaniel Greene is about to take over for the Americans and
exacerbate Cornwallis is also we need to peel off and deal with the utterly shocking treason of American
war hero Benedict Arnold. unquestionably the most famous bit of treason in American history.
at his best, Arnold was an utterly fearless leader, a man who dreamed up bold strokes and then personally
led the way. But at his worst, Arnold was an easily disgruntle hothead, who could find a way to rub
practically everyone the wrong way. From day one, he had steward over the slow advance of his career,
always believing he was at least one or two ranks below his merit.
He gets sympathy points for a problem. We being right about that, but get to those points taken away
by complaining about it relentlessly. So about the time he was appointed military governor of Philadelphia
in May 1778, Arnold had both a huge chip on his shoulder and a tonne of enemies, just waiting for him
to slip up. This combination was disastrous for his loyalty to the American cause.
The angle of attack Arnold numerous enemies took was the reputation he had earned over the years for
making sure that every campaign was a profitable campaign.
You know what I mean? Starting with his early adventures in Canada, there were whispers that Arnold
was as much interested in lining his own pockets, as he was in defeating the British conduct as governor
Philadelphia only increased the volume of those whispers.
He lived in lavish style and got into the business of transporting warm material around for the Continental
Army, which wasn't illegal, but it did run him afoul of local merchants whose business he was cutting
into. adding fuel to the fire was Arnold's Courtship of Peggy Shipton, the daughter of a wealthy Philadelphia
judgewith well known loyalist ties. Soon his political opponents were gathering evidence of Arlen's
misconduct and misappropriations. The Courtship of Young Miss Shipton, who is about to become young,
Mrs. Arnold also moved on into loyalist inclines social circles in Philadelphia.
And those social circles put him in contact with British intelligence officers.
intelligence officers, major john Andre, who had just recently been courting the same is shipped and
during the British occupation of Philadelphia seems that by at least July 1779, disgruntled and disenchanted,
Arnold was passing along information about American troop deployments.
While this secret correspondence was underway, Arnold enemies finally had enough to take to Congress
and demand that he be brought up on charges. When Arnold was informed of all this, he demanded a court
martial to clear his name and defend his besmirched honour.
This while he was telling Henry Clinton that for the right price, he would switch sides.
Arnold's court martial was initially set to begin in June 1779.
But Clinton's advance up the Hudson his Stony Point threw it back six months, so it wasn't until January
17. At the trial began. The various charges levied against him went all the way back to his early days
up in Canada, and the embittered Arnold was further embittered when his expense reports from that campaign
couldn't be verified because all the records had gone down with his ship during the Battle of valcour
Island, which, you know, I'm sorry, I don't have the receipts.
I was too busy stopping the British Army from invading and wiping you all out.
In the end, Arnold's record out shown his reputation and he was cleared of all but too small charges.
This was mostly of indication, but it left him on the hook to the Congress for 1000 unaccounted for
pounds. And that pretty much sealed the deal for Benedict Arnold.
Despite these unseemly charges, Washington tried to keep Arnold in the fold.
I mean, after all, he was a great officer. And in June 1780, he offered Arnold command of Fort West
Point up on the Hudson River, which Arnold immediately turned around and used as leverage with Clinton.
He offered to turn over the fort for 20,000 pounds and indemnification for financial losses, he would
no doubt to stain as a result of his treason. Clinton thought this over stuck mostly on the issue of
indemnification, which was way too wide open a financial commitment.
By the end of August, though, Clinton agreed to the 20,000 but not the indemnification.
Arnold accepted and set to work deliberately weakening the defences of West Point.
This went on for a good month, which no one the wiser, though I'm sure there were a few puzzled looks
among soldiers about some of the stuff they were being told to do, or more importantly, told not to
do. On September the 21st 17, at Arnold finally had a face to face meeting with major Andre who snuck
behind enemy lines to pick up the plans for the Ford along with some other thoroughly incriminating
documents. But two days later, Andre was captured in civilian clothes trying to make his way back to
New York City. Coincidentally, the morning after Andre was captured, Arnold was set to have breakfast
with General Washington and review how things were going at West Point.
Arnold learned of Andres capture literally minutes before Washington was due to arrive.
When the commander in chief showed up he of course could not find Arnold anywhere because he was running
like a madman for New York City. Washington did however, find an inconsolable Peggy shipped and now
Peggy Arnold, who couldn't believe that her husband would commit treason like that she was shockedshocked,
Itell you to discover that there was gambling going on in this establishment.
The gentlemanly Washington consoled her in her grief, suspecting not even a bit that she was basically
the one who had arranged the whole thing. Though Washington raged privately, publicly, he took the sudden
betrayal and stride and calmly offered to hand over Andre in exchange for Arnold Henry Clinton refused
though. It seems like an awfully cold decision given how much he apparently loved Andre and despised
Arnold as traders are almost always despised by everyone.
Even the side they're helping so remember kids, no one likes a trader.
The charismatic and charming Andre Meanwhile, soon endeared himself to his captors and influential men
on both sides tried to get him spared or at least shot as was befitting an Officer and a Gentleman.
But Washington refused to yield to sentimentality.
And he had Andre hanged on October the second as a spy.
Arnold Meanwhile, was commissioned as a brigadier general in the British Army never saw much of the
20,000 he had been promised as the plot had obviously failed.
He will show up again next week in command of troops in Virginia where American officers will be under
orders from Washington to summarily hang him, the ever fell into their hands.
So with the most famous case of treason now wrapped up we can return to the southern theatre.
We're just a few days after major Andre was hanged.
A particularly brutal little battle was fought between 1000 patriot militiamen and 1000.
loyalists militiamen at Kings Mountain in back country, South Carolina.
The American militia companies working without an overall commander managed to surprise and then surround
a loyalist camp. After an hour of fighting in their commander dead the loyalist tried to give up but
either from confusion or from a desire to extend their enemy Carlton's quarter.
The Americans continued firing. Intel 300 loyalists lay dead and another 160 wounded.
Eventually, the killing stopped and the remaining 600 loyalists were taken prisoner.
But a few days after the Battle of viciousness continued, as patriot militiamen started holding summary
court martials of captured loyalists, and nine men were hanged before one of the Patriot leaders stepped
in and put a stop doing. The immediate impact of Kings Mountain was to turn the tide in the Carolina
back country, marking the rise of the Patriots and the decline of the loyalists and forcing Cornwallis
to reconsider his plans. After receiving very little in the way of support from North Carolina loyalists,
and now sensing trouble in his rear, Cornwallis pulled out of Charlotte and headed back to South Carolina.
Meanwhile, the Continental Congress suitably chastened by their decision to ignore Washington's advice
and put gates in charge of the South passed a resolution leaving it to the commander in chief to select
the next leader of the Southern department. Washington appointed Nathaniel green the same day he received
the order. Green, as you will recall, had started as an eager young officer who had promised to hold
Fort Washington and then promptly lost Fort Washington.
He then moved on to being a pretty competent subordinate commander during the campaigns in New Jersey
and Philadelphia. Near the end of the winter at Valley Forge, green was appointed Quartermaster general
with the Continental Army, a thankless and gruelling task that he performed well, in spite sulking a
bit that no one has ever heard of a Quartermaster general in history.
He was led out on parole to go take part in the siege of Newport, and then successfully resigned the
quartermaster post in 1780. As we just saw, Washington tried to get him appointed to the Southern Command,
but it took gates botching the job for green to get his chance to earn the spot in history he had been
craving. Green took with him Baron von stuben, who wound up in Virginia organising the supply lines
a job, I'm sure green relish not having to deal with himself.
He also had with him a guy whose name I tried to shield you from since we've already got way too many
names flying around. But now he's unavoidable. Daniel Morgan.
Morgan was the leader of that crack sharpshooter company that had done so much damage at Saratoga.
He technically had retired in 1779 after being passed over her promotion.
But when Congress offered him a brigadier general ship, he took it and headed for the Carolinas.
When green and Morgan arrived at the Hillsboro camp in late November 1780.
They found a scene not unlike the scene that had greeted Horatio gates earlier in the year 1400 men
in bad shape with little to eat, rags to wear the usual lot for the common continental soldier.
Green then moved down to the American camp outside of Charlotte and found it not only smaller and more
pathetic, but also plagued by internal rivalries between the various leaders of the North Carolina militias.
In all, green commanded now about 2000 men, most not in great shape.
In an ultimately inspired but what looked according to every rule in the book as a lunatic decision,
Greene decided to divide his smaller and weaker army into two branches, hoping that by doing so he could
not only drum up recruits in multiple areas simultaneously, but also hoping that it would force Cornwallis
to divide up his own forces. And the more divided the British, the better.
So in late December 17, at Daniel Morgan and about 600 men a mix of continental and Milan Sherman went
west up the Qatada River. In January the second Cornwallis sent Colonel Tarleton and his Legion off
in pursuit. The two forces manoeuvred around each other, with Morgan picking up recruits and Tarleton
receiving reinforcements. until both were leading just over 1000 men.
Morgan eventually decided that Tarleton was good enough a tactician to trap him one of these days, so
he selected a site to make a stand at a spot called Hanna's cow pens.
Morgan's choice was a terrible one by conventional standards, because flanks were wide open to cavalry
attacks, and he put a river in his back making retreat impossible.
But Morgan later said that this was the idea. The problem with the militiamen is that they run they
don't have anywhere to run, maybe they'll fight. Then he added another dimension asking the militia and
only to fire to volleys and then fall back behind the sterner Continentals.
So I'm not asking you to stand up to the cream of the British Army here just fire to volleys and then
you can get the hell out of there. You can do that much kancha.
And it turns out that they could. On the morning of January the 17th tarlton led his men up in a conventional
line on a frontal assault of Morgan's position on a low hill at the cow pens.
The militiamen did their job firing to volleys into the British and then falling back.
Tarleton took this understandably is the American to once again running for it and he ordered his men
to charge in, but all they found was the core of Continentals waiting for them.
gunfire gateway to a bayonet charge, and suddenly it was the British, not the Americans who were falling
back. Then the militiamen who had supposedly run off reappeared on their flanks and the British started
getting enveloped, and then they started surrendering.
After an hour of fighting, they lost 100 dead, another 200 wounded and over 800 captured, Carlton himself
managed to just barely get away and bring to Cornwallis the thoroughly unhappy news that most of their
best troops had just been captured. Cornwallis immediately took off in pursuit of Morgan, but his intelligence
network was by now in total collapse, and he set off down the wrong road in the wrong direction.
Meanwhile, Nathaniel Greene got word of the Battle of cow pens, and rode off with a small escort to
link up with Morgan and guide him back to the rest of the army, which green had ordered to start pulling
back to Virginia to regroup. What followed was the so called race to the Dan, the Dan river, marking
the boundary between North Carolina and Virginia. Green linked up with Morgan on January the 31st.
Cornwallis shed all his baggage, and the two army spent the next week racing North often just miles
apart through terrible weather with every Ford at every river swollen my reign.
as they approach the dam, Cornwallis was once again tripped up by bad intelligence, thinking there was
no good place to cross downstream, Cornwallis swung west to head off green and Morgan, but there was
a spot to cross downstream where the rest of the Americans were waiting for their Conrad's to appear.
Now at full strength, green wanted to make a stand right there, but he was talked out of it and the
Americans started crossing into Virginia. When Cornwallis finally appeared after being led around on
a wild goose chase, he had no way himself to cross the river as all the boats had been pulled to the
other side. Frustrated, Cornwall is pulled back to Hillsboro, where he tried and basically failed to
raise some loyalist militia companies to augment his forces.
By now, he was totally despairing of his ability to hold on to the Carolinas.
But about a week after the Americans crossed into Virginia, green received some bad intelligence of
his own, that the recruitment drive in North Carolina was working, and that if he didn't act fast, Cornwallis
might command an unbeatable army. So on February 23, green LED his men back into North Carolina.
The two armies manoeuvre around each other for another two weeks, and it was soon apparent that the
Americans actually now outnumber the British something like 40 502,000.
But even with this disparity, it was Cornwallis who decided to finally press for an attack on March
15, the American camp at Guildford courthouse in northern North Carolina.
Green was ready for the attack and have the superior numbers but the British were as always more disciplined
than the American militia companies. And despite being out number two to one, the British just kept
coming and coming until the Americans retreated most in good order, the rest not so much.
For Cornwallis, the battle at Guilford Courthouse was the quintessential Pyrrhic victory.
He had won the battle and held the field. But he had lost something like a quarter of his men in the
process. He couldn't pursue green and he couldn't stop the spread of news that the British were spread
then and losing control of the Carolinas. loyalists morale was devastated.
The Patriots were exuberant. The momentum had shifted decisively.
Next week, we will See what both Cornwallis and green thought of their respective chances in the Carolinas
as Cornwallis pulled out and green dove in? Not the Cornwall's his troubles were over when he ditched
the Carolina swamp. Its next base of operations would be on the Chesapeake Bay, at a place called Yorktown,
Virginia.