Hello and welcome to revolutions.
Episode 20 to supplement
the Declaration of Independence
The unanimous Declaration of the
thirteen united States of America.
In Congress July 4th 1776.
When in the course of human events it
becomes necessary for one People to dissolve the
Political Bands which have connected them with another
and to assume among the powers of
the earth the separate and equal station to which
the Laws of Nature and of Nature's God
entitle them a decent respect to the
opinions of mankind requires that they should
declare the causes which impel
them to the separation.
We hold these truths to be self-evident that
all men are created equal that they are
endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable
Rights that among these are Life
Liberty and the Pursuit of Happiness That
to secure these Rights Governments are
instituted among Men deriving their just powers
from the consent of the governed That
whenever any Form of Government becomes destructive of
these ends it is the right of the
People to alter or to abolish it and
to institute new Government laying its foundation on
such Principles and organizing its Powers in such
form as to them shall seem most likely
to affect their Safety and Happiness.
Prudence indeed will dictate that Governments long
established should not be changed for
light and transient causes.
And accordingly all experience hath shown that
mankind are more disposed to suffer while
evils are sufferable than to right themselves by
abolishing the forms to which they are
accustomed. But when a long train of
abuses and usurpations pursuing invariably the same
Object evinces a designed to reduce them under
absolute Despotism it is their right it is
their duty to throw off such Government and
to provide new Guards for their future
security. Such has been the patient sufferance of
these colonies and such is now the
necessity which constrains them to alter
their former Systems of Government.
The history of the present King of Great
Britain is a history of repeated Injuries and
Usurpations all having in direct object the
establishment of an absolute Tyranny over
these States. To prove this let Facts
be submitted to a candid world.
He has refused his Assent to Laws the
most wholesome and necessary for the public good.
He has forbidden his Governors to pass
Laws of immediate and pressing importance unless
suspended in their operation tell his Assent should
be obtained and when so suspended he
has utterly neglected to attend to them.
He has refused to pass other Laws for
the Accommodation of large Districts of People
unless those People would relinquish the Right
of Representation in the Legislature a
Right inestimable to them and
formidable to tyrants only.
He has called together Legislative Bodies
at Places unusual uncomfortable and distant
from the depository of their public Records for
the sole purpose of fatiguing them into
compliance with his measures.
He has dissolved Representative Houses repeatedly
for opposing with manly firmness his
invasions on the Rights of the people.
He has refused for a long time after
such dissolutions to cause others to be elected
whereby the Legislative powers incapable of Annihilation
have returned to the people at
large for their exercise the state remaining in
the meantime exposed to all the dangers
of invasion from without
and convulsions within.
He has endeavoured to prevent the population of
the state for that purpose obstructing the
Laws for Naturalization of Foreigners refusing
to pass others to encourage their
migrations hither and raising the conditions
of new Appropriations of land.
He has obstructed the Administration of Justice
by refusing his Assent to Laws for
establishing Judiciary Powers.
He has made Judges dependent on his Will alone
for the tenure of their offices and the
amount and payment of their salaries.
He has erected a multitude of New Offices
and sent hither swarms of Officers to harass
our People and eat out their substance.
He has kept among us in times of
peace Standing Armies without the consent of our
legislatures. He has affected to render the
Military independent of and superior to the
civil power he has combined with others to
subject us to a jurisdiction foreign to our
constitution and unacknowledged by our laws giving
his Assent to their Acts of pretended
Legislation For quartering large Bodies of Armed Troops
among us For protecting them by a
mock Trial from Punishment for any Murders which
they should commit on the Inhabitants of
these States For cutting off our Trade with all
parts of the world For imposing Taxes on
us without our Consent For depriving us in many
cases to the benefits of Trial by Jury
For transporting us beyond the seas to be
tried for pretended offenses For abolishing the
free System of English Laws in the
neighboring province establishing there in an
arbitrary government and enlarging its Boundaries so as
to render it at once an Example
and fit instrument for introducing the same
absolute rule into these Colonies For taking
away our Charters abolishing our most valuable
Laws and altering fundamentally the Forms
of our Governments For suspending our
own Legislatures and declaring themselves invested
with Power to legislate for
us in all cases whatsoever.
He has abdicated Government here by declaring us
out of his Protection and waging war on
us. He has plundered our seas ravaged our
Coasts burnt our towns and destroyed the lives
of our people. He is at this time
transporting large Armies of foreign Mercenaries to
complete the works of death desolation and
tyranny already begun with circumstances of
Cruelty and Perfidy scarcely paralleled in the
most barbarous ages and totally unworthy
the Head of a civilized nation.
He has constrained our fellow citizens taken captive
on the high seas to bear arms
against their Country to become the executioners of
their friends and Brethren or to fall
themselves by their hands.
He has excited domestic insurrections among us
and has endeavoured to bring on the
Inhabitants of our frontiers the merciless Indian
Savages whose known Rule of Warfare is
an undistinguished destruction of all ages sexes
and conditions in every stage of these
oppressions we have Petitioned for Redress in
the most humble terms Our repeated
Petitions have been answered
only by repeated injury.
A Prince whose Character is thus marked by every
act which may define a Tyrant is unfit
to be the ruler of a free people.
Nor have We been wanting in
attentions to our British brethren.
We have warned them from time to time
of attempts by their legislature to extend an
unwarrantable jurisdiction over us.
We have reminded them of the circumstances
of our immigration and settlement here.
We have appealed to their native justice and
magnanimity and we have conjured them by the
ties of our common kindred to disavow
these usurpations which would inevitably interrupt
our connections and correspondence.
They too have been deaf to the
voice of justice and of consanguinity.
We must therefore acquiesce to the necessity
which denounces our Separation and hold them
as we hold the rest of mankind Enemies
in War in Peace Friends We therefore the
Representatives of the United States of
America in general Congress assembled appealing
to the Supreme Judge of the world for the
rectitude of our intentions do in the name and
by Authority of the good people of these
Colonies solemnly publish and declare that these
United Colonies are and of Right ought to
be free and independent states that they are
Absolved from all Allegiance to the British
Crown and that all political connection
between them and the State of Great Britain is
and ought to be totally dissolved and that
as Free and Independent States they have full
Power to levy War conclude Peace contract
Alliances establish Commerce and do all other
Acts and Things which INDEPENDENT STATES
may of right do.
And for the support of this Declaration with
a firm resilience on the protection of
divine Providence we mutually pledge to each other
our Lives our Fortunes and our sacred
Honor.