Hello, and welcome to revolutions supplemental the Bill of Rights, amended amendment one, Congress shall
make no law respecting an establishment of religion, or prohibiting the free exercise thereof, or abridging
the freedom of speech, or of the press, or of the right of the people peaceably to assemble and to petition
the government for a redress of grievances. amendment to a well regulated militia being necessary for
the security of a free state, the right of the people to keep and bear arms shall not be infringed.
amendment three, no soldier shall, in time of peace be quartered in any house without the consent of
the owner, nor in time of war, but in a manner to be prescribed by law.
amendment for the right of the people to be secure in their persons, houses, papers and effects, against
unreasonable searches and seizures, shall not be violated, and no warrants shall issue but upon probable
cause, supported by oath or affirmation, and particularly describing the place to be searched and the
persons or things to be seized. amendment five, no person shall be held to answer for a capital or otherwise
infamous crime, unless on a presentment or indictment of grand jury, except in cases arising in the
land or naval forces, or in the militia, when in actual service in time of war or public danger.
nor shall any person be subject for the same offence to be twice put in jeopardy of life or limb, nor
shall be compelled in any criminal case to be a witness against himself, nor be deprived of life, liberty,
or property without due process of law, nor shall private property be taken for public use without just
compensation. amendment six, in all criminal prosecutions, the accused shall enjoy the right to a speedy
and public trial by an impartial jury of the state and district where in the crime shall have been committed,
which district shall have been previously ascertained by law, and to be informed of the nature and cause
of the accusation to be confronted with the witnesses against him to have compulsory process for obtaining
witnesses in his favour, and I have the assistance of counsel for his defence.
amendment seven in suits at common law are the value in controversy shall exceed $20.
The right of trial by jury shall be preserved, and no fact tried by a jury shall be otherwise re examined
in any Court of the United States. Then, according to the rules of the common law, amendment eight excessive
bail shall not be required, nor excessive fines imposed, nor cruel and unusual punishment inflicted.
amendment nine, the enumeration in the Constitution of certain rights shall not be construed to deny
or disparage others retained by the people. amendment 10 the powers not delegated to the United States
by the Constitution, nor prohibited by it to the state are reserved to the states respectively or to
the