This week's episode is brought to you by Harry's razors.
So you go to the drugstore to pick up some razors.
First, you have to find the guy who can open the case, then you have to wait around while he finds the
keys to the case. And then when the case finally gets open, your reward is paying 25 bucks for four
blades and some shaving cream. You leave muttering obscenities about the waste of time and money.
Such was the last straw for Andy, one of the co founders of Harry's razors, who was convinced that there
had to be a better way and there was focused on providing guys a great shaving experience where a fraction
of the price of the competition Harry's razors offers high quality blades engineered in their very own
German factory. Order online, it gets shipped to your home.
It's simple. I've got my own kit working for me as we speak, the blades are sharp, the razor design
is clean, which I like. And the cream is exactly what I need it to be no cuts, no irritation, it's great.
And plus, I don't have to wait around for the guy with the keys just to pay way too much for it all.
So stop overpaying for a good shave and go to harrys.com use the promo code revolutions say $5 off your
first purchase at again harrys.com promo code revolutionsHello, and welcome to revolutionsEpisode 31.
The Rising Sun.Today marks the end of our run through the American Revolution, a revolution that wound
up taking more than 25 years to work through from the end of the French and Indian War in 1763.
To the sitting of the first Congress of the United States in 1789.
It started as a simple protest against an unpopular tax had somehow ballooned into a full scale war
for independence, and then resulted in the founding of a new American Republic.
Today, that new American Republic will vote on whether to adopt a new constitution to replace the existing
Articles of Confederation. It was a vote that would expose the deep divide within the revolutionary
generation about what the point of the revolution had even been.
We left off last time with the call for a convention to amend the Articles of Confederation.
This call was officially endorsed by the Congress of the Confederation on February the 21st 1787.
And so the convention was set to meet in Philadelphia in May.
In the intervening months, state legislatures began selecting delegates.
Not surprisingly, the men most willing to pack up and head to Philadelphia for the summer tended to
be men already predisposed to greatly enhancing the power of the national government.
Those who didn't care one way or the other obviously had no motivation to take part.
Well, those who actively oppose the project tended to boycott the convention as good for example, Patrick
Henry, who refused to serve as a member of Virginia's delegation because he smelt a rat in Philadelphia.
Unfortunately, for those opposed to amending the articles, their absence simply pack the convention
with men totally in favour of wholesale revisions.As the convention approach though, there was genuine
fear among the delegates that their recommendations would not be taken seriously.
So it was essential to secure the presence of the two men who would lend instant credibility and gravitas
to the proceedings. The first was Benjamin Franklin, recently returned from half a lifetime in Europe.
Franklin was breaking down physically, then had the convention been held anywhere in Philadelphia, he
could not have attended, but it was, and he believed in the cause.
So he lent his fame and prestige to the project. But the real key was, of course, George Washington,
it took a bit of products and Washington had just spent a whole war, dreaming of retirement.
But he did believe deeply in the goal of a strong national government, and was always susceptible to
the romance of setting aside personal interest in doing your public duty.
And so he agreed to leave Virginia's delegation, his presence guaranteed that the convention could not
just be dismissed.The Constitutional Convention as we now call it, was supposed to begin on May the
14th 1787. But 18th century travel being one it was almost no one was there on time.
But one guy who was there on time, who had gotten there early, in fact, was James Madison of Virginia,
who it has taken us the entire series to get to, but who is probably my favourite of the so called founding
fathers, probably because I studied political theory in school and political theory was the water within
which James Madison swam.James Madison was born in 1751.
So he was a little too young to be a major player in the run up to the War of Independence, and then
standing at just five foot four inches and weighing noMore than 100 pounds, he was just too small to
be a soldier, which is why it has taken us the entire series to get to him.
Like the other leading Virginians, Madison inherited a lot of land and a lot of slaves.
But when it came time for the young man to pick a college, he did not follow his aristocratic brother
into the College of William and Mary, and instead headed up to the College of New Jersey, which is now
Princeton University. Now, I don't know how much of a role that kind of cross colonial experience played
in his eventual emergence as a strong proponent of national government, but it did certainly give him
a unique perspective.He spent the warrior serving in the Virginia House of Delegates where he came under
the sway of Thomas Jefferson, forging the political alliance that would define the first few decades
of American history. If I ever get around to writing that history of the political parties I'm always
talking about just know that Thomas Jefferson and James Madison will dominate the early episodes.
During his off hours, Madison read voraciously from the ancient Greeks to enlightenment philosophers
like Locke and Hobbes and of course, another favourite of mine Montesquieu, whose theories about separated
power struck a deep chord with Madison see develop a thoroughgoing critique of the Articles of Confederation.
He was a prime mover in the push to amend the articles.
So when it came time to finally get down to business in May 1787, he couldn't wait to get to Philadelphia
with his briefcase full of ideas. He's basically the kids so eager to take the task that he gets to
school like six hours early, and then drumming his fingers impatiently, waiting for the other knuckleheads
to show up so we can blow them all out of the water.
The rest of the knuckleheads started showing up by the end of May, and no, of course, they're not knuckleheads.
This is widely seen as one of the more impressive assemblies of leaders in American history.
Washington and Franklin were there of course, but also Alexander Hamilton of New York and a powerhouse
Pennsylvania delegation that included Robert Morris, the financer of the revolution, who deserves a
supplemental, Governor Morris no relation, and then James Wilson, who along with Madison would come to
dominate the proceedings. Also present was john Dickinson, now representing Delaware and who, frankly,
I'd kind of like to write a book about at this point.
The Virginia delegation included Peyton Randolph and George Mason, who were both early radicals and
deeply committed patriots who will also wind up opposing the Finnish constitution.
I could go on like this, but seriously, every state seem to be sending its best men.
Every state that is but Rhode Island, who refused to send any delegates to this ridiculous farce of
a convention.nodding approvingly from across the Atlantic, Thomas Jefferson called the delegates, nothing
less than an assembly of demigods. Or if you want to be less rapturous about it, you could call them
a bunch of rich white guys looking to make sure the little people didn't get ahold of the levers of
power.On May the 25th, there was finally a quorum of seven states, then business could begin.
Franklin nominated Washington to be president, and deliberations got underway.
Now unfortunately for historians, as the delegates started taking the floor, it was quickly agreed that
the only way this was going to work was if their debates were kept secret.
So detailed records of who said what, when just don't exist.
And we have to rely on informal vote counts and diary entries and a few scribbled summaries to get us
through it. This was probably not such a bad thing, especially since one of the other things they agreed
to right off the bat was that they were going to ignore whatever limited mandate they had to amend the
Articles of Confederation, and probably just rewrite the whole thing from scratch.
There was some brief protest to this, but as I said, the kind of guys who were willing to serve as delegates
were also the kind of guys predisposed towards overhauling the articles.
So the decision to press on with a whole new constitution met very little opposition.
And because Madison had gotten there first, and already had a pretty detailed outline for a new constitution
in hand. The convention voted on May the 29th to take his work, dubbed the Virginia Plan as their starting
point.A few alternative plans popped up along the way, including a proposal by Charles pickney of South
Carolina and a proposal by Alexander Hamilton and then the New Jersey or small state plan that we'll
talk about in a minute. But through it all, the Virginia Plan was the plan that everyone agreed to work
with, and it contained most of the defining features of the Constitution final draft, the bicameral
legislature, the independent executive, the independent judiciary, all based on Montesquieu theories
of separated power, which Montesquieu had developed after reading our old old friend polybius, his analysis
of the Roman Republic.So the first major innovation contained in Madison's Virginia Plan was the separation
of the legislative branch into two houses. almost uniformly the delegates were small are Republicans,
not small d Democrats. So they agreed that some kind of Upper House would be needed to put the brakes
on the runaway anarchie shirt.billowing out of the lower house.
This is where, for example, Shays rebellion helps frame the debate.
No one thought it was a good idea to just let the people run amok.
I mean, they'll come in one day and just vote to abolish debt and contracts.
Plus they had the example of the Pennsylvania State Government meeting right down the street.
Pennsylvania had wound up drafting one of the most democratic constitutions in American history, with
an all powerful unicameral legislature. To men like Madison and Hamilton.
This was like completely crazy, and led to wild swings in policy.
Every time one of the bitter Pennsylvania political factions was able to outvote its rivals.
So yeah, some kind of Upper House was needed a more deliberative body made up of the better sorts.
Let's call it a Senate, like the old stoic Romans used to havethe next major overhaul was to the executive
branch. Now aside from talk, in some circles that George Washington ought to be crowned king was kind
of taken for granted that the executive would be some kind of elected official serving some kind of
fixed term. But in Madison's plan, the executive would not be some your execute or have the legislature's
demand. The lack of a strong executive was seen as one of the great failings of the Articles of Confederation.
So the office would instead be independent, and invested with unique powers of its own, that would allow
it to check the scourge of a tyrannical legislature, just as the unique powers invested in the legislature
would allow it to check the scourge of a tyrannical executive, how the President, as the executive assumed
Doug would be elected and for how long he would serve, would all soon be points of contention.
But it was agreed in principle that an independent executive was essential for the stable and just operation
of government. And obviously, that everyone knew the first president would be George Washington helped
quell any fears of immediate tyranny.Finally, there was the matter of the courts.
Now, the appointment of judges turned out to be an area Madison thought executives traditionally wielded
too much power. unchecked, the appointment power becomes a key instrument of tyranny.
So it's one of those things they had fought about during the English revolution, whether the king would
have the power to remove judges at his pleasure, or whether there had to be a legitimate case for dismissal.
If a king or governor or president has unlimited power of appointment, well, then the courts are just
going to do whatever the king or governor or president wants, and that's no good at all.
So the Virginia Plan placed judicial appointments in the hands of Congress.
But there's, of course wind up simply handing the tools of tyranny to the fickle mob, rather than some
power hungry tyrant, which was in many ways scarier to our small our republican delegates, which is
how we wound up with the compromised system whereby the President nominates judges and the senate confirms
them.As the delegates walked through the Virginia Plan, the first major point of contention was over
the issue of congressional representation. Being a good Virginian, Madison had devised a system of proportional
representation based on population size. This was of course a deal breaker for the smaller states like
Delaware, New Jersey and Connecticut, who could see their interest counting for very little in the United
States of Virginia. So, an alternate proposal was introduced by William Paterson of New Jersey, hence
it being dubbed the New Jersey plan.This plan was in its essence exactly what the convention was supposed
to have been about. It was drawn up as a list of amendments to the Articles of Confederation that would
maintain the supremely powerful single house of Congress and preserve the rule of one state, one vote,
while granting the national government more power to tax and regulate trade and enforce compliant with
a drops. In terms of overall form, the New Jersey plan went nowhere.
But that issue of is Congress and assembly of the state, or an assembly of the people was not going
to go away.After a few weeks of fruitless debates, the question was referred to a committee where the
famous Connecticut Compromise was hashed out. It was called the Connecticut Compromise because it was
hashed out by Roger Sherman of Connecticut, who gets a special shout out for being the only guy who
signed the Continental Association, the Declaration of Independence, the Articles of Confederation, and
in a couple months, the Constitution of the United States.
So good work, Roger Sherman,Sherman Steele was that the legislature would have the two houses prescribed
by Madison, lower house the House of Representatives would be based on population or the Upper House,
the Senate would be based on states, specifically two senators per state.
To help seal the deal with Madison, Hamilton and the other big state advocate.
It was stipulated that all revenue bills would originate in the population based Lower House, which
is how it still works today, in case you fell asleep during sophomore government class.
With these basic issues work through the convention created the Committee of Detail in late July to draw
up an official rough draftThis committee spent the next 10 days cobbling together sections of the Virginia
Plan approved language from the deliberations, various parts of state constitutions and whatever was
still viable from the Articles of Confederation. They reported out a preamble and 23 articles on August
the sixth, that mostly conformed to what had been agreed to, with a few rather glaring exceptions.
at the behest of Southern members, the committee had taken it upon itself to insert clauses that restricted
Congress's ability to interfere with slavery, and set the bar for approval of tariffs at two thirds
super majorities in both houses, both designed to protect the southern economy from Northern meddling.
It also tried to ignore the approved language, that Congress would have the power to legislate, quote,
over all cases of general interest. And instead, it drew up a list of 18 enumerated areas that Congress
would be given jurisdiction over. But James Wilson of Pennsylvania killed this by tacking on at the
end, a 19th clause that said, Oh, and also Congress can pass any laws it deems necessary and proper for
the execution of government. In other words, go ahead and ignore that enumerated list.
When the Committee of Detail reported this draft, it was pretty well received, and most of it made its
way into the final draft. But the slavery and trade issues stuck out like sore thumbs and led to a whole
new round of wrangling. Luckily, the slavery issue also touched on one of the other big points yet to
be decided, because though it had been agreed that the House of Representatives would be rooted in proportional
representation, was not yet agreed how those proportions would be calculated to paint with a large brush.
The southern delegates wanted their slaves counted, the northern delegates did not.
This, of course, was the opposite of the positions taken during the debate over the Articles of Confederation,
when population size was about to become the basis of determining each state's financial obligation
to the national government. In that case, the North wanted slaves counted, and the South did not.
So clearly, everyone was working from a mentality of now make whatever argument gets you the most while
costing you the least.Finally, the two sides agreed to a set of compromises that settled everything
neatly. And without any troubling moral implications at all.
The South, gave up the two thirds majority requirement for tariffs, and agree that the final number
used to a lot seats in the House would also be used to determine financial obligations to the national
government. In exchange, the North agreed that that number would be calculated by adding up the free
population plus three fifths of all other persons, everyone knowing exactly what all other persons meant.
So right there in Article One, section two of the United States Constitution, it explicitly states that
an African American is three fifths of a person. Oh, by the way, it also says that Indians who do not
pay taxes are not even people at all. So yeah, like I say, no troubling moral implications at all.
With this compromise in place, the delegates decided that that was about all the heat they could stand
for the moment and they wrote in a clause for bidding Congress from taking any action on slavery for
25 years. Everyone agreed it would be much easier to just kick the can down the road on that one.
As the summer wound down, the SOTU did the convention, and on August the 31st, they created the committee
of postpone parts to take up the grab bag of leftover issues, a committee that was intentionally stacked
with delegates who have demonstrated a willingness to cut deals and make compromises.
Mostly, this was about crafting more precise language about how patents would be handled in the legal
process warmaking. But this last committee did lower the term of the president from seven to four years
and sanction the right to re election, which was actually a fairly big thing to just slip in at the
last minute. It also drew up the final language for the electoral college system of presidential elections,
which don't even get me started about the Electoral College.
Everything was then handed to the committee for style on September the eighth for a final write up.
This committee was run by Madison Hamilton and Governor Morris, who actually gets most of the credit
for writing the final draft, including the famous preamble.
The committee for style produced its final draft on September the 12th.
rearranging the previous 23 articles into seven Main articles, each divided into subsections, which
is why lawyers quote the constitution article two section three, the way a preacher quotes the Bible,
chapter and verse.Article One dealt with the legislative branch, since everyone assumed that that would
be the most important branch. They would come as quite a shock to the framers to see just how presidential
the government of the United States has become.Article two dealt with the executive branch run by a
president elected every four years with the power to appoint judgesveto laws and act as commander in
chief of the armed forces.article three covered the judicial branch, which is actually pretty hilariously
underdeveloped in the actual text of the Constitution, with no mention whatsoever of the power of judicial
review. That is the ability to declare laws unconstitutional, which is obviously like what the Supreme
Court actually does these days. If you stayed awake in sophomore government, you know that that power
was simply asserted by Chief Justice john Marshall in the 1803 case, Marbury vs.
Madison, which is something you can needle your friends about.
They ever start going on about how they want strict construction as judges because a strict constructionist
judge would have to admit that the supreme court does not have the power to declare laws unconstitutional.
Article four covered relations between the federal government and the states and then between the states
themselves. Article five covered the amendment process.
Article six establishes the constitution as the supreme law of the land.
And article seven lays out the ratification process, which we'll get to in a minute.
On September 15, these seven articles were unanimously approved by the 11 states able to vote, Rhode
Island never did send anyone and Alexander Hamilton to New York colleagues had been among the 13 delegates
who quit the convention early. So New York didn't have a vote led to the nice line in Washington's diary
that the constitution was approved by 11 states and Colonel Hamilton.
39 men wound up signing the Constitution, with only three of the remaining delegates refusing to sign
Peyton Randolph and George Mason of Virginia, and elbridge Gerry of Massachusetts.
All three of them have their reasons for opposing the draft.
But the most important for our purposes was it they did not contain some kind of enumerated Bill of
Rights, explicitly drawing the lines that no matter what the government would not be able to cross.
In hindsight, the omission of the Bill of Rights turned out to be a major unforced error for proponents
of ratification. But for whatever reason, they had never drawn one up and weren't about to do it.
Now at the last minute. A few delegates thought for example, the George Mason's push to tack one on
was just a stall tactic to torpedo the whole project.
So they ignored the issue and sign the damn thing on September the 17th 1787.
They could all go home.As the convention ended, Benjamin Franklin offered a final few memorable quotes
about what had been achieved. After remarking that the constitution was not perfect, and that every
one of them could point to something in particular they didn't like about it.
He told his fellow delegates that during their deliberations, he'd often considered the painting on
the back of the President's chair, depicting a sun on the horizon, without being able to tell whether
it was rising or sitting. But now at length, I have the happiness to know that it is a rising and not
a setting sun.Then, of course, there was the likely apocryphal line uttered as the delegates dispersed,
asked by Elizabeth Powell, who is by the by an utterly fascinating woman, what form of government the
convention had created, he said, a republic mme, if you can keep it.
But for the moment, the question was not whether this new model for national Republic would be kept.
But whether or not it would be launched in the first place.
As I mentioned, the deliberations of the convention had been secret, and no rumours swirled, it was
still something of a shock to discover that the states were about to be asked to vote not on a few amendments,
but on a whole new system of government. And not only that, the vote would take place according to rules
completely outside the system set up by the articles for ratifying amendments.
As I hinted last time, the requirement of unanimous consent was regarded as unworkable, giving everyone
a veto over everyone else, so that nothing would ever get done.
So the framers wrote into article seven that only nine of 13 states needed to ratify for the constitution
to take effect. Then, in another calculated bit of stacking the deck in their favour, they prescribed
that the process of ratification would run through state conventions specifically called to decide the
issue not I repeat, not through state legislatures.
This was critical, because no one would lose more power if the Constitution was ratified than the state
legislatures.The Congress of the Confederation received the signed constitution on September the 20th,
and voted A week later to send it to the states for ratification.
But even before this vote was taken, the war over ratification was underway.
Because though we've mostly been talking about the guys who favoured a stronger national government,
there was strong opposition in almost every state to the very idea of a stronger national government.
Seeing is how defeating centralised tyranny had been the whole point of the revolution.
And here we are not five years removed from the Treaty of Paris, and you want to hand the keys over
to some corrupt despot. And yes, we know Washington will be the first president but for God's sakesWhat
about the next president? And look, you've got standing armies in here and what is necessary and proper
even mean? And sounds like Congress is just going to be able to get their hands into everything.
Opponents of ratification were a diverse long and not at all unified, and they quickly fell prey to a
clever bit of political labelling. Proponents of ratification were calling themselves Federalists, and
they managed to dub their opponent anti Federalists, as if they were simply on renewal standing in the
way of America's rise to power, rather than what it's fair to actually call them the keepers of the
original revolutionary flame. In terms of ideological rhetoric, the anti Federalists can draw a straight
line all the way back to 1763. The Federalists on the other hand, had to somehow prove that that rhetoric
had been fine in its time, but we need to survive as an independent nation now, and it's time to get
real.Now one of the things I love about the Federalist anti federalist campaigns is that everyone's
revolutionary credentials were positively sparkling.
Anti Federalists like Patrick Henry and George Mason and George Clinton had given everything they had
to the Patriot cause and believe deeply, that the constitution was a betrayal of the revolution.
Just as Hamilton and Madison, Washington and Franklin had given everything they had to the Patriot cost,
and believe deeply that the constitution was the fulfilment of the revolution, thing that would guarantee
the survival of an American Republic.As the battle lines were being drawn, both sides picked up pins
and started railing against each other, often using well known Roman pseudonyms.
So the anti Federalists were Brutus, and Cato, and they argued that the constitution invested too much
power in the central government, that the President would soon enough be a king, that the long thought
for sovereignty of the state was being destroyed, that no Republic could survive if it tried to encompass
so vast an area and so many different people. And above all, they agree that the failure to include
a Bill of Rights was an unconscionable omission.On the other side, the Federalist ran with a campaign
that played up the support of Washington and Franklin, the existential threat posed by the current disunity
of the state. And the fact that the states themselves were not doing a very good job of running things.
But of course, the most famous batch of polemics that came out of the ratification campaigns, where
the Federalist set of 85 essays published in New York under the pseudonym Publius, after our old old
old friend Kubilius hilarious, and written by Alexander Hamilton, James Madison, and john J.
The most famous of these is probably federalist number 10, which argue that the National Union was a
necessary safeguard against internal factionalism and interaction, and pretty much demolished the argument
that a republic could only survive if it was small in size.
Number 10, written by Madison argued that in fact, the opposite was true that the larger the Republic,
the less likely it was to be hijacked by narrow interest groups.
Other Greatest Hits include number 51, which is the definitive statement on how the system of checks
and balances works. And number 78, written by Hamilton, which is the one that says that judicial review
is actually a thing, even if it's not there in the actual text.
Now, something I didn't know going into this was the anthem time the Federalist essays were not influential
at all. They were neither widely read, nor timely enough to sway opinion.
Today, of course, they are fundamental to understanding how the federal government is supposed to work
and are cited regularly in judicial opinions and act as basically an annotated reference manual to the
Constitution.The first state to ratify was Delaware, on December the seventh 1787.
The lower counties had suffered mightily under the Articles of Confederation, and without a strong port
of their own had to rely on the whims of New York and Pennsylvania for all trade.
ratification was swift and unanimous.Surprisingly, Pennsylvania became the second state to ratify surprising
because there were strong anti federalist feeling across the state.
Remember, these are the same guys who came up with the radically democratic unicameral legislature.
So the Federalists acted quickly and ruthlessly, to ratify the Constitution before opposition forces
could really organise themselves. The state ratifying convention was assembled on November the 20th.
And after furious debate seem to be headed for ratification, when opposition anti Federalists deserted
the hall to deny their opponents the necessary quorum to take the vote.
federalist delegates literally hunted down and dragged a few hiding anti Federalists back into the State
House, declared a quorum and voted for ratification on December the 12th.
New Jersey followed a few days later and ratified unanimously they being in the same basic situation
as Delaware than Georgia.followed with a unanimous vote of its own on January the second, because now
that they didn't have the British to protect them from Indian attacks, they needed the federal government,
Connecticut and join them all on January the ninth.
So this brought the movement to its first great test, Massachusetts.
still reeling from the anarchy of Shay's rebellion.
The leaders of Massachusetts who might have been inclined to try to go it alone, wound up fairly evenly
divided on the matter. When the state convention met on January the ninth.
They spent nearly a month at each other's throats.
But it would appear that the decisive break came when Sam Adams and john Hancock were persuaded to vote
yes, and bring along the bloc of voters they control.
Massachusetts ratified the constitution on February the sixth by a vote of 187 to 168.
It was a close thing, but it lent the ratification movement a huge dose of momentum.
I mean, if the boys in Boston or Ford, it can't be all bad.
But critically, the Massachusetts convention requested 19 alterations be made alterations that amounted
to a warning that unless some kind of Bill of Rights was attached to this thing, the new federal government
was going to be in deep trouble.The first state to say no, was naturally Rhode Island.
Having never sent delegates to the convention, the leaders of Rhode Island left it to a public referendum
that saw the odious national power grab shot down in a landslide.
This blip aside, though, Maryland voted to ratify in April, and then South Carolina in May, South Carolina,
also strongly urging the adoption of a bill of rights.
Something all federalist now took for granted would be one of the first things they took care of when
hopefully, the first Congress took its seat.So that meant that by June 17, at eight of the 13 states
had ratified, one short of the required nine.in that month, three states began to Liberation's Virginia,
New York and New Hampshire. If just one of them ratified the constitution would take effect.
But it was not lost on anyone that if something along the lines of say New Hampshire saying yes, but
Virginia and New York saying no, then it would be really difficult to proceed.
Nine of 13 states are not.In Virginia, the anti Federalists were led by the enormously influential Patrick
Henry, and lent considerable weight by George Mason and Peyton Randolph, who could say that they'd been
there when the thing was written, and they did not like what it said.
Virginia had every means at its disposal to proceed outside of a National Union.
And the most of fear from a bunch of small states banding together to dictate terms mighty Virginia.
it wound up being an incredibly close race. And until the vote was actually taken, no one knew which
way it would go, especially since everyone realised that Virginia's vote would be the vote to establish
the union. Except it turns out it really wasn't because New Hampshire ratified four days before the
Virginia vote, earning New Hampshire the title, the state that ratified the Constitution.
But the Virginians didn't know that yet. And so their vote maintain the solemn gravi toss that Virginians
like to attach to things they voted in favour 89 to 79.
But like Massachusetts, in South Carolina, they also demanded amendments, the Bill of Rights was now
a foregone conclusion.This put New York in a bind.
The state was pretty wildly anti federalist, and its dominant political leader George Clinton was prepared
to go it alone and had Virginia not ratified. I'm sure that's exactly what he would have done.
But Virginia did ratify. And so staying out of the Union was now a far trickier proposition.
The Alexander Hamilton led federalist did not have the votes to compel ratification.
But they did manage to produce one little trump card that did help convince Clinton to lay down his
guns. New York City itself was dominated by Federalists and they threatened to secede from the state
and join the union themselves if the rest of the state didn't get on board.
Clinton freed up just enough voters to let New York ratify 30 to 27.
On July the 26th. This left only North Carolina and Rhode Island out of the Union.
North Carolina wouldn't join until November 1789. Rhode Island would hold out until May 1790.
So first to declare independence. Last to ratify the Constitution.
God bless you, Rhode Island. I love you.With the Constitution in effect, elections for the inaugural
government were held over the winter of 1788 1789.
with George Washington, of course, elected president unanimously.
As I mentioned, one of the first orders of business for the new government would be to drop a list of
amendment that would satisfy all those calls for a bill of rights.
James Madison himself introduced a list of 12 in August 1789 10 of which would eventually be adopted.
These amendments are focused not on structural changes to the government, but rather on protecting individual
rights from state abuse. And they included all the Greatest Hits freedom of speech, freedom of the press,
freedom of religion, freedom from unreasonable search and seizure, guarantees of habeas corpus and trial
by jury and access to legal counsel. Accompanying This episode is a supplemental where I read the bill
of rights in full, please go listen to it. It encompasses just about everything I love about America.
And for all our faults and all of our mistakes. I believe the Bill of Rights will stand today and tomorrow
and forever as objectively worthy of universal admiration, and they should hang on the wall of every
classroom. Now that they have been adopted, we can close this chapter of the revolutions podcast.
And just in time to because in a few days, I will be flying to London for the first revolutions podcast
tour, where we will get to relive the glory of the English revolution and get fired up for the coming
French Revolution. Since I obviously can't do any real work during those 11 days, I'm going to have
to be gone for longer than the four weeks. So I am officially setting the break to end on oh look at
that Bastille Day.