This week's episode is brought to you by Audible, as you know, Audible is the Internet's
leading provider of audio entertainment with over 150000 titles to choose from.
When you're done with this episode, go to Audible Podcast dot com forward slash
revolutions that again, audible podcast, dot com forward slash revolutions.
By going to that address, you qualify for free ebook download.
When you sign up for a 30 day trial membership, there is no obligation to continue the
service and you can cancel anytime and keep the free book.
You can also keep going with one of the monthly subscription options and get great deals
on all future audio book purchases.
This time, I'm going to go with a double feature as both will be relevant for our latest
revolution 1776 by David McCullough, recommended by listener MC Sean and Common Sense by
Thomas Paine, recommended by listener Mia L..
Hopefully I'm pronouncing both of those right.
I haven't actually read 1776, but McCullough's other stuff has always been top notch and
common sense is, of course, one of the foundational texts of the American Revolution and
everyone ought to go through it at least once.
So when you're done with this episode, go to audible podcast dot com forward slash
revolutions so that they know who sent you.
Hello and welcome to revolutions.
Episode 17.
Ok. Welcome back to the show.
We are now, as you know, jumping a hundred years forward and three thousand miles to the
left to play out the tumultuous drama of the American Revolution, a tumultuous drama that
occasionally parallels and sometimes even explicitly recalls the tumultuous drama of the
English Revolution. But before we can get into the guts of it, we need to do a survey of
the stage and the players.
So today we'll do a quick and necessarily blunt tour of colonial North America who live
there. Why did they live there?
What did they do when they got there?
Then we can get into the good stuff about the colonists going crazy after parliament
started randomly taxing stuff at the end of the French and Indian War.
Broadly speaking, we divide the future United States into three big colonial chunks.
New England, the middle colonies and the southern colonies above New England was French
Canada and below Georgia with Spanish Florida.
There is a map of all this that revolutions podcast dot com.
For those of you who would like to follow along at home.
Now, each of these colonial regions was settled at a different time and for different
reasons. And on the eve of the revolution, the inhabitants of each lived very different
lives from one another.
Indeed, one of the great feats of the revolution was binding together.
The separate colonies into a single unit, something many revolutionary leaders feared was
impossible starting up in the North.
We have New England, which includes Massachusetts, Connecticut, New Hampshire and Rhode
Island. These days, New England also includes Maine and Vermont.
But on the eve of the revolution, Maine was still a part of Massachusetts, and Vermont
was populated by a bunch of unruly squatters who had not yet succeeded in breaking away
from New York. For our purposes, colonization of New England is a nice place to start
because it is an offshoot of the same Puritan movement that eventually led to the English
civil wars that we just covered.
Shortly after King James, the first came to power, a group of Puritan separatists decided
they couldn't hack the ungodly ways of the Church of England anymore and decamped for the
Netherlands. But a decade in Holland only convinced this congregation that Dutch was a
really hard language to learn.
And my 16/17, they got it into their heads to maybe start over again in the new world, as
we'll see in a moment. The English had by now planted a permanent settlement at Jamestown
in Virginia, and the Puritan dissenters applied for and received permission to set up a
colony of their own in Virginia.
But of course, when the first hundred colonists known to all American schoolchildren as
the pilgrims set sail on the Mayflower and 16 twenty, they were blown off course and
wound up landing on Cape Cod instead.
Undeterred, they elected to stay and found the Plymouth comedy.
The early years were, of course, tough for our fanatical Puritans, but with the help of
some friendly American Indians, they managed to survive, establish the permanence of the
colony and invite their brethren to follow and follow.
Their brethren did between sixteen, twenty eight and sixteen forty two.
About twenty thousand Puritans abandoned England for the new world.
And of course, as we all know by now, that period corresponds exactly to the era of
personal rule when both the monarchy and the church started drifting in a tyrannical
direction, at least according to the pittance.
There is even a nice little story that I passed over that during the early days of the
long parliament. An obscure backbench MP all over Craughwell noted that had Parliament
not passed the grand remonstrance in sixteen forty two, that he and his friends were
prepared to pack up and move to America, which means that world history was about 10
votes shy of all over Kromm while becoming an American as the Puritan diaspora continued
through the sixteen thirties.
The other core New England colonies were founded.
Connecticut came along officially in sixteen thirty six, founded by men looking for a
little more religious freedom than the men running Massachusetts allowed.
Because remember, religious freedom doesn't really mean religious freedom.
Shortly thereafter, the Earl of Work granted a patent to Lordes Brooke, and saying cele
to establish a settlement in Connecticut called Saybrook.
And as you'll recall, all three of those guys were in the inner circle of the
parliamentary revolt against Charles the first.
So the connections between New England and the men who were about to start a war with the
king ran very deep.
The little colony of Rhode Island was also founded in 16 36 by a guy named Roger
Williams, who was looking for more religious freedom than the men running Massachusetts
allowed. Rhode Island was the smallest colony and is the smallest state.
And it wound up being populated by a group of obnoxious free thinkers who just didn't fit
in anywhere else. As a result, Rhode Island tended to go its own way, as we will see.
They were very difficult to convince of the utility of non importation agreements.
They were the first colony then to declare independence from Britain and the last state
to ratify the U.S.
Constitution. There is just no accounting for Rhode Island.
Finally, we have New Hampshire, which started being settled shortly after Massachusetts
and basically became its own thing after 16 twenty nine.
Though the on-again off-again political connection to Massachusetts wouldn't be settled
until 16 ninety one.
New Hampshire was defined predominantly by small farming hamlets cut off from each other
by the local terrain economically.
The New England colonies were limited by the harsh land they planted themselves on, land
that would never support the kind of huge cash crop plantations that were growing up in
the southern colonies. So through the colonial period, they survived on small plots of
land for food and started to engage in trans-Atlantic trade with England, mostly
providing fish, lumber and fur to the mother country.
Through it all, the New Englanders a setting.
Rhode Island, of course, ran quasi democratic communities dominated by church leaders who
were trying to put into practice beliefs that had been stifled in England.
There were more than a few Puritans on both side of the Atlantic who saw the colonies as
a laboratory for ideas that could be put into practice.
Back in England. But of course, the restoration put an end to all that.
And rather than being the vanguard of a pure revolution in England, New England became
something of a time capsule as England resettled into its old, familiar traditions.
The dominant city of New England was, of course, Boston first settled in 16:30 and soon
became one of the main trading centres in North America as the surrounding towns and
villages shipped their produce overland to Boston for transit back to England.
On the eve of the revolution, Boston had a population of about 15000 and believe it or
not, they were not all fire-breathing radicals.
Moving south, we find the middle colonies, New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania and
Delaware. The middle colonies were settled under very different circumstances from New
England and under different circumstances from each other.
New York was, of course, initially populated by the Dutch who arrived in 16 13.
In between the founding of Jamestown and the founding of Plymouth, Dutch interest was
focused on the fur trade.
And they built a series of forts up the Hudson River to barter with the native Indians
for the lucrative furs in sixteen twenty six.
The leader of the Dutch merchants allegedly purchased the island of Manhattan for 60
Dutch guilders. Though the details of that deal are way more complicated than the old
legend about buying Manhattan for twenty four dollars worth of beads.
Anyway, the Dutch built New Amsterdam on the southern tip of the island serve as the
capital of the New Netherlands.
But the Dutch hold in North America was always precarious.
And after a series of wars with Britain, the New Netherlands were handed over to the
English in 16 74.
In exchange, the Dutch got to hold Suriname, which probably seemed like a better deal at
the time than it does today.
The English promptly renamed Everything New York after James Duke of York The Future
James the Second. Aside from the trade operating out of the now renamed New York City,
the economy of New York was dominated by huge, essentially feudal estates up the Hudson
River, where the landlords were able to wield extensive legal power over their tenants.
South of New York was New Jersey.
Starting in 16 38, the area was actually colonized by the Swedes and called New Sweden
until it was absorbed by the Dutch in 16 55, who then handed it over to the English in 16
74. King Charles, the second then gave it to his brother James as a gift.
And James turned the territory into a proprietary colony wherein huge tracts of land are
handed over to individuals or corporations who then act as a sort of private government.
Colonial New Jersey wound up being defined by a running conflict between small holding
farmers who trace their claims back to the initial Dutch and Swedish settlements and the
newly arrived English aristocracy who traced their claims to the proprietary grants from
the King. It was a conflict that would run right into and then get merged with the unrest
of the revolution. New Jersey would be reorganized as a royal colony.
That is one directly under the crown in 1:43, which I mention, so that I can mention that
the first royal governor of New Jersey was none other than Edward Hyde, the third Earl of
Clarendon, grandson of the Edward Hyde, who was so instrumental in the history of the
English Revolution.
Of course, this Edward Hyde wound up being so corrupt that he was stripped of his title
in 1788, whereupon New Jersey was governed by New York for the next 30 years.
Speaking of proprietary colonies, the biggest was established right next door to New
Jersey in sixteen eighty one to clear out old debts to the Penn family.
Charles the second granted William Penn control of an enormous tract of land in the new
world, making pan.
the single largest landowner in terms of square miles of any man in the British Empire.
William Penn was also a Quaker, one of those dissenting sacks that had flourished in the
chaos of 17th century England.
But now, though, the Quakers were defined mostly by their quiet pacifism.
And it was along those lines that Penn founded his colony, achieving probably the most
enlightened relationship with the native Indians of any of the North American colonies.
Though in time that pacifism became a huge sticking point because many of the settlers
who started filling up the colony were not Quakers.
Many indeed were German Lutherans settling on the western edges who dealt constantly with
Indian attacks. The tension within Pennsylvania between the Quaker leadership and
everyone else came to a head in a series of political battles that saw the Quakers
essentially admit that their principles were incompatible with the rough business of
actual governance.
Pennsylvania also boasted the city of Philadelphia, which on the eve of the revolution
had a population just north of 30000, was the largest and most cosmopolitan city in North
America, thanks in no small part to the efforts of its most famous citizen, Benjamin
Franklin, who I assure you we are about to have extensive dealings with.
The last of the middle colonies was Delaware and is the one that earns you trivia.
Bonus points, if you say that technically there were only 12 original colonies, not 13,
because Delaware, known as the three lower counties, were included in the sixteen eighty
one land grant to William Penn.
Though Penn quickly saw the utility of allowing the lower counties their own legislative
assembly, its attachment to Pennsylvania was always a little strange because as you can
see from the map, if anything, Delaware should have been a part of Maryland.
But it wasn't. And though it was technically a part of Pennsylvania, it achieved more
than enough de facto autonomy to be considered by everyone.
Both past and present to be its own colony.
The economy of the middle colonies was a mix of agriculture and trade.
The land was better than New England, and the barons of Hudson Valley, for example, were
able to run their operations like little kingdoms.
The Western frontier became populated with smallholder farmers, while the coastal areas
became dominated by merchants operating out of New York City and Philadelphia.
These two groups did not necessarily see eye to eye on how to run things.
The Western farmers always chafing under the thumb of the coastal elites.
That is to say, nothing, of course, of the battles fought between the colonies themselves
over boundary lines and access to resources as migrating families simply settled places
and dared anyone to try to kick them off.
So finally, we come to the southern colonies, Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina
and Georgia, with Maryland sort of hanging out as a border state.
The southern colonies, of course, developed a very different and far more pernicious
social and economic life.
But even still, there were differences among them.
First, we'll clear out the unique border colony of Maryland.
The land for which was handed over to the family of Lord Baltimore in 16 32.
Lord Baltimore was a devout Catholic, and he saw Maryland, which was probably named after
Queen Henrietta Maria, Catholic, wife of Charles, the first as a refuge for his rich
Catholic buddies. Because as much as the Puritans of England saw King Charles and
Archbishop Lott engaged in some popish plot, the Catholics of England knew better.
And like the Puritans on the other side of the religious spectrum.
Lord Baltimore saw the new world as a place to escape persecution.
But soon enough that original intent was washed away by the flood of Protestant settlers.
Coming up mostly from Virginia.
By sixteen forty nine, Baltimore had to give way, and he granted freedom of worship,
making Maryland the second colony after, you guessed it, Rhode Island to do so.
The great colony of the South and indeed the great colony of British North America was,
of course, Virginia, occasionally known as the Prussia of America.
By the time of the revolution, it would be the oldest, largest, richest and most populous
colony in North America.
And its leaders knew it.
After the mysterious false start that is the lost colony of Roanoke, a new settlement
called Jamestown was constructed beside the James River in 6:44.
For those of you who are interested in the whole sordid history of early Virginia should
read American Slavery, American Freedom by Edmund Morgan, which has surprisingly little
to say about slavery, but a great deal about the struggles, failures and hardships of
seventeenth century Virginia, including their persistent inability to grow enough food to
live despite having planted themselves in some of the most fertile soil in the world.
Initially, this was the result of the colonists themselves, a mix of indentured servants
and gentleman adventurers just not doing what it took to survive.
But then John Roffe discovered the miracle of tobacco, which became the cash crop of
British North America.
From then on, it wasn't so much about screwing around when you were supposed to be
working so much as refusing to be distracted from tobacco long enough to grow some food.
So early Virginia was a mess, but by the seventeen hundreds it had established itself as
the Old Dominion. And more than any other colony resembled the socioeconomic structure of
England with large landowners, really a collection of about one hundred families
dominating a population of indebted freeholders, indentured servants and African slaves.
These large landowners propped up the established Anglican Church, Virginia being the one
place in North America that the Church of England really took root.
And they all believe mightily in their rights as Englishmen, especially their right as
gentlemen landlords.
But the truly defining feature of economic life in Virginia, besides the complete
reliance on tobacco as both export commodity and means of internal exchange, was that
everyone from the largest plantation owner to the smallest little freeholder was deeply
in debt. Everyone bought on liberally extended credit from England.
They would always come due with the next tobacco crop.
And this caused more than a little tension.
I promise you. South of Virginia were the Carolinas founded in sixteen twenty nine and
named after our old friend Charles the first.
Carolina was established initially as one big proprietary colony.
But in 1712, the disaffected northern settlements broke away and the territory was
reformed as North Carolina and South Carolina.
Initially, the Carolinas followed the Virginia path in to plantation tobacco with a
smattering of pitch and lumber thrown in there.
But eventually South Carolina became deeply involved in the cultivation of rice in
Indigo. A newly discovered plant that was being used for dye, both commodities unique to
South Carolina will become sticking points in the Continental Congress.
As the Pan Colonial Alliance was taking shape.
South Carolina also house.
The only real city in the South Charleston.
Named after Guess Who, which grew to about 10000 people as the revolution broke out.
Now, the reason the southern colonies never developed major urban centers like the
northern colonies did was because the region had so many deep navigable rivers that any
landowner could just throw up a dock without needing to ship his commodity overland to a
central hub like they had to do up in the north with Boston, New York or Philadelphia.
South of the Carolinas was Georgia the last colony established, not founded until 1733.
Georgia was a proprietary colony dreamed up by James Oglethorpe and a group of benevolent
utopians who saw the colony as a way to rehabilitate and put to good use the desperate
poor of England.
But their excruciatingly detailed plans for how land would be allocated, what you could
grow, what you could import, and what you could export ran smack into the reality of,
well, life in Georgia, which was, for example, not conducive to growing silk, which the
proprietors of Georgia were convinced the colony ought to be hemorrhaging by now, facing
almost certain destruction.
Many of the poor colonies shipped over found life in Oglethorpe Utopia dangerously rigid
and fled to the relative freedom of Carolina.
The proprietors of Georgia finally gave up and 1752 and handed control of the colony back
to the crown. So in broad terms, that covers where the colonies came from, then a little
bit of what they were up to economically by the time the revolution broke out.
It is important to always remember as we walk through this, though, that the colonies
were very much separate entities from each other and they bickered constantly over land
and boundaries and access to resources, really only their shared attachment to England
uniting them. But there was at least one big similarity between them all their distance
from the mother country and said mother country's disinterest in them.
After all, we are talking about a collection of dissenters, secretaries and poor debtors
led them all to enjoy a great deal of local political autonomy.
Every colony had some kind of central assembly that engaged in practical administration,
dispensing of justice and, of course, taxing the inhabitants.
It should not be underestimated just how much the roughly century and a half of English
neglect influenced the course of the American Revolution.
It certainly helped transform some pretty innocuous taxes into a belief that tyranny and
slavery were just around the corner.
And that Segways us nicely into a discussion of the two groups we haven't talked about
yet, but who represent the deep hypocrisy that unfortunately lies at the heart of the
American Revolution.
Slaves and American Indians.
How can we reconcile the ideology of liberty and equality that fueled the revolution with
an all but genocidal policy towards the Indians and the stark reality of African slavery?
The answer is you can't really.
At least I can't. It's just something that is unavoidably there to take the American
Indians first. We obviously can't dive into a comprehensive history of native peoples in
the new world because for one, we're talking about dozens of individual tribes and
nations ranging from frozen Canada down to swampy Florida, the Iroquois, Shawnee,
Cherokee. These are all major nations with rich and unique histories all their own.
But what they shared in common was an encounter with Europeans that generally followed a
similar trajectory in all the colonies.
The first white men appear in small numbers and find themselves incapable of surviving in
the new world. These helpless colonists make contact with the local tribes and often
begin exchanging commercial products for food.
Once the European settlers establish themselves, more colonists arrive.
Indian land is encroached upon, leading to internment and an increasingly bitter
skirmishes and or massacres on both sides.
Then a combination of numbers, firepower and disease lead the Europeans to pretty quickly
get the upper hand and the Indians get pushed west.
By the mid seventeen hundreds, the Indians have been pretty well pushed off the eastern
seaboard, but they were able to maintain some kind of independence sovereignty by playing
the British off the French.
As long as there were two imperial powers competing for the fur trade and the affection
of the tribes. There was hope of national survival.
Certainly hope that the British American colonists would be confined to the land east of
the Appalachian Mountains.
This is what led the majority of Indians to fight with the French in the American theater
of the Seven Years War, which were about to talk about, and then hop over to side with
the British during the American Revolution.
Because, to put it bluntly, the worst case scenario for the Indians was to be left alone
on the continent with the Americans who were hungry for land and never really felt too
constrained by moral or political duty when it came to the Indians.
The subsequent history of Indian American relations, I think pretty well establishes that
those fears were not at all misplaced.
The other great hypocrisy deep in the heart of the revolution is, of course, slavery at
the time of the revolution.
There were about four hundred thousand slaves living in the U.S.,
mostly in the southern colonies.
They had been present from almost the beginning with the first nineteen Africans arriving
in Virginia in sixteen nineteen.
But for the rest of the century, African slavery was more of a supplement to the far more
common use of indentured servants as the colonial labor force.
Since mortality rates were so high in colonial America, it was cheaper to pay for seven
years labor than a lifetime of labor.
Since the labor was going to be dead in three years anyway.
But once mortality rates began to improve, it became increasingly common to invest in a
slave for life, since you would never have to let them go, nor deal with the pressure
from ex indentured servants who now wanted land and political rights.
So by seventeen hundred, the African slaves that had been getting mostly shipped to work
in the horrific sugar plantations of the British West Indies started being funneled north
to work the estates of major landowners, the kind of guys who could actually scrape
together enough cash to buy a slave.
Now, this point has been made 10000 times before, so there is no reason to belabor it,
but basically all the southern leaders of the American Revolution were slave holders and
they weren't conservative fence sitters either.
I mean, we're talking about George Washington, Thomas Jefferson, Patrick Henry, George
Mason, James Madison.
These were the guys who defined American liberty, fought a war to protect American
liberty, and then built a new government to preserve American liberty.
And they all owned slaves.
It's ridiculous. Now, had these guys followed through on the logic of their own argument
to its conclusion, that is that all men are created equal and like freed their slaves,
that is, had George Washington issued the Emancipation Proclamation.
The American Revolution would have been the greatest historical event in world history,
simultaneously tossing off the archaic bonds of monarchy and the evil chains of slavery.
But they simply couldn't see a way out of the economic implications of emancipation.
So the legacy of the revolution remains forever tarnished.
We'll wrap up today with the war to set the stage for the conflict between Britain and
her North American colonies in the United States.
We call it the French and Indian War.
It is known elsewhere as the Seven Years War.
A wide ranging conflict between France and Britain, which North America was simply one
theater of the war, technically started in 1754, but had been in the making for some
time. As the British began to colonize North America, the French got in on the action and
established a foothold in the far north along the St.
Lawrence River from their main bases in Quebec City and Montreal.
They grew up a primarily fur based trade network that extended deep into the interior.
Now, though, it took a while.
Eventually, British Colonial started pushing West in search of more land, and they ran up
against the French traders in the Ohio Valley.
Both sides claim sovereignty over the land and the local Indians were caught in the
middle. The resulting war is intricate enough and dramatic enough to sustain a multi
episode arc all its own from Braddock's initial disastrous march to Wolf's final victory
at the plains of Abraham. But for our purposes, we need only note that the British won
and the French lost. The final peace was signed in Paris in 1763, leaving the British in
sole control of North America.
The story of the American Revolution begins just as the ink is drying on the Treaty of
Paris. The cost of the war and the cost of their empire let Britain's political
leadership, both in parliament and the royal ministry to re-evaluate how that empire was
governed and financed, in many ways, their goal was both prudent and far sighted.
Make the colonies self-sufficient.
But the instruments they devised to achieve this goal were heavy handed, the manner they
were employed, clumsy.
The justifications offered downright arrogant.
So the story of the American Revolution owes at least as much to British bungling as it
does to American bravery patriotism valor etc.
etc. etc.
So next week we will kick things off with the first of two episodes covering the 17 60s
and early 70s 70s which saw American anger expand and contract in turn.
As the Stamp Act was passed and repealed the towns and Acts were passed and mostly
repealed and then the Tea Act was passed and now by then things had gotten out of hand.
Then we will move on into the campaigns of the Revolutionary War.
On our way to American independence and then finally the ratification of the United
States Constitution does either the ultimate embodiment of the ideals of the revolution
or an abject betrayal of the ideals of the revolution.
Depending on who you talk to.