This week's episode is brought to you by audible. As you know, audible is the internet's leading provider
of audio entertainment with over 150,000 titles to choose from.
When you're done with this episode, go to audible podcast.com forward slash revolutions, that again,
audible podcast.com forward slash revolutions. By going to that address, you qualify for a free book
download when you sign up for a 30 day trial membership, there is no obligation to continue the service
and you can cancel anytime and keep the free book.
You can also keep going with one of the monthly subscription options and get great deals on all future
audio book purchases. This time I am going to go with a recommendation from listener Daniel, but also
from revolutions tour alumnus Pete who told me about it on our trip and that is the historical novel
a place of greater safety. I haven't read it myself yet, but it chronicles the intertwined Adventures
of Robespierre, Denton and demola through the height of the French Revolution, and apparently it's pretty
engrossing. So when you're done with this episode, go to audible podcast.com Ford slash revolutions
so that they know who sent you. Hello, and welcome to revolutions Episode 3.8.
Today of the tiles. Last week, we saw the Royal ministry and the Paris Parliament battle over the big
financial reform package that had been cooked up to save the kingdom's bacon.
After accepting a few of the initial offerings. The Parliament then rejected the main pieces of the
puzzle, leading to a series of showdowns between the summer of 1787 and the spring of 1788.
To many an outside observer, it looked like the parliamo was gaining the upper hand, they had forced
the king to withdraw the stamp tax and stop pursuing the land tax.
And we're riding high on a wave of public acclaim.
But the Kings ministers are not yet ready to just give up completely.
And this week, we will see them make one last push to assert the kings will in the face of Parliament,
obstructionism, their solution, destroy the parliament.
But before we get into that, I want to backtrack a little and briefly cover the reaction of the provincial
parliament to Brian's reforms. Because though Paris was the centre of the action, there was lots of
noise being made out on the periphery, that will have a huge impact on what will happen in today's episode.
So let's wind back the clock to June 1787, when Brienne first started bringing in the reforms to the
Paris parliament. Now, as you will maybe recall, Brienne started with what I called the easy stuff,
turning the korovai into a money tax that seemed fine lifting regulations on the green trade, which will
I can promise you be hated by the lower classes. But remember, we're still talking about the Uber elite
here. They saw a more rational and more profitable system and said, Yeah, let's do it.
Then finally, the magistrate accepted the creation of provincial assemblies to assess and collect taxes.
Now, this breeze through the Paris Parliament who had little to fear and much to gain from these new
assemblies, and most of the areas under the jurisdiction of the Paris parliament, tax collection was
all handled by the royally appointed intendant and the much despised tax farmers.
So injecting a new institution composed of the wealthiest taxpayers like you know, us, was a welcomed
devolution of power. But in the outer provinces, where the parliament has already enjoyed a great deal
of autonomy, these new assemblies did not look to the local magistrates, like more power was being given
to them, but rather that power was being taken away.
They were further incensed when they saw the specifics of the plan, specifically, that there were no
specifics. The edict they were presented with was vague about both the jurisdiction and the scope of
the new assemblies. Plus, the order came with a really suspicious kicker, because the assemblies needed
to get to work right away, and it would take too long to set up the whole tiered process of lesser taxpayers
electing greater taxpayers to go represent them. The first members of the assemblies would be wait for
it, appointed by the king. In this, the provincial Parliament smelled a big, fat hairy rat.
complaints about the provincial assemblies were drawn up by the several regional Parliament with varying
degrees of intensity, usually arguing that the ministry was doing an end run around the long established
political constitution of France. But more than that, they were also just kind of opposed to the whole
idea of tax reform in the first place. Up until now, we've been talking about the Royal ministry.
The assembly of notables and the Paris parliament.
And in each of those three places, we've seen men either resigned to or openly pushing for a new tax
system. So for the first time now we're actually hitting on some nobles who were flat out against giving
up their tax privileges. These provincial nobles were not the super nobles living in Versailles and
Paris, they actually relied on their land to make up the bulk of their often meagre income, rather than
enjoying rich diversified portfolios, to say nothing of the fact that if this kept up there would be
very little to mark them out as special, whose tax privileges were a social calling card that they were
not prepared to give up of the Parliament that resisted the creation of the provincial assemblies.
The one that needs to be highlighted right now is the Parliament of Porto, monta scuse old stomping
ground. They were the political and judicial hub of a fairly prosperous port city that had long enjoyed
a great deal of autonomy. In July 1787, they issued a remonstrance back to the king saying that they
refuse to register the edict establishing the new provincial assemblies, until the jurisdiction and
scope of those assemblies was clearly laid out, which for the moment really wasn't.
They were stiff enough in their resistance that when the Paris parliament was exiled in August 1787,
the Bordeaux parliament was given the boot to letras de cachet exiled them from the regional capital
for the small town of libran. But unlike their brother magistrates in Paris, the exile did not make
them amenable to a compromise. It only made them matter.
So when the Paris parliament was recalled in September, the Bordeaux Parliament stayed in exile.
They would not be allowed to return home until just before the main edicts were issued, which were designed
to make them irrelevant. Despite the resistance though, the provincial assemblies began to convene in
November 1787 justice The king was going off script in the middle of that royal session we talked about
last time. As I mentioned, this first batch of assemblies were indeed appointed by the Royal ministry.
So the entire apparatus was obviously suspect, but just how suspect came down to how strongly the members
actually favoured the king. Because not everyone in the assembly was a staunch royal ally, there just
weren't enough of those guys to go around. Some of the members were there to do the king's bidding for
sure. But others wound up full of guys like for example, the Marquis de Lafayette, who were eager to
steer the assemblies in the direction of independent mindedness, and most especially serving as yet
another stage to advocate for the calling of the estates general.
With Brienne, having dropped the land tax as a part of his compromise with the Paris parliament, the
one order of business the assemblies really had to haggle over was the extension and collection of the
VA tm, which was supposed to once again help bridge the rail deficit.
But where lacks collection had long been the order of the day.
The VA tm was now supposed to be pursued with an unprecedented vigour.
So over the winter of 1787 1788, the Royal ministry, the provincial parliament, the intendant, the provincial
assemblies, all waged a running battle with each other over who owed what and for how long? And of course,
the big question, who now outranked whom the parliament still wanted assurances that the taxes would
have to be duly registered before the assemblies could set to work collecting them.
The assemblies generally ignored this and just went to work.
But more than a few got to work simply so they can drag their feet and force the king to call the estates
general. Meanwhile, Brienne threatened to go back to arbitrarily assessing and collecting the VTM if
the assemblies didn't get in gear, and then another flood of angry remonstrance is from the parliament
would come pouring in the spring of 1788 approached, this mess needed to be simplified, so Brian's ministry
decided to cut at least one tangle out of a knot. by just taking the parliament out of the equation.
It was as audacious a move as Chancellor mapu had made back in the early 1770s, if not more audacious
for Brianna and his colleagues. The hope was that when they were done, the parliament, the self proclaimed
defenders of French liberty, would be turned into an insignificant Social Club.
The setup for this came at the end of last week's episode when rumours started flying around in April
1788 that the ministry was about to make a really serious move.
This resulted in even more heated rhetoric coming out of the Paris parliament, and then the rest of
the premier Neil and that other guy, then on May the eighth, the wild rumours were confirmed by a sweeping
series of decrees that basically gutted the power of the Parliament, known as the may eat acts.
These decrees set up a new plenary court that would be staffed by high ranking nobles.
This new plenary court would become the institution where all future taxes and legislation would be
registered and come to court of final appeal for almost all criminal and civil cases.
All that was left to the parliament were cases involving sums over 20,000 Libra, and a few other estate
and contract issues that affected only the richest men in the kingdom.
In one bold stroke, the ministry was trying to reduce the parliament to little more than an arbitration
Council for the super rich, all real power and authority would be transferred to the plenary court.
And as if this wasn't shocking enough, begin further plan to create lesser courts over the next few
years to replace the existing hodgepodge of weirdly overlapping jurisdictions.
If all went according to plan, France would shortly have an entirely new judicial system, and the parliament
would become relics of a bygone age. Now Brian was of course expecting some resistance, but it seems
pretty clear that he underestimated just how widespread that resistance would be.
The Kings principle minister was no doubt thinking about the parliament, as they truly were.
Little enclaves of aristocratic privilege, cared a little about the general welfare.
But by now the parliament had morphed into something far greater in the public imagination.
It would appear that all they're bloviating, about protecting the ancient liberties of France was actually
being taken seriously. The Parliament were for the moment, the one institution in the kingdom who could
resist the king's will, and then send him remonstrance is explaining why.
So when the king tried to abolish the parliament, well, as we'll see in a minute, everyone from the
highest noble to the lowliest fishmonger had something to say about it.
Although as we will also see, when the magistrates of the Parliament notice that the unwashed masses
were jumping into the fight, they will get really super uncomfortable.
Because when we said we were the defenders of liberty, we meant our liberty you dummies, not yours.
Oh crap, that one's got to break Let's run for it.
So what this led to in the summer of 1788, was a series of protests, demonstrations and riots that knock
the ministry back on its heels, and it all got started almost immediately after the main effects were
announced. First of all, the parliament were collectively put on vacation, whereupon almost the entire
legal profession went on strike and protest, the wheels of justice ground to a halt.
Unlike last time, when mobu was able to entice ambitious young attorneys into the new system, though
Brienne found almost no takers. The solidarity of the legal community was for the moment, unbreakable.
But though they had been ordered to disperse, not all the parliament were willing to just go away without
a fight. Some disperse quietly after a token remonstrance or two.
But once again, those on the periphery of the kingdom elected the path of stiff resistance.
When, for example, the local intendant came to prevent the Parliament of a friend from meeting, he was
met by an angry mob of such size and force that he was forced to flee.
And whenever authority the monarchy hadn't Brittany was basically lost for good two months.
But the most famous incident happened down in the city of Grenoble, the traditional capital of the province
of ruffini, down on the edge of the Alps. When the authorities there attempted to disperse the Grenoble,
a parliament. What they got was the day of the tiles.
The Grenoble, a parliament had outright called the main edicts illegal until Brienne ordered them exiled
from the city letras de cache were issued and due to be delivered June the seventh 1788.
Now the problem delivering the exile orders on June the seventh was it it was a Saturday, aka market
day. That meant that granola was full to the brim with people who were already a bit agitated over rising
bread prices and lack of work. the closure of the Parliament would mean that granola would take yet
another economic hit. So all morning speakers railed against the injustice of it all.
And around 10am everyone shut up their stalls to get down for a little direct action.
One group went to the Palais Royale to prevent the magistrates from leaving, a second group went to
the city gates to ensure the same and then a third group convened at the governor's house and basically
laid siege to it. The authorities had on hand two regiments of soldiers to try to quell the unrest,
but torn between the twin evils of attacking unarmed civilians and letting anarchy reign, they opted
for a halfway measure that just made everything worse.
Soldiers were dispatched in small groups to establish a presence, but told not to fire on the demonstrators.
The effect of this was to make it look like the protesters were about to be attacked, while leaving
the soldiers totally outnumbered and without any means of protecting themselves if the people started
to get out of hand. Now most of the troops managed to hang tough and not fire into the unruly crowds.
But one group near the Jesuit college building found itself pelted by debris from all sides then pelted
with roof piles from the building above. When they actually started getting hit, it was much too much
and they started firing into the crowd. This of course, only confirmed to everyone in the city that
they were indeed under attack. And they rang the toxin bells, which drew in even more men and women from
the countryside. The authorities then tried to cut a deal with the magistrates of the Parliament and
say, Look, we'll pull back if you just leave the city.
The magistrates of the Parliament said yeah, well that sounds awesome.
But unfortunately, we're not really in control anymore.
We're frankly as freaked out by all of this as you are, with the mob, as you can see, has unbridled
all the carriages and is now manning the gate. But after peaking with a good old fashioned ransacking
of officials house, the demonstrators slash rioters started to naturally disperse as the sunset, at
which point, almost all the magistrates of the Paris parliament, re bridle their carriages, and got the
heck out of town. The day of the tiles represents the first major incursion of the mob into our story,
and served as a rather Stark wake up call to the parliament that they were toying with Pandora's box
here. Remember, for the most part, what they wanted was to keep things the same, but they found themselves
now seized on as a vehicle for those who wanted change.
And now all of a sudden, these lower class yobbos, who had no business being anything but anonymous
plebs were violently getting in on the action. For the moment, these anonymous plebs were defending the
parliament as the people's champion. But how long could that possibly last? Spoiler alert, it will last
until about September. But though most of the magistrates of the Grenoble a parliament were disturbed
by the day of the titles, one guy saw at all as an opportunity to capitalise on the expose weakness
of the Royal authorities to demand more than just the continued existence of the Parliament.
That man was 30 year old john Joseph Mooney. Mooney was a wildly successful young judge ennobled at
the age of 25 after buying himself a place in the Grenoble parliament.
But despite his success, he was a forward thinker, and clearly wanted more than to just rise up the
old judicial hierarchy, both for his own sake and for the sake of France.
So he was the mastermind behind the movement to get the Dauphine a state to provincial recall a necessary
first step in what would hopefully become a wider movement to establish a sound constitutional monarchy
for France. Though he was out in front of events for the moment, munia would remain committed to the
dream of a constitutional monarchy even as events swept by him.
As we'll see, he'll enter the estates general as one of the most influential and genuinely recognisable
members, and then resigned from that body less than a year later, unable to reconcile himself to the
pace and direction of events, then branded as a reactionary, he will be forced to slip away to Switzerland
in 1790. The French Revolution moves fast, but that is all still in the future.
For now, Mooney was in his prime on June the 14th.
A week after the day of the tiles he organised a meeting of about 100 prominent men representing each
of the three states. At moonies urging, the group endorsed a call for the restoration both of the Parliament
and for the convening of Duffin as a state to provincial.
But by far the most critical aspect of this meeting, is that it gave the first formal expression to
an idea that would soon sweep the country that when the estates met, as they surely must, the number
of the third estates representatives should be double that of the other orders.
So the composition would wind up being 50% clergy and nobility and 50% third estate, and then critically,
that voting should be by head rather than by order.
This Maxim of double the third vote by head would become a major rallying cry in the lead up to the
estates general and when the issue still hadn't been resolved when these states finally meet in May 1789.
Well, you'll see what happens when we get there. While he waited for word from the Ministry about whether
the Dauphine estate would be allowed to meet munia simply plunged ahead as if they were going to say
yes, word went round Dauphine a for everyone to prepare for the calling of the estates provincial, and
to convene a preliminary assembly at a Chateau in Vizio.
meeting on July 21, this assembly was composed of 50 clergymen, 165 nobles, and 276 representatives
of the third estate. Monia got himself appointed secretary and then guided the debate into unprecedented
territory. Though he was not a great orator, his arguments carried enormous weight instead of making
the case for power Lamar and the estates on the basis of the old constitution, he went back even further
than that into the primordial ooze and started bringing up points about natural law, the rights of man
and the necessity of true liberty. These were concepts that had been floating around for years among
the philosophic, but they were now being mainline directly into the body politic.
Then they went further, and said that no convening of the states provincial or the estates general could
be considered legitimate if it was not convened on the basis of double the third and vote by head.
And anyone who oppose that idea was a traitor to France.
And now we're talking revolutionary language because man, once these guys grab hold of the notion that
political opponents are actually guilty of treason, boy, watch out.
Meanwhile, back up in Paris, King Louie was of course vacillating like crazy.
He had come down hard with the rest of deployment Neil and the main effects, but the size and scope
of the pushback shocked him. For a minute he tried to keep up the tough guy act, group of Breton nobles
were thrown in jail for meeting under vaguely suspicious circumstances.
And then the delegation on the way from Ren to ask for their own estates provincial, was arrested.
But a week later, he backed down and suddenly agreed to let the Breton estates meet.
Then on August the second, he more or less accepted the legitimacy of all Munoz activities by allowing
the Duffin estates to meet as well. Now, if you will recall from way back when the big problem with
King Charles The first was that he wouldn't listen to anyone.
He was so insanely inflexible that he basically forced Cromwell to cut off his head.
In this respect, Louie was the opposite. He was so flexible that he just couldn't stick with any one
policy. He was one of those guys who will just go with whatever the last person who talked said this
was starting to become a problem from a monarchy, and Marie Antoinette and the Kings brothers started
talking amongst themselves about how they were worried Louis might not be up for this.
The Queen then started taking a more forward role in policy to protect the interests of the royal family.
But unfortunately, all of this royalist entrenchment did was create an even more extreme position for
Louie to jump back and forth from when the state's general finally met.
The bottom finally fell out of the alcyone regime on August the eighth 1788.
That was when Brienne was informed that there was only 400,000 lever left in the Royal Treasury, barely
enough to keep the lights on for a single day, and no one would lend them any more money.
The ministry was forced to admit defeat, scrapping the plan to replace the parliament with the plenary
court, Brianna announced that the meeting of the estates general would no longer be at some vague point
in the future. He announced that on May the first 1789, the estates general would convene at Versailles
for the first time in 175 years. This announcement was met by wild euphoria throughout the kingdom,
as everyone had come to believe that basically all their hearts desired would be granted by this now
almost mythical assembly. In a move that looks shrewd to Brienne, at the time, wound up really sowing
the seeds of true revolution. The King then invited public debate on the form the estate should take.
This was supposed to drive a wedge between the nobility, who would insist on going by the old three
equal estate vote by order, and the commoners who were already on record opposing anything but doubling
the third and voting by head. Now it did indeed drive a wedge between them, but the resulting rupture
did not lead to the king regaining his political footing.
It opened up instead an unbridgeable chasm that would eventually cost the king his head.
But though the call to convene the estates general was for sure necessary to satisfy the Kings creditors.
It was not sufficient. The regime needed loans to get them through until May 1789.
But as had happened with cat loan, Brienne was now personally becoming a sticking point.
On August the 16th, with credit exhaustion, were getting cut off repayment of loans and started issuing
pieces of paper for the amounts to plus 5% interest, collectible at some point in the future.
This was not a satisfactory response, and Brienne knew it.
But there was little he could do, beaten, tired, and now well aware that the regimes bankers were opposed
to him personally. He resigned on August the 25th.
He had spent 16 months trying to get somewhere anywhere, and instead God Himself nowhere and the kingdom
officially on the road to revolution. With Brienne out of the picture, there was only One man the bankers
would accept if the monarchy expected to see even a single lever.
That was of course the Swiss Wonderboy. Jacques Macare.
As much as the King hated it. He was forced to choose between the care and the care because there was
no other choice. The news that the now hated Brienne was gone and the people's banker netcare was being
recalled. Set off yet another wave of jubilant celebration across the kingdom.
This is all going fantastically, don't you think? And now we get to have a great debate over how our
estate should be composed. I mean, this really is the dawning of a new era.
And next week, we will dive into the dawning of that new era, with freedom of the press all but declared
France would be flooded with newspapers and pamphlets and diatribes all trying to influence public opinion
and sway the future of France. It was exhilarating, intoxicating, and ultimately would prove totally
uncontrollable.