Hello, and welcome to revolutions Episode 3.4, neck hair and the necklace.
Last week we talked about the efforts of successive royal ministries in the early 1770s to reform some
of the more glaring problems with the Asan regime.
And we saw how those efforts were frustrated by those who stood to lose the most from reform, whether
they be aristocrats who weren't about to let their privileges be ignored, or peasant who weren't about
to let free market experiment literally take bread off their table.
With the failure of those reforms, the ministries of the late 1770s and early 1780s took a slightly
different approach to solving Francis problems. And though it would be an unfair exaggeration to say
that that approach was Hey, let's pretend like nothing's wrong.
As you'll see that unfair exaggeration is not too far off the mark.
Once we get done talking about that, we're going to switch gears and trace the steadily declining reputation
of Queen Marie Antoinette because that steadily declining reputation finally curse splattered for good
just as the Hey, nothing's wrong attitude was blowing up in the monarchies face.
So we left off with the ousting of the physiocrats reformer targo in May 1776.
As his reform package of spending cuts in the palace and free market economics out in the provinces
left him with a list of enemies a mile long, it wasn't hard to see that Turco would soon be on his way
out the door. So as the comptroller General's influence waned, one man positioned himself as the best
and frankly only candidate to replace him. Jacques Nick hair after tear go got the boot.
It would take the Kings advisors a good six months to get into care elevated into the ministry.
But when he was finally brought on board, everyone was convinced that he would be able to lead the Royal
Treasury out of danger and into the Promised Land of permanent solvency.
Now, one of the reasons it took a little while to get into care into the ministry was that he had three
pretty big strikes against him. He was a commoner, he was Swiss, and he was a Protestant.
Any one of those alone would have made him suspect to the inner circles of Versailles combined, they
would have torpedoed a lesser candidate, but netcare was no lesser candidate.
He was widely viewed as a financial genius who had the answers to all Francis problems.
Born in Geneva in 1732, and the care had been sent to Paris at the tender age of 15.
To work as a bank clerk for an uncle. It became apparent immediately that an aptitude for banking didn't
even begin to describe his talents. He worked his way quickly up the ranks and was made a full partner
in his uncle's bank just after turning 30. Now a wealthy young superstar in the world of finance, netcare
founded his own bank, and made even more money lending to the Royal Treasury and speculating in the
grain trade. Around the same time, he got involved with a wealthy widow, but when said wealthy widow
brought around a pretty Swiss girl named Suzanne Kirsch show, a carer fell in love with Suzanne, and
dropped said wealthy widow. interesting side note is that Suzanne had previously been engaged to none
other than Edward Gibbon, but the engagement was broken off when she took up with the care.
The couple was married and then had a daughter in 1766, named German, who met Omnicare raised on the
educational theories of Rousseau. And when she grew up, German became a literary celebrity in her own
right as Madame de stall, who waged a ceaseless intellectual war against Napoleon.
But now I'm starting to drift off topic. With the assistance and or prodding of his wife, Nick hair
started aiming for government office. In the late 1760s, he was appointed director of the East India
Company, which like its British counterpart was a privately chartered corporation that held a legal monopoly
on the Indian trade markets. The company was failing badly from corruption and mismanagement.
And despite his efforts to maintain its independence, the company was liquidated in 1769, and all its
assets and debts were taken over by the crown. But this will not be the last we've seen of the East
India Company. It will be reconstituted in 1785 and then be at the epicentre of a massive scandal in
1793. That was a big part of explaining when and why the revolution began to eat its own children, so
watch out for that. Returning to private business, then Macquarie spent the next few years building
up Jack's reputation as a financial wizard, mme Nick hair hosted a well attended salon, the top most
prominent intellectuals and government officials passed through at one point or another.
When Turco took over as Comptroller General in 1774, the carrier started publishing economic tracks
that attacked the physiocrats reforms denouncing most especially the free trade in grain So by the time
tear go was driven from the Ministry, it was well known that Nikesh was sitting on a slate of ideas
that ran in the opposite direction to the discredited policies of the physiocrats.
Still, as I said, it took a few months to bring him in.
And even when he was brought in in October 1776, mcare had to take a less prestigious post because Protestants
were not allowed to hold a major office like Comptroller General of finances.
But whatever the title netcare was now more or less in charge of the Royal Treasury.
Like everyone else these days, he could see that taxes needed to be distributed a little more evenly
across the three estates. But being a banker, and the care was utterly convinced that actually raising
taxes was unnecessary, and that the Royal Treasury would be best served by floating more loans.
He was also in complete agreement with Virgin about the benefits of France getting into the American
war. And he scoffed at two NGOs complaints that they just couldn't afford it.
We won't even have to raise taxes. He said, we can just finance the whole thing and it'll be fine.
Trust me, I'm a financial genius, remember. So off he went to raise the money, offering good rates and
utterly self confident assurances that the Royal Treasury was in great shape.
On the strength of his personal reputation more than anything else, Nick hair, got his loans.
Even sceptics in the parliament only fought them a little bit on the first loan, and then started registering
future requests without complaint. Now trying to figure out exactly what Nick care was up to here is
a little tricky. And now I haven't got a good source on this, I would bet that he was interested in
taking France in the direction of the British, who when they created the Bank of England back in 1694,
more or less invented the idea of a permanent national debt serving as an engine for growth.
As long as the interest is being paid, the state would always have a ready supply of cash.
This would help explain decaires bookkeeping, without resorting to words like con artist, charlatan,
and complete fraud, because mcare started dividing royal expenditures up into two categories, ordinary
expenses and extraordinary expenses. As the loans piled up to fund the American warped netcare filed
the interest on those loans as ordinary expenses, but he dumped the principal off into extraordinary
expenses. He was happy to show anyone who asked the tally for the ordinary expenses.
And with those apparently in good order, no one thought to ask about the extraordinary expenses, which
would have sent potential lenders running for the hills rather than happily handing over more money.
The peak of knickers power, popularity and influence, at least on this first go around in the ministry
came in February 1781. When he convinced the king to let him publish for the first time ever a complete
accounting of the Royal finances. The resulting kontron do was meant to silence all critics and put
to rest any whispers that all was actually not well, in the king's pocket book.
The kontron do was a bonafide sensation, as nearly every educated man and woman in France wanted to
get a look at the king's books. I mean, this was an unprecedented lifting of the veil.
There were even mentions by later writers who were children at the time, that they literally learned
how to read from the kontron do it was seriously that big of a deal.
And what did it show? It showed that the Royal Treasury had a 10 million Libra surplus that this was
because the comp Ron do only dealt with those ordinary expenses, the regular cost of government compared
to the regular streams of revenue. But as I just said things like you know, the massive load of loans
taken on to finance the war in America are just not even mentioned.
Had they been all France would have seen that the Treasury was actually running deep in the red.
In the long run, the legacy of the compound was not just that it swept Francis financial problems under
the rug, but that it became impossible to believe netcare successors when they revealed that the king
was not only broke, he was catastrophic Li broke. I mean, how do you convince someone who literally
learned how to read by flipping through the compound do that in less than five years, the monarchy had
somehow gone belly up. There were guys who right up until the end just couldn't believe it, and thought
that cologne was running some sort of Shakedown operation when he presented his reform package to the
assembly of notables in 1787. In the short term, though, the Comforter rendu led directly to netcare
getting himself kicked out of the ministry, believing that he was now indispensable, he demanded that
the king let him into the inner circle of decision makers or he would resign.
But like everyone in government in the care had his enemies, then they convinced the king not to bite.
His bluff called Macare had to make good on his threat, and he resigned in May 1781.
Though critically for future events, his popularity with the public only grew as he was martyred by
evil nobles who feared the influence of this commoner who the people of France had come to believe could
do no wrong. netcare was succeeded by a guy JOHN Francois Zhu Li de Flurry, who was far more conservative
in his outlook, coming from a staunchly anti enlightenment family.
He's not of major importance, and his name will not be on the test.
But he was the bridge between netcare and Catalan.
And so I have to mention that Florrie took one look at the books and said, holy crap, we have got to
raise taxes. And thanks to his long standing connection to the parliament, he was able to push through
a third VA tm that would run through 1786. But the additional money raised was only going to cover interest
payments on all the previous loans. So just to keep going flurry had to borrow even more money, and
then go back to selling venal offices, a practice that had been slowly ratcheted down by previous ministries.
Given what he had to work with flurries days were always numbered.
I mean, how do you ask courtiers and ministers to cut back on spending and submit to new taxes when
the kontron do is sitting on their desk telling them that everything is fine.
He finally called it quits in March 1783. Just as negotiations to end the American War we're getting
underway. flurry was succeeded by a guy whose name will absolutely be on the test Sharla Alexandria
deck how long because it will be cologne who will spark the so called pre revolution.
When he finally gives up the ghost and says it's either major reforms or the kingdom collapses.
Those are your options. Unfortunately, as we'll see, cologne was not a particularly good messenger for
this dire warning, given his previous embrace of a little thing called useful splendour.
So as we'll see next week, when it came time for major reform, there was major pushback.
kalon had been born in 1734 in Flanders into a respectable family of the robe nobility.
He was trained as a lawyer and then slowly rose up through the political judicial ranks, serving in
the Flanders parliament and then securing positions in the central bureaucracy, and eventually rising
up to be an intendant. Along the way, he earned a reputation as a man far more interested in nailing
down his next promotion than really doing the job that was in front of him.
But he was savvy in business and at least clever enough to always land that next promotion when it became
available. With the help of foreign minister version, who was by now Louise most trusted adviser, cologne
was brought in to serve as Comptroller General finances in November 1783.
And he brought with him the rather novel idea that the best way to get out of debt was to spend more
money. Now, this is crazy, of course, and it didn't work.
But cologne did have a plan. Like his predecessors Turco and Macare.
cologne believed that raising taxes was at least for the moment a political non starter.
his immediate predecessor, Florrie had pushed the limits of the nobilities patients by initiating the
third VA tm. Anything more that would require a concerted ro push that the ministry did not have the
stomach for, especially since it might eventually involve recalling the estates General, which was a
surefire way to completely lose control of the situation.
So cologne decided that the only way out was to keep borrowing and hope that maybe in time new loans
taken at lower rates would pay off the loans with higher rates, and then they could start getting ahead
of this thing. So instead of cutting back spending at Versailles, cologne conspicuously jacked it up.
The idea being that if creditors saw that the monarchy was spending lavishly, they would be assured
that the king was in good shape, and see more royal loans as a safe investment.
And for a while it worked. Its cologne took out hundreds of millions of Libra more in debt.
But even the useful splendour was not enough to quiet doubt.
And in December 1785, the Paris Parliament baulked at approving yet another loan, and they had to be
marched as a group to Versailles and basically ordered by the king to approve it.
And so they did. But as you might guess, spending your way out of debt turned out to be not a very good
solution to the problem. Especially when cologne took to the books to survey the situation.
Now that flurries VA tm was set to expire at the end of 1786.
He was mortified to discover that the crown was about to start running an annual deficit of well over
100 million lever, which was a full quarter of expected revenue.
And it was only going to get worse as the interest started coming due for all the loans over the last
few years. Once those started kicking in something like half of all annual revenue was going to be going
to debt servicing. This was a grind the wheels to a halt revelation.
cologne realised that there could be no more tricks, no more kicking the can down the road.
The crisis everyone had been trying to avoid for the last decade was finally upon them.
And so he retired to his offices and started drawing up a plan to completely overhaul the Crown's finances.
A plan that would touch on almost every part of the ossian regime, a plan that would ruffle every feather
in the kingdom and a plan that the king would not be able to implement by his own royal will.
But we're going to leave the financial crisis there for the moment on the eve of cologne presenting
his reform package to the king. Because I want to close out today's episode by getting into a royal scandal
that would break just as all of this financial stuff was coming to a head.
It is a scandal too crazy to just breeze by without stopping to smell all the delicious details.
Plus, it offers the perfect opportunity to talk a bit about Maria Antoinette, who wound up losing whatever
popularity she had left as a result of the scandal, even though as we're about to see, she had nothing
whatsoever to do with anything. So let's talk about Maria Antoinette and the diamond necklace affair.
Maria Antoinette was born Maria Antonia in 1755. In Austria, the eighth child and youngest daughter
of Maria Teresa and Francis the first who were Holy Roman Empress, and Emperor respectively.
And in that order, Maria Teresa having inherited the throne from her father in 1740.
Little Maria Antonia grew up in a fairly private and relaxed environment.
And though she never took much to formal education, she excelled at singing and dancing and seems to
have had a fairly happy childhood. But it just so happened that she was born right as Europe was undergoing
the diplomatic revolution of 1756, which we're going to talk about I think in two weeks, when we pull
back to survey the international scene within which the French Revolution is about to explode.
The diplomatic revolution meant that Austria had a whole new set of partners that needed to cement alliances
with including its longtime enemy France. It looked for a while like Maria Antonio wouldn't be called
upon to play a major role in the new alliance system.
But smallpox took its toll on the Australian royal family.
And by the time she turned 12, in 1767, negotiations were underway with the French to marry her to the
future Louie the 16th. himself just 13 years old. All the arrangements over the dowry and whatnot were
finalised over the next few years. Maria Antonia was restyled Marie Antoinette and shipped over to the
custody of the French royal family, where she and Louie were officially married in May 1770.
Now, given that she was 14, and he was 15, and there was probably a roomful of people milling around
as was the weird royal custom. It is not surprising that the marriage was not consummated on the actual
wedding night. But as the days and then weeks, and then years passed, the missing act of consummation
became a mild concern than a running joke, and then a downright threat to the Franco Austrian Alliance.
Not that many in France were much concerned about that.
Though Murray herself was fairly popular in the early going the alliance with Austria was most assuredly
not, and that's up to an including Foreign Minister Virgin and King Louie himself, who both chafed under
an alliance and marriage that had been arranged by their predecessors.
So as the time passed, and Marie Antoinette continued to be ignored by King Louie who preferred hunting
and tinkering with locks, she took comfort with a small circle of friends, and indulged in whatever
frivolities happened to present themselves shopping for clothes gambling, horse racing attention from
discrete male admirers. She was, after all, basically still just a kid, and was only 18 years old when
her husband ascended to the throne, and she became queen of France.
This title bumped changed a little for her though, including the constant barrage of letters from her
mother berating her for not having betted the king yet a harsh spotlight hit this failure of royal intimacy
when the king's younger brother had a son in 1775.
And by now, the gossipy underground press was having a field day and there were rumours that Louie actually
had a physical defect that eventually required surgery to fix, though that seems to have been just a
rumour. Finally, in 1777, Murray's brother Joseph, the second now Holy Roman Emperor, came to visit
and he was very much concerned about the state of the Franco Austrian Alliance.
After badgering the couple to do their duty, the king and queen finally went to bed seven years after
they were married. But Marie Antoinette only enjoyed temporary relief from public mockery when their
first child turned out to be a daughter. But then in October 1781, she gave birth to the sun everyone
had been waiting for the last 11 years. Unfortunately, as we will see, the new dolphin that is the Crown
Prince was a sickly kid, and he would die at just about the worst possible moment in the spring of 1789.
A few years later, though, the royal couple had a second son, who would also come to a miserable end
at the hands of the evil revolutionaries, and then in 1786, a second daughter, who would not live to
see her first birthday. Now through all of this, Marie Antoinette continued to spend money by property
push for her own favourites to be given offices and pensions and gifts.
And her standing with the French public was not good at all.
She was just too frivolous and extravagant and out of touch, and she took a constant beating in the
press. But up until the diamond necklace, affair which we're about to talk about.
She may have been the object of scorn and mockery, but it wasn't like she was hated.
And what's hilarious is that the thing that really got her hated was something that she had nothing
at all to do with. Okay, so the diamond necklace affair.
Here's how it goes. Way back in 1772 King Louie the 15th ordered an incredibly elaborate diamond necklace
from a Paris jeweller. It was meant to be a gift for his mistress, Madame Dewberry.
But the piece was so complex that it was not completed by the time the king died and but um Dewberry
was kindly asked by the royal family to take a hike.
The jeweler's now out the money they fronted to put the thing together tried to sell it to Marie Antoinette
in 1778. But she said no, it wasn't her style, and she wasn't too keen on but I am to bury herself.
So why would she want to wear her jewellery? After failing to sell the piece of bra the jewellers again
tried the queen in 1781. And again, she said no. Okay, so far, so good.
There's a fancy necklace the Queen doesn't want it simple.
But here's where it starts to get complicated. along comes a con woman named john delamotte, who was
successfully passing herself off as a descendant of King Henry the second.
At some point in 1784. She and her husband and army officer who was also passing himself off as a noble
set their sights on fleecing the rich and hapless and hopefully pronounced correctly.
Cardinal de la Han, or Han was one of those wealthy aristocrats who made up the top level of the first
estate, and he had once upon a time been ambassador to Austria.
It was well known around town though that ohan A wanted a new position in the government, and B was
currently being iced out by the queen who did not approve of for Han reporting on her activities to her
mother, while the cardinal was serving as ambassador to Austria.
So our con woman john takes up with the good Cardinal and convinces him that she's developed an intimate
friendship with the Queen bait the gullible or Han could not pass up.
JOHN agreed to start delivering flattering notes from the cardinal to the queen, and then return with
the Queen's replies, replies that were of course forged.
These forts replies were apparently affection enough in tone that all Han started thinking maybe he
and the Queen had like something special. So he begged john to arrange a meeting.
No problem, says john and goes off and I'm not making this up to hire a prostitute who looked like the
queen. On a moonlit night in the gardens of Versailles, or Han and the fake prostitute Queen met and
promised to put all their bad blood behind them. Now, of course, while this is going on, john is routinely
taking money from pawn to invest in the Queen's charity work, which is a nice running scam.
But then along comes the jewellers with the huge diamond necklace they can sell.
They have just found out that john has got the Queen's here, and they offer her a commission if you
can get it sold. So in January 1785, john forges a request from the queen to have Mohan buy it for her,
it would be too unseemly for me to go buy it myself, you see.
Jumping at the chance to serve the queen. The Cardinal arranges with the jewellers to buy the thing
for 2 million Libra to be paid off in four instalments.
He then takes the necklace and hands it off to the Queen's valet, who is of course just some guy in
cahoots with john and her husband. Ron is now absolutely giddy with the fine work he's done.
Not even suspecting for a moment the husband has just taken the necklace up to London, where he will
strip it and start selling the diamonds off one by one.
Eventually, though, Ron started to get nervous, and maybe a little suspicious, when he noticed that
the Queen had not yet worn the necklace, and still hadn't sent any of the money to pay off the jeweller
by the time the first instalment came due in August 1785.
When the payment deadline arrives, and john reveals to him that there's no money coming, the angry jeweller
goes directly to the queen. And the Queen says something along the lines of I don't know anything about
this and why are we still talking about this necklace? So the king and queen dragon will hon for an
audience and demand and explanation. He tells them everything, and shows the forge purchase order which
sends King Louie into convulsions because it's obviously a forgery.
It was signed Marie Antoinette of France. And as a handful well knew the royalty only ever signed with
their given names. terminally pissed off, the king has bohan thrown in the steel.
And from there, the whole plot unravelled and everyone connected is hauled into court.
JOHN, the prostitute look alike, the forger the husband in absentia, since he's still up in London.
The trials were a sensation, one of those trials of the century that come along every few years.
But in a crazy twist, the public chose to sympathise with the defendants, Cardinal vahagn had been duped
simply Because he was too honest and eager, the prostitute was an innocent girl sucked into a sorted
world. Even john was painted as a sympathetic noble woman down on her luck who had been driven by poverty
to make bad choices. Everyone it seemed, was given a pass except the queen, who somehow came off as
a vindictive a harpy who had purposefully set the whole thing in motion to destroy Han, abscond with
some pretty necklace, while all the while engaging in some fairly graphically depicted sexual manipulations.
And the actual judges appear to have picked through all of this well enough, john and her husband were
convicted. The forger was exiled. Cardinal dehaan was acquitted, and the Queen was found completely
innocent. But in the all important court of public opinion, the diamond necklace affair was devastating
to the Queen's and by extension, the entire monarchies reputation.
And what was really damning was just how easy it was to believe that she was this rotten, manipulative
shrew who was all too eager to destroy anyone who stood between her and some shiny things.
It was a devastating public relations nightmare from which she would not recover, especially because
over the next few years, she would not have an opportunity to recover.
Things were about to go from bad to worse for the Austrian regime.
And next week, the public will be hit with the great bombshell that had been kept hidden for so long.
The Royal Treasury is exhausted and unless drastic measures are taken, the entire kingdom is going to
implode.