This week's episode is brought to you by Harry's Harris founders were tired of paying up
for razors that were overpriced and overdesigned.
They knew a great shave doesn't come from gimmicks like vibrating heads, flecks, balls or
handles that look like spaceships.
Tactics that the leading brands have used to raise prices for decades.
They fix that by combining a simple clean design with quality durable blades at a fair
price. Harry's replacement cartridges are just two dollars each.
That's half the price of the Gillette Fusion pro shield.
All Harry's blades come with 100 percent quality guarantee.
And if you don't love your shave, let them know and they will give you a full refund.
Mrs. Revolutions and I both continued to use our Harry's razors.
We love the closeness of the shave, the look and feel of the handles and the precision
trim blade is great for cleaning up my hairline.
So join me. And the 10 million others who have tried Harry's.
He can claim your trial offer by going to Harry's dot com slash revolutions.
The $13 value trial set comes with everything you need for a close, comfortable share
weighted ergonomic handle five blade razor with a lubricating strip and trimmer blade
rich lathering shave gel and a traveled blade cover.
Listeners of revolutions can redeem their trial set at Harrys dot com slash revolutions
and make sure that you go to Harrys dot com slash revolutions to redeem your offer so
that they know that it was me who sent you.
Hello and welcome to revolutions.
Apso 10.4
historical materialism.
One of my hobbies is studying historiography and the philosophy of history.
I don't like just studying history.
I like studying the history of history.
It's why, for example, the first appendices in the history of Rome was about the ancient
Greek and Latin historians.
I enjoyed the history of history in all of its medha glory.
And you can't really do the history of history without devoting a lot of space to the
Marxist historian graphic revolution, which opened up a whole new theoretical approach
that tied the course of history not to great ideas or great men or divine providence, but
rather to economics.
How a group of humans produces the material means of their biological survival.
Those base elements at the bottom of Maslow's hierarchy of needs food, drink, clothing,
shelter that is the base structure upon which the rest of the cultural superstructure is
built. Religion, arts, literature, politics, science.
All of it is rooted in how we produce the means of our survival.
And it is changes and conflicts in that base that determines the course of human history.
That is the basic premise of historical materialism and it is the subject of today's
episode. Starting in the 1840s, certainly no later than his arrival in Paris, Karl Marx
started considering the course of human history and what causal mechanisms might be at
work. He did this because he was beginning to conceive of a new kind of scientific
socialism and he wanted to put it on a solid foundation.
But because he had this fundamentally materialist philosophical outlook when Marx went
looking for these causal mechanisms, he did not plumb the depths of human reason like the
utopian socialist did.
Instead, he studied economics and politics and the actual events of actual history going
back to the dawn of time.
Marks begins with the idea that the thing that makes humans different from animals is
that we come together to produce the means of our survival.
We don't just passively depend on what nature provides.
We actively produce the necessities of life.
We grow food, make shelter, weave cloth.
That's what makes humans human with this idea in mind.
Marks comes to believe that society is defined by the manner in which it does this
production. This is the stuff we talked about last week.
We're talking about the forces of production and the relations of production and more
specifically, the combination of those two concepts into the grand concept mode of
production, how a society produces its material needs.
This based mode of production is what defines all the other parts of a society's cultural
superstructure. As I just said, art, religion, philosophy, politics, science, forms of
media, everything.
And we can lump all of that stuff together and call it the ideology of the mode of
production. Now, though, Marx believes that the material base defines the cultural
ideology. He recognizes that it's a feedback loop between the base and the superstructure
and that each maintain and reinforce the other.
Just as the prevailing mode of production shapes legal, artistic and religious
institutions, the resulting law and art and religion serves to justify and maintain the
prevailing mode of production.
Now for Marks, the really frustrating part of this is that the organizing ideology of a
mode of production is always synonymous with the ideology of the ruling class in that
mode of production. So right and wrong, good and bad.
Who gets what and why?
Essentially, all the prevailing morality is the morality of the ruling class imposed on
everyone else, instilling in the exploited a set of beliefs designed to do little more
than rationalize the fact that they are being exploited.
And why? That's fine, actually.
The ruling ideology of a given era imprints itself and makes it seem like this is the way
it's always been and will always be.
Marx further believes that humans are fundamentally conservative creatures who prefer
routine habit and continuity to novelty and change, and that this social imprinting is
very difficult to undo.
But for Marx. History is progressive.
It moves in an evolutionary way from the simple to the complex.
It does change and grow and evolve.
So how then do we move from one mode of production to the next?
From small hunter-gatherer groups to walking around to these huge industrial cities
linked by railroads? Well, for Marx, it clearly comes down to changes in the means of
production. Right.
Those are the tools and the subjects of labor.
So we invent a better bow for hunting, maybe discover a technique for preserving food in
the winter. Learn how to domesticate some wild plant.
And this is fundamentally a concept that we would call the development of the productive
forces, which can partly be understood as a measure of human power over nature.
And if you survey human history, you can trace the development of our productive forces,
new tools, new techniques, new technologies lead to new ways of social organization, all
with the aim of producing more of the necessities of life more efficiently.
This can happen both slowly with refinement of technique, work and happen all at once
with some breakthrough discovery or invention.
But the tendency to develop the productive forces is clearly present.
Now, because he's working in a dialectical tradition, Marx sees things evolving through a
process of action and reaction.
And he has this theory that changes in the forces of production, developments in the
forces of production will ultimately seek to create new relations up production to
continue that development.
This is one of the underlying tensions in history.
What if the developing productive forces start slipping out from under the prevailing
ideological superstructure?
Put in another way, if the existing ideological and cultural superstructure starts to
become a hindrance to the further development of the forces of production, then we have a
major problem on our hands.
And society is either headed for revolution or complete social collapse.
When this happens, the inhibited forces of production will of necessity burst asunder, as
Marx likes to put it, and reorganize as a new mode of production better suited to
continue the development of the productive forces.
Marx thinks that these moments of revolution or social collapse occur when a society is
ready to transition from one overarching mode of production to its successor.
And as Mark says in the German ideology and I'm quoting here, at a certain stage of
development, the material productive forces of society come into conflict with the
existing relations up production from forms of development of the productive forces.
These relations turn into their fetters.
Then begins an era of social revolution and quote, to use metaphors, invoking industrial
imagery than revolution is thus the motor force of history.
One of the most important tensions and contradictions that exist in a society is how the
development of these forces up production produce different classes that are defined by
who is doing the labor and who is reaping the rewards.
Who is the laboring class and who is the ruling class?
Who is the oppressor and who is the oppressed?
Now the development of the ruling class, freed from the drudgery of manual labor to
produce the necessities of life is not just how we come to have lords and priests who
were the first two groups to say No, actually, you work.
I'll just be over here, chairman.
It also brings us all the things we associate with that cultural superstructure art,
music, philosophy, science, sports, all of it.
But for nearly all of human history, the production of culture, as we understand it, has
been the province of a small minority inside or adjacent to the ruling class who do not
have the labor to survive.
And this tension between the laborers and the non labourers, between the oppressed and
the oppressors, will naturally create tension, class conflict and class struggle.
And that class conflict is central to the course of history.
Marx opened the Communist Manifesto by stating boldly The history of all Hitler to
existing society is the history of class struggles.
And then he goes on to say, Freemen and slave, patrician and plebeian, Lord and Serf
Guild, master and journeyman.
In a word, oppressor and oppressed stood in constant opposition to one another, carried
on an uninterrupted, now hidden, now open fight, a fight that each time ended either in a
revolutionary reconstitution of society at large or in the common ruin of the contending
classes. Now, I am leaving a lot of nuance out of this.
But before we move on, I want to say that Marx does not think human beings are mere
passengers in history.
They are not carried along by some mystical force of history outside of free will.
And this makes sense for a guy like Marx, who is at heart a passionate, energetic,
revolutionary activist who doesn't want to just interpret the world.
He wants to change it.
And so though sometimes he gets carried away and uses phrases like inevitable to describe
the triumph of the working class.
He doesn't actually think this, but he does believe that the conditions within which
humans live at any given moment limit the scope of available action.
Individual humans are rooted in history.
Early hunter-gatherers could not invent capitalism because the technological level of
their means of production simply did not allow it.
It was impossible for the levellers and the diggers to usher in communism during the
English Revolution because the mode of production and level of technology did not allow
it. And Marx sum this up, and I heartily endorse this sentiment.
By the way, he says this in the 18th premiere of Louis Bonaparte.
Men make their own history, but they do not make it as they please.
They do not make it under self selected circumstances, but under circumstances existing,
already given and transmitted from the past, the tradition of all dead generations, ways
like an ALP on the brains of the living.
And that is a million percent true.
So we will now move on to the stages of historical materialism, Mark's divided the eras
of human history up by their prevailing mode of production.
And he was here working in the Enlightenment and post-Enlightenment tradition.
The Scottish Enlightenment guys like Adam Smith had come up with their own progressive
stages of economic development and defined them as hunting pasturage, agriculture and
commerce. And so Marx has his own version of this to keep things simple.
I will keep it restricted to what is now the accepted canon.
First, tribal or primitive communism than ancient or slave mode of production.
Then the feudal mode of production than the capitalist mode of production.
And finally, the socialist mode of production.
There are slightly modified versions of this that involve an AC ADIC mode and a barbarian
mode that exists in the area between the tribal and the ancient motive productions.
But I will set those aside for now.
The basic questions we are going to be asking ourselves are what are the means of
production? Who owned or controls the means of production?
What are the relations of production that surround and enable those means?
Whereas the surplus production going.
What is the class conflict?
How are the forces of production being developed?
Those are the fundamental questions.
And I should stress, though, before we get into this, that Marx never really grappled
with East Asian or South Asian history, and he gets pretty fuzzy about everything the
further you get from, say, the Rhine River.
And so what follows amounts to mostly an accounting of European history from pre-history.
OK, so we begin with primitive communism or the tribal mode of production or as it is
commonly known, hunter gatherer society.
Now the first thing we should say is that for the materialist historian, the big thing
that advances Proteau humans beyond their initial animal state is not that they had big
brains, but instead that they decided to adopt bipedal locomotion which freed up their
hands to use tools.
And that is what allowed their brains to grow big and smart.
Remember, always material development first ideas.
Second, you can disagree with that.
But this is what the materialists say.
The other big things humans have going for them is cooperative labor.
We always find humans working in groups together.
So those early, modern and enlightenment era depictions of man as a solitary creature in
the state of nature that you find in like Rousseau and Locke and Hobbs, that is all
wrong. Humans were never solitary creatures.
We were always in groups.
Sharing and cooperative dependence are the essential survival skills of the human
species, not self-reliance and independence.
So the means of production in this first mode are just rudimentary tools and available
natural resources.
So axes and spears, baskets, knives, they tame fire where simple animal skin clothing.
They live in rudimentary shelter and both the means of production and the production
itself is shared in common by the group.
The relations of production are kinship groups with a loose and fluid division of
hunter-gatherer labor without a great deal of specialization and sense.
This is a very hand-to-mouth existence.
There is no surplus to cream off that would allow a non laboring life.
So everyone is working.
This means there is no class.
There is no state. Property.
Money. Kings. Aristocrats.
Any of that stuff. There was no class.
And so there was no class conflict.
And the forces of production basically stayed the same.
That is, they were not developing for hundreds of thousands of years for the majority of
human existence. I mean, just by sheer number of years, this primitive communist mode of
production has been the prevailing mode of production.
Then about ten or twelve thousand years ago, give or take, human society underwent what
has been dubbed the Neolithic revolution.
This is when the ancient aliens came down from the heavens, messed with our DNA and
taught us how to be farmers.
The forces of production developed from hunting and gathering to settled agriculture and
animal husbandry. Our new found ability to domesticate plants and animals to produce the
necessities of life changed how and where humans lived.
This material change altered our social relations.
Some societies stopped being nomadic and started to live in permanent settlements.
Harnessing the productive power of farming also introduced a truly transformative element
surpluses. These societies could produce so much food that some people didn't have to
devote themselves to productive labor.
So we have the origins of class between a laboring majority and a non laboring minority.
This non laboring minority becomes the ruling class who initially, through sheer physical
intimidation, are able to command and control the surplus production.
The free time of this non laboring ruling class allowed for even greater developments in
the productive forces, but also everything else we think of as culture.
All the elements of what we now call civilization become present.
As a result of surpluses.
So this Neolithic revolution is arguably the single most important event in human
history. This revolution takes us from the tribal or primitive communist mode of
production to the ancient or slave mode of production, which at its highest state is
basically synonymous with Greco Roman civilization.
The means of production now include large scale settled agriculture, the extensive use of
animals for power, the beginnings of industry, mining and craft work in cities and
advanced large scale trade networks.
We also have the arrival of legal private property.
This field is mine, not yours.
And because we now have a surplus that can be allotted to a non laboring ruling class, we
also have advancements in the cultural superstructure, the development of the
intellectual means of production, writing, cataloging, archiving, math calendars,
science, weights and measures, all of which will be handled by a new professional class
engineers, lawyers, architects, traders, artisans, musicians, actors and teachers.
Real permanent specialization of labor starts to set in.
But the defining feature of the ancient mode of production is the arrival of the slave.
With warfare now a much larger scale proposition, captured prisoners can be brought home
and put to work. Get them not us to do the productive labor for marks.
The defining class division then in the ancient mode of production, is not necessarily
between ruler and ruled, but between free individual and slave.
And it's these free individuals who are gobbling up the surplus created by the laboring
class of slaves who were the private property of another human being, no less than the
hammer or the skies.
Now, this is a very general depiction of like a thousand years or more of Mediterranean
history with the ancient mode of production, again, just sort of being a picture in the
mind's eye of a timeless Roman Empire.
Now, from the materialist perspective, the big thing that wrecked the ancient mode of
production was the decrease in supply of cheap slaves from about the end of the Punic
Wars up through the disaster in the Tuta Burg Forest.
The Roman legions steadily expanded Rome's borders and its population of slaves.
But after this, the Roman Empire stopped expanding, aside from a few side projects and
the ambitions of Trajan.
This meant that slaves became dearer and more expensive, and eventually it's going to
make sense to stop using slaves and start using again some version of non owned people.
When this happens, the transition from slave society to feudal society oh so
imperceptibly began.
Now, we actually mapped a lot of this transition out during the history of Rome, right,
starting with the crisis of the third century.
The large, broad and safe empire started to become internally isolated.
Big walls along the frontiers were replaced by walls around cities.
The inability of the central government to guarantee safety raise the power of local
nobles. Labor was willing to send its surplus not to some central state bureaucracy, but
to the local lord who promised to actually defend them.
And this is the origins of Lord and serf.
State taxes levied on commerce by the later emperors tended to make those rising feudal
lords say, Well, screw it, I'll just make it myself rather than buying it on the open
market. And this developed internal self-sufficiency.
All of this makes late antiquity a great transition phase from the ancient mode of
production to the feudal mode of production.
But this is not accompanied by a revolutionary reconstruction of society at large, but
rather this other thing, the common ruin of the contending classes.
In this case, the ancient mode of production was tottering and decrepit.
And when the great migrations came through, they swept aside the Roman Empire.
And what was left was those Proteau feudal relations.
According to historical materialism, this switch from the ancient to the feudal mode of
production was a regression for society.
It was a step back.
The forces of production were still defined by agriculture manual and animal labor with
some technological help from things like water mills.
But the technological level went backwards or at the very least did not advance.
And this is also not happening in a huge linked together empire of trade and
distribution, but rather local self-sufficiency.
And more importantly, most importantly, perhaps, the slaves were now gone.
They were replaced by serfs out in the field, ostensibly non owned individuals who were
nonetheless legally bound to the land.
And this is the fundamental class antagonism during the feudal mode of production between
the productive serfs and the non laboring nobility in the cities.
Crafts were made by free artisans who eventually organized themselves into guilds.
The surplus went to the new class of feudal nobles.
The cast of warrior families who entered into complex reciprocal contracts with each
other and claimed most of the land for themselves.
But it is important to note that in the feudal mode of production, the artisan owned all
his own tools, the means of production, and thus the products of his labor and the
peasant. While they had to give some designated portion of the produce of their land to
the local Lord, the rest was theirs to live on.
There was a direct relationship between the labor invested and the produce consumed for a
long time. The forces of production were not really developing at all.
In fact, they were producing less than the Roman Empire had at its height.
And this went on for a thousand years around these feudal forces of production came on
monotheistic Catholic church and a hierarchical monarchy with divinely ordained kings
that preached a timeless chain of being.
But around about thirteen hundred, something started to happen.
Most probably rocketed forward by the Black Death, which swept through Europe and killed
a third of the population.
Suddenly, the oppressed peasants could demand better pay and conditions and terms of
service. Land that had previously been owned by people who were dead were claimed by
people who were living, growing their landholdings and creating something like a wealthy
peasant class or an emerging gentry in the cities.
The merchants and traders were able to assert more autonomy and weight against the land
based feudal aristocracy.
And these guys were the Bergers, basically the urban oligarchs.
And it is from that title Burgher that Marx dubs them the bourgeoisie, a class that was
destined to develop the forces of production more than any other group since at least the
ancient aliens who taught us how to farm by the 14 hundreds.
You start getting real developments in modern banking techniques of pooling and investing
and lending capital. The printing press is invented.
Then the Americas were discovered.
The whole world was discovered.
Constantinople fell in.
Islamic civilization was pushed out of Spain, leading to European rediscovery of ancient
philosophy and knowledge on a wide scale.
So inside late feudalism, the forces of production began to change.
Industry started to become larger, more co-operative and more centralized.
The old guild system came under pressure from larger scale investments based off of
pooled capital, and the historical role of capitalism was to concentrate all the
scattered means of production spread out across a bunch of mostly self-sufficient local
regions and start producing goods on a massive scale.
This goes hand-in-hand with a change in mentality.
Production now is not just for use, but for sale in a consumer economy, and that sale was
meant to create a monetary profit for the capitalist investor.
Now, of course, people had always produced things that people need, but this was taken to
a whole different level.
And a consumer economy organized around profitable commodities produced on a heretofore
unimaginable scale was born.
The old feudal culture was replaced by new concepts, rationalisation of processes,
training, efficiency and discipline.
The division of industrial labor that is the production of goods rather than just food
had mostly been between guilds.
As in you make shoes.
I do hats. This was replaced by a division of labor inside the shop itself.
You cut leather, I pound nails.
We can make way more stuff.
So this is clearly a major development for the forces up production, but it was running
up against a feudal system that was not fit for this next stage of development.
And just to take one example, serfdom was tying people to the land.
And so they weren't allowed to move to the cities to become workers or you have archaic
tax and tariff systems that inhibited the free movement of mass produced goods.
So this brings us basically to the beginning of the revolutions podcast, because in the
historical materialist conception, the English Revolution and the French Revolution are
both major bourgeois revolutions.
The forces unleashed by the bourgeoisie bursting asunder against the old feudal
aristocracy or, if you like, the new capitalist base trying to shake off a now thoroughly
ill fitting feudal superstructure to build a capitalist society on top of the capitalist
forces of production.
Now in France, things were set back a bit by the fall of Napoleon, but the July
revolution 15 years later was explicitly and nakedly a bourgeois revolution.
There's a quote from Jacques Le Ft.
He says, Now the bankers will rule.
So we talked about some of the hallmarks of the capitalist mode of production last week.
Labor has now been collected and socialized, but the means of production, the tools, the
natural resources and eventually the factories are owned by a single individual or a
small collection of investors who claim all the profit from the commodities produced.
And everything is now organized around the principle of producing commodities for profit
and more specifically, exploiting labor to extract profit from the produce of that
exploited labor. And as Mark sees it, this upend the intuitive old style of market
economics where you sell a commodity to get some money so that you can go buy a different
commodity that you need but do not have.
So you make a table, sell it for money so you can go buy some clothes.
Under capitalism, there's a new version where you take your money.
Use it to make a product so you can sell that product to get more money.
And this whole new conception of reality starts to attach itself to everything and
everything becomes abstracted into a commodity that can be bought and sold inside the
market, and the market used to be just this ancillary piece of society.
And now it's the whole obsessive focus.
No one, certainly not the historical materialist, denies the results.
Once unleashed, the capitalist mode of production, advance the productive forces further
than all of human history put together.
It is practically as significant as the Neolithic revolution.
This new mode of production created a fundamentally new class struggle, no longer between
the noble and the surf, but between the capitalist and the worker, between the
bourgeoisie and the proletariat.
A new class of laborers who own nothing and can only sell their labor for wages and the
etymology of proletariat.
Just so you know comes from an old Roman census designation for a landless citizen who
fell well short of all property qualifications for real citizenship and participation in
civil society. Now, as we discussed two episodes back, Marx, the young revolutionary,
identified a restrained bourgeois class that was both suffering under the fetters of
feudalism and who had unique power thanks to their position inside the developing forces
up production to stage a revolution.
They were the revolutionary class, and when he went looking for a group that fit these
parameters inside the new capitalist mode of production, he landed on this previously
unidentified and unknown.
Working class, the proletariat, their misery and exploitation was such that they would
desire revolutionary emancipation and their proximity to and position within the new
capitalist means of production.
Place them in a unique position to have a real revolutionary impact on the economic base
of society. And Marx further believed that these proletarian forces, the forces that
would destroy the bourgeoisie, had been summoned by the bourgeoisie themselves.
That, like the Sorcerer's Apprentice, they had conjured forces they could not control.
And in the end, the bourgeoisie ultimately produced above all their own grave diggers.
Now, when the proletariat overthrew the bourgeoisie, it would usher in a new socialist
mode of production.
Now, I will say, though, that both Marx and Ingles are very vague and cagey about what
this new socialist mode of production will look like.
And partly this is because they don't want to be dreamy utopians building castles in the
sky, but they do think that something is going to happen and that it will be socialism.
They hint that it will probably unfold in two stages, a lower transitionary phase and a
higher stage. And this is sometimes divided between socialism and then full communism.
But Marx often just uses the terms lower and higher socialism.
In this new mode of production, the means of production will be owned by the workers
themselves. They will be the beneficiaries of their own labor rather than seeing it
creamed off and hoarded by a small minority of exploitive rulers.
He also thinks that this will bring about the end of all class distinctions which dated
back to the dawn of agriculture since the Neolithic revolution.
Every mode of production has been dominated by a minority ruling class living off the
produce of a majority laboring class.
Now that this has been upended with the majority laboring class, now the new ruling
class, all class distinctions will evaporate because there will be no more oppressor and
no more oppressed. All of the surplus will be shared in common.
In fact, there will be such an abundance.
Thanks to the productive powers consolidated during the capitalist mode of production, a
post-scarcity society will not require oppressor or oppressed and all becomes irrelevant.
Who's fighting for control of the necessities of life?
They are in abundance.
Everyone can share.
From each according to their abilities and to each according to their needs.
So that is the materialist conception of history and that is the trajectory that Karl
Marx believes human civilization is on.
And this is going to be picked up by his successors because Marx has sketched out an idea
that by necessity, the working class proletariat and only the working class proletariat
is the revolutionary class.
And that in the transition phase between capitalism and socialism, they are going to have
to seize revolutionary power and impose what Marx problematically dubbed the dictatorship
of the proletariat.
And so next week we are going to set Marx aside and we are going to turn to the
philosophy of people who rejected all of that, who thought that this was not the stuff of
emancipation, but the stuff of further tyranny.
And just as we did with Marx and Angles next week, we will cover the life and times of
Mikhail Bakunin, their ideological opponent in the battle for control of the first
international and further revolutionary future of all of Europe.
I will end, though, by reminding everybody that I will be at the Intelligent Speech
Conference in New York on June the twenty ninth, a bunch of us podcasters will be there.
You can beat us. We can hang out all day.
I will be doing a presentation called What is the Point of all this?
And then later in the day, I'll sit for a roundtable discussion about whatever we decide
to roundtable discuss.
It is going to be great and I very much hope to see you there.