This week's episode is brought to you by Casper Casper is a sleep brand that makes
expertly designed products to help you get your best rest.
One night at a time, you spend one third of your life sleeping, so you should be
comfortable. The experts at Casper worked tirelessly to make quality sleep surfaces that
cradle your natural geometry and all the right places.
The original Casper Mattress combined multiple supportive memory foams for a quality
sleep surface with the right amount to both sync and bounce.
But Casper now offers three other mattresses the wave, the essential and the hybrid.
And prices are affordable because Casper cuts out the middleman and sells directly to
you. And that includes free shipping and returns in the United States and Canada.
And you can be sure of your purchase with Kasper's hundred night risk free sleep on it
trial. The Duncan family still heartily endorses the Casper mattress and pillows.
Many great naps and good night sleeps were taken thanks to Casper was a great comfortable
mattress that helped us all sleep better.
So got a hundred dollars towards select mattresses by visiting Casper dot com slash
revolutions and using revolutions at checkout that again get $100 towards select
mattresses by visiting Casper dot com slash revolutions and using revolutions at checkout
terms and conditions apply.
Hello and welcome to revolutions.
Episode ten point twenty four The Union of Struggle for the Emancipation of the Working
Class. Last time we introduced Julius Markoff and a new theory of organizing for the
Russian Marxist agitation, not propaganda, which Markoff would then carry with him to St.
Petersburg when his two years administrative exile in Vilna finally wrapped up in the
autumn of 1895.
In today's episode, he will arrive bearing this new strategy and then join with other
Marxists in the capital to form a new group who would agitate their way towards the
revolution they all dreamed of.
Now, one of Marta's key allies in this project is going to, of course, be Lenin.
And it is in the course of today's episode that these two future friends turned future
rivals. We'll meet for the first time.
So what has Lenin been up to?
Well, while Mahtob was trumpeting the success of the new program of agitation to his
comrades in Vilna in May of 1895, Lenin was off on his first trip abroad on a mission he
undertook on behalf of his comrades in St.
Petersburg to make contact with the now legendary old guard emigre Marxists of the
Emancipation of Labor Group.
Our old friends Grigori Farhana, various sulik and Pavel Axlerod.
When Lenin submitted his travel paperwork to the authorities, he claimed that this was a
vacation he undertook for his health, which wasn't totally made up.
He had been very sick in April of 1895 and did actually need to recuperate.
But the authorities didn't really care whether it was a lie or not.
Lenin was well-known to them and they happily stamped his papers to get him out of the
country because maybe if they were lucky, he would just decide to never come back, which
would be all right with them.
So in the last week of April 1895, Lenin departed on what would be a four month tour
through Austria, Germany, Switzerland and France.
His most important object being linking up with the emancipation of labor group.
Now, he left this group back in episode ten point seventeen around about 1890.
And I wrapped up episode ten point seventeen by saying and I'm quoting myself now, It's
fair to say that by the dawn of 1890, the emancipation of Labor Group had zero influence
on socialist politics at home or abroad.
But much to everyone's shock, the forces of history turned in their favor.
on/off suddenly appeared to be a mad prophet who had predicted a great flood and who
everyone had laughed at until the flood suddenly came and quote.
So having spent the 1880s publishing their interpretations and translation of Marx into
the void, the Vitesse system had come along and made Marxism suddenly very relevant to
this younger generation like Lenin and Crips Gaia and Ma Tof.
Not that the emancipation of labor group yet had any formal ties to any distributors or
allies inside of Russia.
Their work was smuggled in and passed around, but it was all very haphazard.
Like the kids who would go on holiday with their families and come home with trunks full
of illegal books, these books would then be passed around hand to hand inside of reading
and discussion circles.
But there was no permanent stable distribution link.
One of the reasons Lenin was undertaking his mission to find the emancipation of labor
group was to forge just such a permanent, stable distribution link between Switzerland
and Russia. So even as late as 1895, the emancipation of labor group was still just as
small as they had always been.
It was still just the three of them, Kahana, sulik and Axlerod.
And this is not to say they could not have built a larger organization inside the emigre
community had they wanted to.
They just did not want to.
The triumvirate of Tarnoff, sulik and Axlerod conceived of the Emancipation of Labour
Group as a close knit intellectual brain trust that must remain compact in order to
maintain ideological coherence and purity, coherence and purity as defined mostly by
plant. So they were happy to meet with potential supporters or followers or people who
might like to spread their work.
But they were never going to offer you membership in the group.
And one way to think about this is that they basically conceived of themselves as
something like a modern rock band cranking out albums.
If you like a band, you support the band, you go to their concert, you buy their albums
and tell your friends. But just because you like a band doesn't mean you get to join the
band. But young radicals at the time didn't really have any concept of this.
Being invited to join parties and circles in groups was a fairly normal thing.
So it often came as a disappointing shock to fans who came round up Cohon off being like,
Oh man, I dig your stuff.
Where can I sign up and plan off?
Would say, Hey, great bison books spread the word.
But no, you don't get to join the band.
And then they would leave and he would go back to writing.
Now there are pluses and minuses to this approach.
But for sure, the biggest plus, at least in part on OFT's mind, was that he never had to
share songwriting duties with anyone.
Is it time for me to let this metaphor go?
Yes, it is time for me to let this metaphor go.
You get it. While they were busy not expanding their ranks in the early 1890s, Kahana was
hard at work on what became one of his most important books the development of the most
view of history, which was meant to be the definitive articulation of historical
materialism for a Russian audience written under a pseudonym.
The title, The Development of the Most View of History was intentionally designed to be
unwieldy and boring, to hopefully slip it past the censors.
And it worked just as they had done with capital.
The bureaucrats and the censors office decided the development of the modest view of
history was a snooze fast.
And they let it be published legally in Russia once it started making the rounds.
Though it turned out to be a real hit, the most view became the basic textbook
explanation for historical materialism, leaving readers with a clear argument why the
Marxists were so focused on this growing urban proletariat as the key to the future
socialist revolution.
And it turned out to be a must read for all budding socialist revolutionaries.
One of those budding socialist revolutionaries was, of course, Lenin.
And a 25 year old Lenin arrived in Switzerland in May of 1895, moderately intimidated by
the prospect of meeting the great plan' off the Moses of Marxism, Farhana.
For his part, seems to have appreciated Lenin's appreciation of his work.
At least once it became clear that Lenin did not want to, like join the band.
Lenin was instead offering his services as a representative of supporters inside Russia
who could help spread the ideas up on often the other members of the Emancipation of
Labor Group. And this was the perfect moment to really flood the intellectual market with
Marxism because the Vita's system was in full swing by this point, which really did seem
to be proving that Marx and historical materialism were dead.
Right. So on/off and Lenin worked out an arrangement in principle, and Lenin departed
with a stack of letters of introduction written by on/off that would open doors for young
Lenin throughout Europe.
And though in the future they were almost never in the same place at the same time.
Lenin and Klawonn Off would spend the next 10 years or so basically on the same side.
So this meeting in May of 1895 was the beginning of an effective partnership.
But please, Tarnoff also recognized in Lenin something that Lenin probably recognized in
himself, already a potential rival for the title leader of the Russian Marxist.
This concern was deepened a little bit when Lennon moved along to Zurich to stay for a
week with Pavel Axelrod and Axelrod straight upset.
I think we found our leader in Russia.
So Lennon and Axlerod hung out for about a week and got to know each other.
They read and discussed various articles and books and ideas.
And Lennon was very pleased when Axlerod commented on a collection of articles Lennon had
brought with him, saying that he'd like one in particular, which just so happened to be
the one written by Lennon under another pen name.
They also discussed the role and relationship of those revolutionaries inside Russia to
those outside Russia.
And they agreed that when the revolution came that the centre of leadership had to be
inside Russia.
That the best way for emigre outfits like the Emancipation of Labour Group to help the
revolution would be, as Axelrod put it, to act as a fortified redoubt overlooking a great
battlefield. They would be able to take in the whole picture, give strategic advice and
protect the most precious valuables.
Axelrod did not really agree with many of his fellow emigres, who, in their kind of
arrogant and insular myopia, believe that the people inside Russia should be the foot
soldiers, while the emigres should be the generals.
Axelrod thought this was kind of crazy.
If nothing else, it was a supremely inefficient way to run a revolution, which is almost,
by its very nature, a rapid fire event that will require instantaneous decision making on
the ground. Lenin agreed wholeheartedly.
So agreed on this point.
Lenin departed, and it would come as a bit of a shock to Axelrod to find Lenin making the
opposite case just a few years later.
Of course, that was after Lenin had been driven into exile himself, which I'm sure had
nothing to do with his change of heart.
After his stay in Switzerland, Lennon moved on to parents where he met with other emigre
radicals. The most important of these audiences being with the legendary Frenchman Paul
Lafarge, the veteran of the Paris commune who had fled to London in the aftermath of the
bloody week and who soon thereafter married Karl Marx, his daughter Laura, sitting there
with this commu Nahed and the daughter of Marx, Lenin listened to their stories with rapt
attention, and the pair's commun in particular would be a historical event.
He would often return to in his own writings.
Aside from this meeting, Lennon enjoyed his time in Paris as best he could, though his
health did start to deteriorate.
He suffered headaches and insomnia, and eventually he had to make his declaration to the
Russian authorities that he was travelling abroad for his health.
True, with an infusion of cash from his always supportive mother, Lennon returned to
Switzerland, where he recuperated at a spa before heading back to the battlefield in
Russia. Lennon returned to St.
Petersburg in early September 1895.
Looking forward to implementing a program he had discussed with the Emancipation of
Labour Group, linking together the 20 or so currently separate Marxist reading circles in
and around St. Petersburg and then linking that linked group to the emigres abroad.
It was going to be the beginnings of the beginnings of a Social Democratic Party.
Maybe. It was in the service of this project that Lenin first met Ma Tof, who returned
from his exile in October of 1895, bearing the new gospel of the Vilna program and eager
to make it work in St. Petersburg.
Now, up until now, Lenin himself had mostly been doing polemical work against the
Philistine protists, who could not see that they were the past in Marxism was the future.
He had also done some propagandizing among the workers, though he didn't really enjoy it.
He was a writer, a debater and a leader, not a schoolteacher.
So, though he did enjoy the intellectually stimulating life of a salon radical.
He saw in the Vilna program a straightforward way to advance the revolutionary character
of the working classes, because in the end the working classes were going to be expected
to do their revolutionary work as a class, as a mass movement.
This was not supposed to be about an elite intellectual vanguard.
Lenin agreed that focusing on specific factory grievances would help show the workers
living examples of the theory of the exploitation of labor outlined by Marx.
Lenin also agreed that prodding the workers towards strikes by socialist agitation would
give those workers necessary experience and a fighting spirit that would serve them well
in the revolution to come.
So the leaders of the various Marxist discussion groups in St.
Petersburg got together and founded this thing called the Union for the Struggle of the
Emancipation of the Working Class.
The union adopted Markoff's recommended strategy Talk less, listen more, publish
leaflets, not books, focus on lived reality, not abstract theory.
Your audience is the workers, not other coffee house radicals.
Now, the actual membership of this coordinating union of struggle was never very big,
maybe 20 members and all Lenin and marched off, both sat on the central committee where
they implemented Mahtob strategy.
Their first task was to go out among the workers and find out what their grievances
actually were. So they printed and distributed questionnaires for people to fill out that
they hoped would allow them to cobble together a list of complaints that might motivate
the workers to go on strike.
And this did generate some useful information.
And the members of the union also attempted to supplement this with direct personal
interviews. But as we've discussed, many of the members of the Union of Struggle were
white collar, middle and upper class intellectuals.
They'd come around asking these potentially seditious questions of the workers and be met
with understandably tight lipped suspicion from those workers.
But groups Guy was assigned to one of the poorest working class districts.
And thanks to her years of experience and connections as a night school teacher, she was
able to come back with reliably detailed information about pay conditions and hours.
And one of the most interesting things to come out of this exercise in gathering
information was that the managers had a habit of imposing fines on workers for any number
of infractions. So they're already pitifully low.
Hourly wages were in reality, even lower than that because their pay was routinely
docked. Lennon, with his training as a lawyer, would soon be writing up a 44 page booklet
explaining to the workers their rights with regards to these fines.
But that was the last thing he was able to do as a free man, because as he sat down to
get started on the first issue of a new newspaper, they hoped to get going.
Lennon was arrested.
For as much as our young revolutionaries enjoyed playing cloak and dagger, dodging
surveillance and meeting secretly and writing to each other in secret codes with
invisible ink in all the stuff you find in a standard issue spy novel, the Irana was
watching them pretty much the whole time.
Lenin was well-known.
He had been tracked in and out of Europe.
The authorities knew about his false bottom trunk that he used to bring home illegal
literature. But as long as Lenin and his comrades posed no immediate threat, it was
better to just wait.
Monitor them, gather more information, more names and more plans.
And most especially, wait until they did something.
You could really nail them to the wall for.
Now, the reason the authorities knew so much about them is because they had spies,
informants and agents provocateur liberally sprinkled around keeping tabs on everyone.
Among the founders of the Union of Struggle was a certain dentist who was just such a
spy. Now, the problem of police spies was one of the biggest hurdles that Lenin and his
comrades struggled to overcome.
It's one of the biggest problems any revolutionary group struggles to overcome.
You can't trust nobody because if you trust nobody, then you're just a paranoid crank
hiding out in a studio apartment, afraid to talk to anybody.
You're not a revolutionary of the people, but you also can't trust everybody because for
sure, some of your comrades are police spies.
Of course they are. Now, in his novel, The Moon is a harsh mistress, which is a manual
for revolution dressed up as a space adventure.
Heinlein recommend making friends with a sentient and basically omniscient supercomputer
who will be able to identify such police spies, group them together in their own cordoned
off revolutionary cells where you can feed them disinformation.
But in the absence of a sentient and basically omniscient supercomputer, spies are going
to get in. You just have to trust your instincts.
Trust evidence that they are spies.
If and when it does come in and then go with your gut.
In these early days, especially, Lenin tended to air on the side of being too trusting.
So because they trusted this dentist, everyone wound up arrested before they got a chance
to do much of anything in 1895.
Now, the authorities finally decided to go from surveillance to arrest in November 1895
because some factory workers did start a brief strike and the authorities became
concerned that maybe this new Union of Struggle group was having an impact.
So the dentist's spy tipped off his handlers that the six principal editors of the new
underground newspaper would all be in the same place at the same time.
On December the 8th, the police raided the rooms and Lenin and five of his comrades were
carried away about a month later.
A second sweep picked up Mahtob and a bunch of others.
Now, not all the members of the union struggle were in custody groups.
Guy kept her name clear, as did some of the younger members, and they tried to carry on
with their agitation work.
And though it was difficult, it was not impossible to stay in contact with their
imprisoned comrades.
As we saw last week, the people running the prisons and detention centers were not
exactly committed to their jobs and for the entirety of 1896, while Lenin and Mahtob and
friends were held in the preliminary detention facility, which is where you were held
without trial until your sentence was handed down.
They freely access their comrades on the outside without too much difficulty.
They used coded language, an invisible ink and hidden notes smuggled into the binding of
books because the inspectors at the detention facility never tried too hard to stop it.
And in between this regular correspondence, Lenin, for example, was able to return to
more abstract theoretical ideas beginning work on his first contribution to Russian
Marxism, the development of capital in Russia, a Lenin's principal facilitator.
And all this was crib's Gaia, who was still on the outside and who had taken a job as a
copyist in the Railroad Administration.
She happened to have a co-worker who was a non movement family friend of the lianas, who
could somewhat innocuously visit Lenin in prison.
So people would send letters to Coop's guy at her office.
She would write or in code things into books and letters, hand them off to this family
friend who would then take it all into Lenin.
And it was in this way that everybody inside prison was able to cheer on the strikes of
1896. These great strikes were, of course, blamed on the socialist agitators, and the
socialist agitators were happy to take credit for it.
But in fact, the strikes were quite spontaneous and undirected by anyone inside the union
of struggle. The 1896 St.
Petersburg textile workers strikes were something of a watershed in retrospect, and their
importance only grew in time, as it seemed to be proving what Carl Koutsoukis had said in
which the Vilna program was working towards the merger of the blue collar worker and the
white collar socialist into a single movement.
The strikes lasted for three weeks in May and June 1896 and were the largest industrial
worker actions in Russian history to date.
The strike specifically hit the textile industries in Saint Petersburg, where you found
the lowest paid, least educated and most maltreated workers.
These people were doing 12 to 14 hour days and miserably hot conditions.
Doing monotonous activity began as a small walkout of just a few workers in one single
textile plant, but quickly spread to 20 more factories and in the end included at a
minimum 18000 workers and at a maximum thirty thousand depending on what source you're
looking at. Half of these workers were men and half of these workers were women.
And it was a big moment in Russian labor history.
And the liberal professor turned liberal politician Pavel Millia cough, who we talked
about back in episode ten point 20, said that the 1896 strikes were when the Russian
masses first stepped on to the revolutionary stage.
The first action started on May the 23rd, 1896, when about one hundred very low grade
assistance walked off the job and demanded pay for the recent plant closure that had
coincided with the coronation of Tsar Nicholas, the second, who I should mention we will
be catching back up with next week.
Now, in addition to this recent affront, they were also demanding back pay related to
this additional twenty minutes of unpaid labor that employers had started adding to the
end of the day back in 1887.
This is just 20 minutes that were tacked onto the end of the day that you weren't paid
for. It was as literal an expression of the exploitation of surplus labor as you could
get. The next day, these hundred assistants were joined by about 100 spinners at the
plant who further demanded a shorter workday, and this first plant would remain shut down
until June the 5th.
In the meantime, word of this strike spread to other workers as they talked to each other
at Canteen's or in parks or shared boardinghouses.
And it became very apparent very quickly that these workers understood the importance of
getting as many factories as possible to catch the contagion of strike just as a single
workers isolated without his or her co-workers.
A single factory is isolated without other factories also joining in.
So over the last week of May 1896, the strike spread to the six hundred workers in this
factory over here than the 700 in that factory over there, eventually reaching something
like 20 factories and all.
And as I said, somewhere between 13 and 30000 workers.
Now, these strikes were not started by the union of struggle, but when they got going,
the remaining free members of the union did what they could.
And principally that meant helping spread the word and make sure other people knew what
was happening. This turned out to be extremely helpful because previously the authorities
had just been able clamp down on all information about an isolated factory strike to stop
the contagion of strike from spreading.
But they were unable to do this in 1896.
So for three weeks, St Petersburg had to deal with tens of thousands of workers refusing
to work and the textile industry basically shutting down.
Now, in the end, no great victory was really won here.
Some small concessions were extracted and the factories restarted.
Now, another follow on strike in early 1897 did eventually lead to a maximum hour law
being passed by the government later in 1897.
But the importance of the 1896 strikes weren't just about what specific demands they
extracted. They were peaceful and disciplined and seemed to be both spontaneous and
widespread, which indicated prior organization and planning.
And given that on agitation had just come out, it seemed like the merger between the
workers and the socialist was in fact taking place.
And even if we know in retrospect that that merger was not fully consummated in 1896, it
certainly showed that things were heading in that direction, which terrified
conservatives, exhilarated radicals, and made cautious liberals wring their hands and beg
for reform. And working class demonstrations, strikes and direct actions would only pick
up steam as Russia's embrace of industrialization continued and everyone pointed
themselves toward these shockingly massive confrontations of 4:41.
But 4:41 is still a little ways off, though I promise we are moving towards it quicker
than you might realize, certainly quicker than anyone in Russia realized.
But before the revolution could come, the members of the Union of Struggle were going to
have to become exiles and emigres groups.
Guy was finally identified as a revolutionary and arrested in August of 1896, and she
drew got placed in the preliminary detention facility.
Then they all sat in custody until the end of January 1897, when their sentences were
handed down and they all agreed these sentences were surprisingly light.
Just three years exile in Siberia.
They even got three days freedom in St.
Petersburg to arrange their affairs and prepare for their trip.
And it was over these three days that Lenin and Ma Tof apparently cemented their lasting
friendship. In the few months they had worked together at the end of 1895, they hardly
knew each other. They were still strangers and they were kept separate.
In the preliminary detention facility.
But here in these last 72 hours, they bonded.
Even if they had been apart, they had gone through something together.
Their spirit was unbroken and both of them were as committed to the cause as ever.
So they agreed to ride out their three years in exile without making any attempt to
escape. And then they would meet backup and plot their next move.
Among the last minute arrangements Lennon made before he had to depart east was to write
a small message in invisible ink to croup Skiba, who being arrested later than the
others, was still in prison.
The invisible note was a marriage proposal.
Vladimir and Nadia had now known each other and work together for nearly three years.
And they liked each other and respected each other.
Most importantly, if she agreed to marry him, then their union would be recognized by the
state and she would be allowed to come join Lenin in Siberia, where they could continue
their work. And if nothing else, keep each other company.
She agreed. Now, the marriage of Lenin and Group Sky would never be the stuff of romance
novels, and down the road it will become emotionally complicated, but they will remain
loyally married until death did them part.
So next week, we will ship these revolutionaries off to Siberia, but keep the story in
St. Petersburg to pick back up with newlyweds whose marriage, for better or for worse,
was more like something out of a romance novel.
They really, truly loved each other as man and wife.
And I am talking here about Nicholas and ALEXANDRA, who are opening their reign as
emperor and empress of Russia by telling all those whose hopes for progress, reform and
change, hopes which had been raised by the elevation of the young czar, and that those
hopes were hopeless.
No, no, no, you silly heads, there will be no progress, reform and change.
There will be only orthodoxy, autocracy and nationality.
And isn't that simply marvelous?