This week's episode is brought to you by Audible.
Listening makes us smarter, more connected people.
It makes us better partners, parents and leaders.
And there's no better place to start listening than audible.
Audible members now get more than ever before.
You get to choose from three titles every month, one audio book plus two audible
originals that you can't hear anywhere else.
You also get access to exclusive sales and 30 percent off all regularly priced audio
books. Members also have unlimited access to more than 100 audio guided fitness and
meditation programs. So you can explore all the ways that listening to Audible can help
improve your mind, body and soul with entertainment, information and inspiration.
My personal recommendation this time is the latest massive classic which I've never read
but decided to finally listen to.
And it's the Once and Future King by T.H.
White. I've never read it, but it's always been on my list and I came by it because I got
the version read by Neville Jason.
That again is Neville Jason.
He's the one who read the version of Warren piece that I also listen to and also highly
recommend. So if you're looking for 33 hours of medieval Arthurian fantasy, it's pretty
great. You can start listening with a 30 day audible trial and your first audio book,
plus two audible originals are free visit audible dot com slash revolutions or text
revolutions 2 500 dash 500.
That again audible dot com a u d.
I B l e dot com slash r e v o l u t i o and s or text.
Revolutions 2 5 0 0 dash 5 0 0.
Hello and welcome to revolutions.
Episode ten point two, The Adventures of Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels.
We launched this series last week by launching the International Working Men's
Association in 1864.
Mostly I did this because the international tried to bring all left wing political groups
together under a single tent.
And since I'm trying to avoid making the Russian Revolution the narrow story of the
Bolsheviks, it seemed like a good way to establish that the Bolsheviks are going to
emerge as one faction that represented one variant of Russian Marxism.
But there were a lot of other factions and variants out there.
Unionist, anarchist, socialists, communists, reformers, revolutionaries.
But all that said, the Bolsheviks are ultimately the victorious faction from the
victorious variant of Marxism.
So it's going to be important to understand where they came from.
So as the title of this episode suggests, today will be an intertwined biographical
sketch of the lives of Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels that will take us through to the
foundation of the international.
And then next week, we will go through the critical concepts to understand the philosophy
and revolutionary program that became known as Marxism.
Then we'll go on to do the same for Bakunin and the anarchists so that we understand what
core revolutionary principles were out there that opposed what some people saw as the
authoritarian tendencies implicit in that Marxism.
Karl Marx was born in 1818 in the city of Tahrir.
A middle sized city in the Rhineland.
Little Karl was born just three years after the final fall of Napoleon.
Non-career had been under French administration going back to the 1790s.
But at the very recent Congress of Vienna, it was handed to the Prussian monarchy, whose
backward looking feudal conservatism clashed with the more progressive and forward
looking Rhine. Both of Karl's parents had ethnic Jewish lineage.
But to maintain his budding legal practice, Marx's father converted to Protestantism when
the Prussians took over and instituted more carefully draconian restrictions on what Jews
could and could not do.
Not that this conversion was anything but nominal.
Marx's father was into Contine Voltaire and the Enlightenment.
And though his children were baptized Luther and they were hardly a religious bunch.
Karl then got a good enough secondary education where he was sent to the University of
Bonn in 1835 to study law.
But Karl's first year at university was mostly filled with drinking beer and reckless
brawling. And so his dad shipped him off to the University of Berlin, which was located
in the capital of the kingdom before Carl departed.
He proposed marriage to Jenny Vun Vest fallen the daughter of a minor nobles civil
servant. And though the couple were only together in person once over the next five
years, and that one time they got together almost wrecked their relationship.
Their engagement held. And when they finally got married, they remained together through
the occasionally thick and very often thin rest of their lives.
Arriving in Berlin in 1836, Carl did something even worse than drinking and brawling.
He became enamored with philosophy in Germany in the mid 1830s.
Getting into philosophy meant getting into the just recently deceased Hagel, whose
philosophy cast an all encompassing shadow over German intellectual life, especially here
in the first half of the 19th century.
We'll talk a little bit more next week about what concepts Marx pulled out of Hegel.
But for now, the crowd Marx fell in with was the more radical and iconoclastic group
called The Young Aliens.
The young Hegg aliens were working from themes that came from the early days of the
French Revolution, and they took Hegel seriously when he said that the purpose and course
of history was all about the abolition of anything that restricts freedom and the use of
reason. The young Galen's were obviously critical of the repressive Prussian government,
but unable to express their opposition openly.
They turned to theology and philosophy.
They published challenges to the reliability, historicity and believability of
Christianity and the Bible.
They believed that by doing this, they could undermine one of the core pillars of the
Prussian monarchies alleged legitimacy.
Marx fell in with the young aliens at the worst possible moment because while their
controversial philosophy was tolerated by King Friedrich Wilhelm, the third of Prussia
when he died in 1840, and his son Friedrich Vill Helm, the fourth ascended to power, that
tolerance evaporated.
Now you know Friedrich Wilhelm, the fourth from our episodes on 1848 because he will be
the King of Prussia during the revolutions of 1848.
He's the one who had to crawl on his belly away from Berlin.
Conservative, romantic and evangelical.
This Friedrich Wilhelm had no tolerance for seditious blasphemy.
And so the young hag aliens were marked and blacklisted in spite of this.
Marx pressed on with a doctoral thesis that used a Galey and methods to analyze ancient
metaphysics. Even though his conclusions were now outside the boundaries of acceptable
thinking, knowing he couldn't submit his thesis to the University of Berlin, Marx instead
sent it to the more permissive University of Jayna, which made him a doctor of
philosophy. In 1841.
But as I just said, this was a bad time to be a young Hegelian, and Marx's dream of a
university position was squelched.
To make matters worse, Marx's father had died in 1838, beginning endless rounds of
bickering with his money over money from the inheritance to make a living.
Marx, like many of his ideological comrade, turned from academia to journalism.
So this newly minted doctor of philosophy moved to Cologne, where he submitted articles
to a progressive paper called the Rhineland News.
Showing off a rhetorical style that was a setback witty, intelligent, sarcastic and
occasionally savage.
This was also the period that by his own account, he started being handed socialist and
communist ideas, moving him away from abstract philosophy towards the realities of social
and economic life.
When the editorial brain trust of the Rhineland news fell apart, Marx became its de facto
editor in chief in the middle of 1842.
The paper was successful and that looked like that Karl Marx was going to be a newspaper
editor in Cologne. But the paranoid hand of conservative censorship dug up Marx's new
roots before they even had a chance to settle.
The Rhineland news was suppressed and banned in 1843.
Whatever plans Marx may have had for a normal life with a steady income were turned
upside down by his politics.
During his stint with the Rhineland News, Markes came into contact with a young
semi-anonymous contributor named Friedrich Engels.
Engels was two and a half years younger than Marx.
Born in 1820 in Barmen City, about 35 miles east of Cologne, the Engels family were first
devout evangelical Protestants and second industrial pioneers in the Rhineland.
They owned textile factories in the region and had further expanded up to Manchester,
England, which was rapidly transforming into a hive of industrial factories.
The scion of this rich, capitalist and very religious family rebelled on nearly every
front. In 1842, Engels did a requisite year in the Prussian army and stationed in Berlin.
He attended lectures and came into social and intellectual contact with both the young
Hegg aliens and various Proteau socialists.
Engels took to thinking and writing, and he submitted pieces to the Rhineland News
anonymously, as I said, since he was the son of filthy rich capitalists scandalized by
their son's new friends and his new ideas.
His parents sent him to Manchester to apprentice in a family owned factory there and in
the annals of parents trying to halt the radicalization of their children, only to see it
backfire. Sending Friedrich Engels to Manchester may be the single greatest backfire in
world history. Now, despite having lost his job, Karl Marx and Jenny von Vest fallen
married and moved to Paris in October of 1843 under the semi liberal auspices of the July
monarchy, Paris was a haven for emigre radicals from across Europe Russians and Poles,
Italians, Germans, Spaniards, creating a swirling mildew of nationalists and Democrats,
socialists, anarchists, tepid reformers and single minded revolutionaries.
The Marxists settled down, and their first daughter, little Jenny, was born in early
1844. Marx worked as a contributor and editor for a couple of different German language
publications, meant for audiences in the emigre community, but also for audiences back in
Germany. None of this work, though, was steady or particularly profitable.
Engle's, meanwhile, went off to Manchester, where he embarked on a program of
self-radicalization. He was absolutely appalled by what he found there.
Shortly after arriving, Engle's met an Irish worker named Mary Burns.
They fell in love and began a 20 year non marriage marriage where they never tied the
knot because they both rejected the oppressive bourgeois institution that was marriage.
Mary Byrnes was Engels is early guide to Manchester and he was deeply affected by what he
saw. And basically, he saw every single stereotypical thing you might cram into a period
piece drama about England during the industrial revolution.
Crowded slums, ill fed, filthy workers, men and women walking around with missing limbs,
child labour, environmental degradation, grinding metal, choking, black smoke.
The works Engels started writing articles and submitting them to various outlets.
Among them, those Marks was working on in Paris.
Pretty soon, Engels decided to collect and revise his notes and articles and ideas and
turn them into a book that he called The Conditions of the Working Classes in England,
which became his first contribution to mid 19th century socialism.
Now, in semi-regular correspondence with Marx, Engels swung through Paris on his way back
to Germany so they could meet.
And on August 28, 1844, they got together at a cafe near the Palais Royale.
It was not technically the first time they had met, but it was the first time that they
realized what kindred spirits they were.
The two young men, both still in their mid-twenties, got along famously and Engels wound
up staying at Marks's home for the next 10 days.
The beginning of a lifelong collaboration and friendship.
Marked by this point had begun thinking deeper and more seriously about the link between
economics, society and politics, and not just in the abstract.
Marx was a man who dreamed of revolution, and he had hit upon this idea that the new
industrial, quote unquote, working class might just be miserable enough to be the engine
of the next revolution.
And when angles came along with these horribly evocative descriptions of working class
misery, they agreed with each other that they were really onto something that they had
discovered. The revolutionary proletariat, both Marx and Angles, then got involved, at
least peripherally, with a radical group of emigre German artisans who had formed
themselves into something they called the League of the just to promote socialist and
anarchist philosophy and prepare for the very revolution Marx and Engels now believed was
coming. The Marks's probably would have stayed in Paris indefinitely, or at least until
the revolution came. But Prussian diplomats complain to the French government about
radical German propaganda being produced in Paris and in 1845 demanded that some of the
more offensive elements be expelled from France.
Specifically citing this guy, Karl Marx, to his horror and dismay, Marx discovered he had
one week to leave the country and the order was signed personally by France SWAT.
Gizo earning lifelong enmity from Marx, who then had to pack up his wife Jenny, who was
pregnant again, and little Jenny, and scoot over to Brussels to start over again to keep
himself free of the long arm of Prussian conservatism.
About six months after arriving in Brussels, Marx renounced his citizenship.
Their arrival in Brussels happened to coincide with the beginning of the hungry forties.
The potato blight and harvest failures were going to send recessive shockwaves
reverberating through every sector of the European economy.
So the going was hard for the Marx family and his son Edgar was born in February 1847 at
a very difficult time, both for his family and for families across Europe.
In Brussels, Marx and Engels also reconnected on a more permanent basis, and they
actively collaborated on various book ideas, some of which, like the Holy Family, were
published at the time, while others, like the German ideology, sat around in piles of
paper until Soviet researchers put them out in the 1920s and 1930s.
Most of these ideas, though, revolved around their various beefs with other German
radicals and philosophers.
Old friends and mentors became derided rivals as Marx and Angles moved decisively towards
the idea that material economics was the basis of everything else.
And if you disagreed, prepared to be skewered with a sarcastic and acidic pen they broke
with the young had Galen's.
They attacked other socialist theorists as Philistines and heretics and reactionary pawns
who all either had things upside down, or if they had things right side up, they
advocated different means to the same ends.
Now, Marx and Engels were not unique in this regard.
And in return they were attacked, derided and mocked just as hard and with just as much
venom. But outside of these beefs, they continued to keep an eye out for the revolution.
And in one of Marx's works from this period that only saw the light of day well after he
was dead, he wrote that, quote, Philosophers have hit there, too.
Only interpreted the world in various ways.
The point is to change it.
But when it came to changing the world, Marx was never a fan of Blanky style
revolutionary Vanguard ism and he wanted the working class move Mr.
B. Out in the open, not secret that their great power was in their great numbers.
Let the ruling classes tremble, exerting more intellectual force inside the League of the
Just. Marx succeeded in getting them to make a strategic shift in June of 1847.
The League of the just rebranded itself as the Communist League and then came out into
the open to attract members and announced their program.
They commissioned Marx and Angles to draft a manifesto.
Mark's got to work using as his foundation a pamphlet Engels had written called
Principles of Communism, which Marx then redrafted and reworked into what has gone down
in history as the Communist Manifesto.
Now, as I said in Episode 8.1,
the Communist Manifesto was more prophetic than it was a work rooted in the actual
economic and material conditions of Europe.
At that moment. Prophetic in part because angles just so happened to have been sent to
Manchester, which was then on the leading edge of full blown industrial capitalism, which
would not really sweep the globe until the later 19th century and early 20th century.
But it did show that most of the basics of later fully developed Marxism were already in
place by 1848 historical materialism, class conflict, the exploitation of labor by the
bourgeoisie, and the historical role of the proletariat as the next revolutionary class
whose aim would be the abolition of bourgeois property relations.
The Communist Manifesto also advocated such civilization shattering policies as a
progressive income tax, a national bank, free, universal, secular education and the
suburbs. This revolutionary statement of Principles was published in London in February
1848 by complete coincidence.
The February revolution hit Paris at almost that same moment.
For all their anticipation and planning and organizing, this revolution took Marx and
Angles and frankly, everybody else by surprise.
As revolutions nearly always do.
The authorities in Brussels were terrified by the revolution in France.
And on March the 3rd, 1848, they expelled everyone who might potentially destabilise
Belgium. Marx and Angles and other Communist League guys were on the list.
But that was OK because their lives as emigres and exiles was over.
It was time to go home and embark on the revolution.
Now, at this point, everything is moving in a straight line.
Marx and Engels had been young, stubbornly nonconformist students who had been
radicalized, politically, dreamed about and work towards a revolution against the
conservative powers of Europe.
And now that revolution was at hand.
With the revolution afoot, Marx and his family went back to Cologne.
Other members of the Communist League went to other German cities to start a Pan German
revolutionary network to make sure this went right and by went right.
Marx specifically meant carrying out his theory of a double revolution in Prussia.
First, they must recreate the course of the French Revolution.
Have all classes combined behind the liberal bourgeoisie to topple the Prussian monarchy.
Once that was accomplished, the working class proletariat could break off an immediately
stage a second revolution against the oh so recently triumphant liberal bourgeoisie.
Thus they would advance rapidly towards the dream of communism.
Marks's part in all this was to wield the pen, and he started a new paper dubbed the New
Rhineland News to publish his ideas.
The paper was successful locally, but events moved very quickly and Marks's activities in
1848 would ultimately be limited just to the city of Cologne.
The Communist League struggled to make inroads with the actual workers they were supposed
to be representing. They also had trouble forming alliances with other socialist leaders
who Marx and Angles had just spent the last few years so thoroughly mocking and deriding
to say nothing of the articles in the new Rhineland news that denounced rival working
class organizations as reactionary.
Not because they were insufficiently radical, but because they were too radical.
These leaders wanted to skip the bourgeois revolution that Marx thought was so essential.
So they didn't want to make alliances with the Democrats.
They wanted to move straight on to the revolution of the worker.
And these leaders, in turn, thought Marx was a cowardly stooge of the bourgeoisie for
advancing the necessity of this bourgeois revolution in the first place.
Not that it mattered. By the fall and winter of 1848, everything was falling apart.
The King of Prussia disbanded the Prussian diet, and the Frankfurt Parliament did not
seem long for this world.
Only with the walls closing in in April 1849 did Marx belatedly conclude that the
Democrats were too cautious and uncommitted, and that a strong, unified push had to come
from the workers and the workers alone.
But in May of 1849, the hammer of reaction fell hard in Cologne, flexing his muscle after
being forced to sew, ignominiously crawl on his belly.
King Friedrich Wilhelm, the fourth, put the Prussian army on the move.
The Frankfurt parliament broke and fled, disappearing into the footnotes of history.
Marx, who had never regained his renounced citizenship, was expelled from Cologne as an
alien. On May the 19th, which coincided with the last issue of the now banned and
suppressed new Rhineland news in these chaotic final days, Engels joined a volunteer
rifle company led by Future Union Army Major General Auguste Volk to fight the last stand
of the revolution. Marx was no soldier and he made for Paris, and he would occasionally
be dogged for the rest of his life by accusations of cowardice by those who did stay in
Germany and fight. But the cause was well and truly hopeless.
By this point, and the company Engels had joined was quickly pushed across the border
into Switzerland. In Paris, Marx hoped to find radical Democrats and socialists combining
into a coalition that would seize control of the Second Republic and turn France into the
revolution's war machine.
Just as the first republic had once done.
But by now, French President Bonaparte and the party of order had come to power.
After probably witnessing the suppression of those Paris radicals in June of 1849, Marx
was told he could stay in France if he removed himself to the coast of Brittany and made
no trouble. Instead, he quit Paris and went to London, calling for Jenny and their three
kids to join him. He arrived in England in August of 1849.
Karl Marx was 32 years old.
The revolution was hopefully only set back, but not yet dead.
Marx prepared for a life of temporary exile in London.
He would live there for the rest of his life.
That life in London was tough on the Marks's as the city filled with other exiles fleeing
the reactionary hammer, working class artisans and more professional types like doctors
and lawyers could find work.
But Karl Marx was a radical journalist who didn't speak English and who carried few other
credentials or letters of recommendation.
The Marks's spent the next few years hovering around destitution.
They were broke and constantly harassed by creditors.
During these miserable years, the German emigre community in London was itself a
miserable mix of pessimistic disillusionment or recklessly grandiose declarations that
they must restart the revolution now.
It was full of rivalries, infighting, denunciations, blame, tossing police spies and
agents provocateur.
Marx's mood completely soured, and he systematically got into fights with everyone,
contributing to his isolation from practically everyone.
Jenny gave birth to another son in September of 1849, but the baby died just a month
later. Just about the only friend Mark's had left in the world was Angles, who arrived in
England in November 1849, himself destitute and without prospects.
Engels decided to tactically renounce his revolutionary past so that his parents would
let him work in the family business again, so that he could make a living not just for
himself, but he also sent cash when he could to.
He wasn't very happy about having to take this job, but it was all for a good cause.
Marx and Engels is last hope for getting the revolution going again in Germany ended in
1851 when their last remaining allies in Cologne.
People who they were actually allied with were arrested in a police sweep.
Then at the end of the year came the last cruel blow, the last spark of hope that Paris
might yet save the revolution in Europe was smothered by the coup of print President
Bonaparte in December 1851.
The revolution was over.
Friendless, broke.
Angry and terminally depressed.
Marx responded by writing the 18th broodmare of Louis Bonaparte.
It's easily Marx's greatest literary work.
And I really do highly recommend it, especially since if you've listened to the episodes
on 1848 and the Paris Commune and then these episodes right now, you'll have some idea
who and what he is talking about, making use of a line from angles that history repeats
itself first as tragedy, then as farce.
Marx deconstructed the course of the failed revolution in France.
But when you read the 18th primary, keep in mind that when Marx is criticizing all the
dummies who thought that they were going to play act a revival of the French Revolution,
he's kind of talking about himself and his scathing criticism of those who thought cross
class alliances were possible or would end in anything but the betrayal of the working
class. He's also talking about himself repudiating and walking away from those positions.
It all makes for great reading.
It's a great review of 1848 and its aftermath.
It's really well written.
It's fun and rightly one of the great masterpieces of 19th century political commentary.
It's also an epistle from a failed revolutionary wallowing in veiled self-criticism as he
descends into broke and friendless obscurity, having alienated himself from everyone.
Renouncing revolutionary activism, we now get to the familiar version of an older and
more worn down Karl Marx going daily to the British Museum Library to pore over mountains
of government records and reports, newspapers, history books and philosophy as he made
mountains of notes.
For any eternally forthcoming magnum opus on political economy.
To make a living, he got hooked into a job as European correspondent for Horace Greeley's
Progressive, an abolitionist paper, The New York Daily Tribune.
Writing for The New York Daily Tribune gave Marks the steady income he needed, and Engels
pitched in again to ghostwrite some of these articles.
For example, accounts of the Crimean War, which gave Engels an outlet for his pen and got
his friend a few more paychecks.
But though Marx's life was stabilizing, he was still depressing and rocked by tragedy.
Their eight year old son, Edgar, unexpectedly succumbed to a fatal ailment in 1855, and
then another baby died in 1857 without even being named Marx.
His health was in a state of constant decline.
He drank too much and smoked too many cheap cigars.
And the possibility that none of this really mattered.
None of this was ever going to matter seemed very real indeed.
But he kept scribbling his notes in the British Library.
Dedicated full time to research and writing.
Marx finally produced a contribution to the critique of political economy in 1859, which
developed in further detail his theories about.
Capitalism money politics and history.
It was meant to advance and correct the traditions of classical economics that had begun
with Adam Smith and David Ricardo.
It was exciting and bold stuff and sold quite well among interested German readers and it
gave marks both the moral and financial boost he needed to finally fulfill his life's
work which would eventually become known simply as Das Kapital or in English capital in
the early 1860.
Things were looking up.
Engels his father finally died and so his communist son inherited the family's capitalist
fortune. Engels put Marx on an annual alliance that put his friend who Engels was
convinced was one of history's great geniuses into a state of permanent financial
security in 1864 Marx was forty six years old.
Fifteen years removed from any kind of political activity and was nearing the completion
of his first volume of capital when a French anarchist acquaintance came round looking
for Germans to attend a meeting in a week's time at St..
MARTIN tall to join the disparate and separate forces who stood opposed to the political
and more importantly economic status quo.
Marx suggested a friend of his who was actually a worker but he went along to the meeting
himself his intellectual reputation had been boosted by a contribution to the critique of
political economy. But among emigre radicals he was still mostly known as an old 1848 or
who had pissed everyone off and then retreated to the library to be an intellectual grump
who never hung out with anyone never really learned English and wasn't on speaking terms
with most of the other Germans so that is how Karl Marx came to join the International
Working Men's Association marking his return to active leftwing politics and giving him a
vehicle for his more mature and developed theories.
And next week we will talk about those more mature and developed theories because they
are going to be so important to nearly all revolutions going forward.
Historical materialism class conflict the proletariat and the bourgeoisie modes of
production and most especially how this would fit with the never ending question of how
to turn the world upside down or in the estimation of Marx right side.