This week's episode is brought to you, by a way, a way creates thoughtful products
designed to change how you see the world.
They started with the perfect suitcase crafted with features that make travel more
seamless. Now they offer a range of essentials that solve real travel problems.
So all you have to think about is where you're headed next, because getting away means
getting more out of every trip.
To come away knows that everyone has a different travel style.
That's why they make their carry-on in an array of colors, two sizes and two materials, a
strong yet flexible public carbonate and anodized aluminum.
These are suitcases that are designed to last a lifetime.
But if any part of your suitcase ever breaks away, standout customer service team will
arrange to have it fixed or replaced.
a.S.A.P. The bags come with an optional injectable battery to keep your phone charged for
360 degree spinner wheels to guarantee a smooth ride and free shipping on any away order
within the continuous United States, Europe or Australia.
Our away bag has been great for all our world travels.
The lightweight design makes it easy to maneuver around through sidewalks and on and off
the metro and trains and in and out of planes.
And on more than one occasion, that battery has saved me from a dying cell phone with no
available power outlets in sight.
So for $20 off a suitcase, visit a way travel dot com slash revolutions twenty.
That's revolutions to zero.
And use the promo code revolutions twenty during checkout again for $20 off a suitcase,
visit a way travel dot com slash revolutions twenty and use the promo code revolutions to
zero during checkout.
Hello and welcome to revolutions.
Episode ten point twenty one The Socialist Revolutionaries.
Last time we talked through the liberal or at least liberal ish tradition of 19th century
Russia, however thin the thread winds are, Nicholas the second ascended the throne in
1894. There was a group inside the intelligentsia who hoped the arrival of a young new
monarch would bring liberal political reform.
A Constitution representative government.
Freedom of speech. And the press and assembly.
Something resembling the rule of law.
Economic modernisation.
Social improvement.
They were as grossed out as any radical by the chauvinist stick authoritarian and
backwards triptych of orthodoxy, autocracy and nationality.
It embarrass them abroad and humiliated them at home.
But those liberals were always going to want to stop well short of the places more
radical leaders wanted to take Russia in the 1890s.
Whether these new groups of Marxist Social Democrats or the groups we're gonna talk about
today, the neo narrowest socialist revolutionaries or as everyone calls them, the S Rs.
To begin this discussion, we need to back up to the late 1870s in 1879, the terrorism
question divided the once unified Land and Liberty Party into two factions the small
minority who followed Tarnoff into the splinter group Black repartition, which then wound
up breaking with the protest ideology entirely when they formed the explicitly Marxist
emancipation of labor group.
In 1884.
But the majority of land in liberty had done what?
That's right. They embraced the terrorist campaign, redoubled themselves.
People's will, and went off to kill the Tsar.
Finally succeeding in 1881.
But what happened to them after that?
Well, as I mentioned somewhat obliquely in episode ten point sixteen and ten point
seventeen, the People's Will organization was almost immediately smashed and scattered by
the vengeful fist of the krona, the TSA's new Secret Police Service.
The members of people's will were hunted, arrested, tried by military tribunals, and then
either hanged or exiled.
Those who slipped this round up were forced into exile, taking off for Switzerland or
France or Britain. A few stayed behind and dug in even harder on terrorists campaigning.
But Thorold networks were so disruptive and the repressive hand of the new czar,
Alexander the third was so heavy that it was nearly impossible to meet publisher plan.
So they're a great prize for successfully killing the Tsar was the destruction of their
party. Not only were the 1880s a low point for radical new road ism in terms of literal
personnel and party organization, but it also seemed like their ideas and theories were
dead too, because what was the main organizing principle behind people's will when those
critical years leading up to the assassination of Czar Alexander the Second?
Well, first, while they fought for the peasants and wanted to base future Russian
socialism in the rural villages, the peasantry was at present too hopelessly smothered by
the repressive imperial government to rise up en masse.
It would only be after the political war against the Tsarist state was won, that the
peasants could be freed and rural socialism could flourish.
Now one of the main arguments in favor of an assassination campaign carried out by an
elite Cordray of revolutionary terrorists was that it would deal a fatal physical and
psychic blow to the forces of political despotism.
On the physical level, this was very much a kill the head and the body dies kind of
thing. But on the psychic level, on an almost cosmic level, assassinating the czar would
prove that the czar was just a man after all, not some divine demigod, and the
superstitious peasants would then be roused from their fearful and superstitious stupor.
So on both a practical and a spiritual level, killing the czar was supposed to
simultaneously cause the imperial apparatus to fall apart and trigger the people to rise
up, and then people's will did it.
They killed the czar. And what happened?
Pretty much the opposite.
The repressive Imperial Police state only spread wider and drove deeper and ask for the
peasants. They did nothing.
They were seemingly as inert and apathetic as ever.
Certainly there was no mass insurrection accompanying the death of Czar Alexander, the
second kind of disproving and discrediting all the strategic, tactical and ideological
assumptions that peoples well had been operating under.
Not leads of what might seem like a pretty straight historical story for the evolution of
Russian radicalism at the end of the 19th century.
The nihilism of the 1860s had led to the mass mobilization going to the people of 1874,
which failed, giving way to the elite terrorism of people's will, which was exposed as
fatally flawed in 1881, paving the way for the exciting new brand of Russian Marxism to
pick up the fallen torch in the 1890s.
And this is what happened. Well, yes.
And now everything I just said definitely led a new generation of radicals to be drawn to
the Marxist ideas being disseminated by the emancipation of labor group, because Marxist
analysis was going to make a lot of sense against the backdrop of the rapid
industrialization of the Vitesse system.
But neuroticism did not die in the 1880s.
It simply went into hibernation.
And when it emerged from its slumber in the 1890s, it still found a lot of enthusiastic
adherents. Not for the least reason that even with the rapid industrialization of the
Vitesse system, the empire was still overwhelmingly rural, agrarian and peasant.
The revival of the fortunes of neuroticism can be traced to two coinciding events in the
early 1890s.
The first was the famine of 1891 1892.
That we talked about an episode ten point eighteen bad harvests led to frightening
scarcity and then outright famine, which resulted in the deaths of upwards of 500000
people. The government was simply unprepared and unequipped to deal with the crisis.
And while people's will theory had been if we killed the Tsar, maybe the people will lose
faith in the Tsar. There was now a new revelation.
If the czar lets the people die, then maybe the people will lose faith in the czar.
The experience of mass starvation caused by bad luck, but exacerbated by incompetence,
indifference or outright malevolence by the Tsarist imperial apparatus.
It was a real blow to the regime's perceived legitimacy.
Old Neruda's veterans of the 1870s, working among the peasants in the 1890s, remarked how
much more open and receptive they were to radical critiques of the government.
So going to the people had failed in 1874, but suddenly it was maybe an idea whose time
had come. By 1894.
And speaking of those Naruto's veterans, they are the other coinciding event of the early
1890s. Many of those who had been tried and convicted of various crimes back in the
1870s, like those convicted in the famous trial of 193, were now completing their
sentences of Siberian exile and returning home by the early 1890s.
Then in his benevolent generosity, when Tsar Nicholas the second ascended the throne, he
marked the occasion by granting wide reaching amnesties and pardons that invited former
political prisoners to rejoin society.
Now, sure, many of those who returned were like, okay, that's all in the past.
Siberia sucked. I have paid for my youthful follies and I would like to just go home now,
please. But plenty of those returning had changed, not one jot, and they had spent their
years either in prison or in exile, simply biding their time.
And because they had gone into isolation, holding old in protest ideas, they came out of
that isolation, holding those same old ideas.
They missed the memo that their ideas had been discredited.
That narrowed ism in the rural peasants were old news.
The future belonged to the Marxists and the urban proletariat.
Now they were not insensible to the fact that conditions in the 1890s were not what they
had been in the 1870s, and that past experience and new ideas would mean some of the
program would need to be adapted or revised.
But still, they had no intention of being merely a stepping stone on the road to Marxist
proletarian revolution.
OK, so what we are up to specifically in this week's episode is setting up the formation
of the coming Socialist Revolutionary Party in January of 1982.
So what we're gonna spend the rest of today talking about are the four distinct groups
who would start coming together independently of each other.
In the mid 1890s, who would go on to form the core of that socialist revolutionary party.
These groups formed organically and separately, often starting with one or two people
deciding one day to get a little group together, maybe to educate the workers or the
peasants, maybe to offer reading material and discussion space for students, maybe to try
to link with like minded members of the intelligentsia.
These groups or self-starting and self-funded.
They were often a mix of old veterans and young upstarts.
They were never very big.
7 people here.
A dozen people there, 50 at most.
But what they all had in common is that they were working in the old neuritis tradition.
Well, Matt. And they were all destined to feed into the S Rs.
So the first group we'll talk about is called the Union of Socialist Revolutionaries, but
they will be better known to history by the shorthand name the Northern Union.
And just as a general warning as we go forward, not just for today, but for the rest of
the series. All these people are going to be calling themselves the Socialist
Revolutionary Union and the Workers Union of Revolutionary Socialists and the Socialist
Revolutionary Party, as opposed to the Revolutionary Socialist Party as opposed to the
Party for Revolutionary Socialism as opposed to the Revolutionary Party of Socialists.
Don't worry too much about the names just now.
Just try to follow along with the ideas and the people who are participating in the
movement. So anyway, what becomes known as the Northern Union, formed in 1896 in the
southwestern city of sahÃtof, but moved its headquarters to Moscow the following year.
And just to remind you of the scale here, the Northern Union at its peak is only going to
have about 30 full fledged members.
Me organizing force behind the Northern Union was Andre Argan Off, who will be on the
Central Committee of the SRB come the revolution of 1985.
Born in 1866, he was too young to have been a part of the original run of peoples, well,
terrorism. But in his early 20s, Argonaut hooked up with the few 1880s holdouts in Tomsk
and then spent the early 1890s circulating among student groups, which led to the more
formal organization of the Northern Union a few years later.
When it was formed, the Northern Union represented the most unreconstructed ideological
continuity with the now defunct people's will.
aag enough would write a declaration of principles for the group in 1898 called Our
Tasks, which set out their political goals and tactical approach for the revolution.
Both friends and rivals alike noted that it was cribbed almost entirely from similar
people's will declarations in the 1870s.
The argument was that though the peasants, the people would be the principal
beneficiaries of the revolution, they were not yet ready to carry out the revolution
themselves. They would not be able to overcome their poverty, ignorance and apathy until
the Tsarist apparatus had been brought down.
And the best way to attack and topple that apparatus was through violent terrorist
assassination campaigns.
Before there can be a social or economic revolution, there must first be a political
revolution carried out by diehard radicals inside the intelligentsia.
So this I mean, all of this I just said five minutes ago when I was talking about what
people's will believed and other groups, among them Neon A ROTAS and anarchists and
Marxist Social Democrats would read our tasks and find it full of tried and failed
Neruda's dogmatism.
While the Northern Union was getting going, there was another developmental pattern
centered, especially in Ukraine.
That is collectively referred to as the southern groups.
Unlike argand off and the Northern Union, the southern groups really leaned into the neo
part of neo narrowed ism and they adapted their program to a account for the failures of
the 1870s.
B Acknowledge the reality of Vitesse system Russia in the 1890s and c grappled directly
with the Marxist analysis now going mainstream inside radical circles.
On the matter of terrorism, they either tried to avoid directly taking a stand or coming
down firmly in opposition.
Terrorism and assassination might be viscerally exciting, but it had not and would not
get the job done. The southern groups were also recalculating the immediate revolutionary
potential of the peasants, while the old recycled people's will dogma that the Northern
Union was spouting said they can't be activated until the Tsar has been toppled.
The southern groups suspected that things had changed.
The times changed.
And then activating the peasants was not only possible, but necessary to carry out a
socialist revolution in Russia.
And they also agreed that a sure path to appealing to the workers and the peasants was to
focus on addressing their immediate concerns and grievances and then helping them
alleviate those immediate concerns and grievances.
But just as the southern groups criticized the Northern Union for reheating spoiled
potatoes, the Northern Union criticized the southern groups for splitting off from
narrowed ism entirely.
This isn't neon or ism.
This is something else entirely.
For example, one of the big features of neuroticism was a desire to either head off or
leapfrog over industrial capitalism, and the southern groups tended to accept the Marxist
position that capitalism was coming and that the urban proletariat might very well serve
as the advance guard of the next revolution.
On top of this heresy, they added another.
That willingness to talk about and improve living and working conditions was a break with
the core beliefs of both narrowed ism and Bakunin is anarchism.
Those guys wanted to reject capitalism, a root and branch and not sap the revolution of
its vitality by marginally improving the workers lives in exchange for tacitly accepting
this new capitalist system.
Putting padding on the chains does not break the chains.
But the southern groups were not closet Marxists.
In fact, they had more faith in the rural peasantry than the Northern Union did.
They still believe that the future of Russia was agrarian socialism and that the failure
of the going to the people should not be taken as permanent proof that a revolutionary
army would never come marching out of the rural countryside.
When they looked around in the mid 1890s, they noted that conditions had changed and
there were two new classes who provided an excellent opportunity to more efficiently and
productively focus recruitment, propaganda and education efforts on the peasants.
First there was the so-called rural intelligentsia.
And second, there was that large subset of the growing industrial working class who
regularly returned home to their native villages.
Neither of those classes had really existed back in the 1870s, but now they did.
And now they could be used.
As to the first class, this rural intelligentsia, the zemser wound up being the factory
that produced them. Remember, the Zemser were focused on creating schools and hospitals
and health services and improving local infrastructure.
So this drew out to more rural areas, educated professionals who used to be found only in
the bigger cities. Teachers, lawyers, engineers, doctors and so forth.
And then especially thanks to the educational improvements of the 1870s and 1880s.
You saw a new generation growing up much better educated than their parents.
Now, obviously, many people in this rural intelligentsia group are going to wind up
mostly in political sympathy with the liberal zemser for constitutionalists that we
talked about last week, but there were plenty with more radical ambitions, especially
among the teachers. They would start their own little reading, discussion and medication
all circles. Partly this was to alleviate boredom, but partly it was out of real zeal.
And you would see things like little lending libraries get organized that allowed the
increasingly literate local population to access new and interesting ideas.
And one of the great lessons learned of the failed going to the people was that the
people had not known or trusted the people who went to the people.
But the rural intelligentsia was engaged with far more permanent cohabitation and they
were identified as the perfect bridge between the elite revolutionary leadership still
based in the capital cities and the mass of peasants.
They hoped one day to organize and lead.
The other group that this elite revolutionary leadership realized had potential was that
semi seasonal labor force that moved back and forth between industrial labor sites like
factories and mines and railroad projects and their home villages.
If you were a socialist revolutionary organizer, you could maneuver your way into one of
these mass concentrations of industrial workers that we talked about at the end of
episode ten point eighteen on the Vita system and find a very receptive audience, an
audience whose minds had been opened by the general terribleness of their working
conditions. Then you could explain to them your theory of what socialist revolution would
look like, and they would carry that message back to their friends and families in the
home villages. Ideas that were now being delivered not by strangers who just showed up
one day and started saying, Hey, you know what?
Down with the czar.
They heard it from their cousin or their sister or their best friend.
And with a little luck, when those workers then returned to their factories, the people
left behind might find a radical member of the rural intelligentsia lurking around, ready
to talk more about all of these interesting new ideas and further foster revolutionary
consciousness. So this was a pretty exciting realization and it made the Southern groups
more convinced that right now, today, they should think of the peasants as a force that
could be mobilized. Now, as I've said, these groups are not very big and they would still
have to be based in the cities, focused mostly on the urban workers, but they could
create a social web that would spread ideas.
And when the time was right, a revolutionary army could come marching out of the rural
countryside. This wasn't going to happen overnight, but the path was clear and the heart
of what is going to become socialist revolutionary ideology started beating.
The third pillar of the future is ours grew out of a worker education circle in Minsk
that was dubbed the Workers Party or the political emancipation of Russia.
Founded in 1895, the Workers Party for the political emancipation of Russia was unique in
that it was specifically focused on the Jewish community, a community that held its own
unique position inside the Russian empire.
Navigating as they did between the anti-Semitic assumptions of the czarist authorities,
that the Jews did not really fit into a system of orthodoxy, autocracy and nationality
and the anti-Semitic assumptions of many revolutionary Marxists and populists and
anarchists that the Jews were greedy parasites, adversaries, not allies.
In the coming revolution.
But that said, this Jewish centered Workers Party operated a lot like the Northern Union
did in the tradition of terroristic narrowed as a man orgasm.
They believed that first and foremost, the revolutionary task was to overthrow the Tsar.
What better way to fight the encroaching tyranny of capitalism than overthrowing the
state which backed up those capitalists with the force of the police and the army and an
array of anti-labor laws?
So the Workers Party for the political emancipation of Russia and the Northern Union were
largely in agreement about both the task and the methods of revolution.
One of the key organizers of the Workers Party was an old veteran of the 1870s who was
among those leaders now returning from a long period of political exile.
They had in fact, spent the last 20 years bouncing around between prisons, penal labor
camps and supervised exile.
I'm speaking of Yekaterina Bresch, cofs Gaia, a revolutionary stalwart on her way to
earning the nickname Babushka, the grandmother.
Born in 1844, into a well-to-do land and serf owning family purse, coskata was 17 years
old when the Emancipation Decree was issued in 1861.
She enthusiastically helped her father navigate the logistics of freeing the family's
serfs and took it upon herself to organize education and literacy programs.
Two years later, she followed a normal social path by marrying a landowning magistrate.
But that was a very short lived experiment with normalcy.
She left her husband two years later and moved to Kiev with her sister and a friend named
Maria called akina.
Upon arrival, the three of them set up house and got super into Bakunin ist anarchism
meeting at this point. A young 20 year old name, Pavel Axlerod.
Now, her sister appears to have died young, but in 1874, Prescotts, Gaia and Maria called
akina, of course, went to the people.
They were, however, soon tipped off that they might be arrested and called.
Akino went home.
But Bresch cofs Gaia simply bounced to other villages.
Eventually, though, she was arrested while trying to pass a checkpoint dressed as a
peasant. She failed to act the part and show the instinctive deference expected from a
peasant woman. She blew her own cover and was arrested.
So now she's in jail.
And then she wound up as one of the 193 in the famous trial of the hundred and ninety
three, when it was her turn to stand a queue, she gave a defiant speech declaring that
she did not recognize the court's authority over her and that, yes, she was a socialist
and that, yes, she was a revolutionary and she was damn proud of it.
The court, of course, recognized its own authority over her and unlike most other
arrested women who were acquitted and set free.
BISKUPSKI I was given five years penal labor in Siberia and I have seen it claimed that
she was the first woman in Russia sentenced to prison labor for political crimes.
And now I must break this story so that we can tie ourselves back to some big drama from
previous episodes because after the sentencing, Bresch coughs, his old friend Maria
called akina resolved on a plan to murder the prosecutor in revenge, and Maria got
together with one of her new friends to plot a double assassination.
And that new friend was Veera ZATZ sulik.
So, yes, when I talked about Zeze Xu Lynches Conrad in the murder conspiracy that was
Maria killed akina. This is a very small world we're talking about here.
Anyway, Welles sulik was able to get her shot off called akina was not, and instead she
was arrested and sentenced herself to 10 years in Siberia.
But getting back to brush costs scam after a couple years, her sentence was reduced from
penal labor to mere exile and she immediately attempted to flee the country.
But the attempt failed and so she got four more years hard labor.
After completing that sentence, she was back to living in mere exile again.
When an American journalist came through in 1885 and Bresch cost, Gaia gave an interview
where she said that maybe she would die in exile.
Maybe here children would die in exile, maybe her grandchildren would die in exile.
But someday it would all be worth it.
This interview made her a minor celebrity among unionists and radicals and progressive
liberals in the English speaking world.
Though, as it turned out, neither she nor her children nor her grandchildren died in
exile in 1896, she was released as part of a general amnesty that accompanied the formal
coronation of Nicholas.
The second now well past 50 years old.
She returned home so full of thankfulness at the amnesty that she went right back to
organizing for a socialist revolution.
This time in Minsk.
Her partner in crime during this period was future inner circle as our leader, Gregory
Yasuni. You're Sunni, was 25 years younger than Breast scoffs Gaia, but they formed a
working revolutionary partnership with Bresch cofs Gaia.
As the dynamic, charismatic, passionate, living witness to the indomitable spirit of
revolutionary will.
Then once the audience was fired up, Gear Chinny would follow in her wake and handle the
practical logistics of organizing and establishing groups and communication between them.
Their partnership made the Workers Party for the Political Emancipation of Russia one of
the most dedicated and well organized inside Russia.
And though even at its peak, there were never more than 60 full time members.
They would be one of the backbones of the coming S.R.
coalition. The fourth and final group we need to talk about today are those not in Russia
at all, because if you had been in people's will when the reactionary hammer came down in
1881 and you managed to escape arrest and execution or exile, you invariably wound up
fleeing abroad and settling in Russian emigre enclaves, usually in Switzerland or Paris
or London. As so often happens with communities of exiled radicals, as we've seen going
all the way back to the post 1848 emigre waters that marks and angles and Bakunin swam in
these exile groups, continued to publish pamphlets and newspapers that focused as much on
prosecuting beefs and rivalries amongst themselves.
As the larger project of socialist revolution, everyone was pushing their own
idiosyncratic vision for the revolutionary future.
Even as that revolutionary future seemed further away than ever.
The most important of these groups came together in Paris, where one of the old deans of
Russian populism, Pyotr Lavrov, had moved after his time in Switzerland.
Lavrov, remember, had been an influential Neruda's theorist going all the way back before
the going to the people, and he was as old an old timer as they came in the mid 1890s.
He was enjoying something of a personal renaissance after the failure of people's will
style. Quick terrorism made Lavrov pitch for slow and steady education seemed much wiser
in retrospect. So in the early 1890s, Lavrov and a few other old exiled luminaries formed
their own group of veterans.
Now that conditions in Russia seem to be improving, they hope to form a kind of Neruda's
senior leadership in exile who could observe and direct their younger comrades who were
making good headway back home.
But though their voices were listened to and their service was respected, they suffered
from the same delusion that many emigrate groups abroad suffer in all times in places,
namely that while they consider themselves to be the leaders of the movement, the people
on the ground back home didn't know them and certainly weren't going to take orders from
them. The leaders in Russia saw themselves as the leaders, and they saw the emigres
serving merely as ambassadors and fundraisers, not as like the Central Committee of the
revolution. This disconnect is shown clearly in that one of the principal preoccupations
of those leaders inside Russia was how to get their own printing presses and newspapers
going because the literature being smuggled in from abroad was so thoroughly out of touch
and disconnected from realities in Russia, it was just all around unhelpful.
So the emigres are going to form the fourth group, the fourth pillar of what becomes the
Assads. And by the late 1890s, our future socialist revolutionaries are coming back to
life like buddying little schuetze after a long winter.
But as they came back to life, they would find themselves in direct competition with a
new species of revolutionary that they had not had to contend with back in the 1870s.
And that was Marxist Social Democrats.
And next week will be a very important episode in the Revolutions podcast, because we
will be introducing two of the most important members of the energetic younger generation
of Russian Marxists.
So join me next week when I finally introduce you to Lenin and Crips Ghayad.