This week's episode is brought to you by Audible Audible has the world's largest
selection of audio books and audio entertainment, including audible originals, stories
created exclusively for audible, including documentaries, exclusive audio books and
scripted shows that you just can't hear anywhere else.
automl keeps you informed, inspired and entertained with the convenient audible app.
You can listen anytime, anywhere and on any device mobile Alexa enabled Bluetooth and
more. You can listen at the gym while shopping in the car while travelling.
Anytime you can't read, you can just listen to audible.
Audible members also now get more than ever.
Every month you can choose one audio book regardless of the price, as well as to audible
originals. From a fresh selection, members stay motivated and inspired with unlimited
access to exclusive guided fitness and meditation programs.
And you can sign up for free updates from The New York Times, The Wall Street Journal and
The Washington Post, which will be delivered daily to the app.
Members also get to keep their library and listen forever, even if they cancel.
And though I think I have recommended this before this week, I am going to recommend
again The Count of Monte Cristo, which is a fantastic book because it does have a fun
little tie in to today's episode.
So if you want, go get the Count of Monte Cristo and you'll be following along with one
of our characters in today's show.
So start listening today with a 30 day audible trial.
Choose one audio book and two audible originals.
Absolutely free visit, audible dot com slash revolutions or text revolutions 2, 500, 500
that again visit Audible.com
a new D.I.D. B L E slash r e v o l U.T.
I O and S or text revolutions 2 5 0 0 5 0 0.
Hello and welcome to revolutions.
Episode. Ten point twenty two.
Vladimír and Najia.
So here we are at episode 22 into our series on the Russian Revolution, and I am just now
getting to the people who will be the main characters going forward and to the guy who
would probably be the main character if this wherever, say, adapted as a prestige
television show. Just throwing that out there.
But if you have friends who like to wait until I am done with the series before bingeing
at all at once. Be sure to tell them that we are at.
Episode 22 of the Russian Revolution.
And we have just gotten to the early life of Lenin.
So this new group of characters came from a generation who were too young to have been a
part of the radical upheavals of the 1870s.
They were just kids when Tsar Alexander the Second was assassinated.
They were in grammar school through the reactionary 1880s.
But by the time Tsar Nicholas the second ascended the throne in 1894, it was their turn
to be the young 20 something student radicals offended by the society within which they
had been raised and who were determined in the face of all of Russian history to be the
cohort that finally, finally pulled off a revolution.
And today we are going to introduce two of these up and coming revolutionaries who will,
in fact, in the future actually pull off the revolution.
Vladimir Elliot Liyana, known to history as Lenin, and his wife, now Déja Konstantin Nova
crimps Gaia. Vladimir Ilyich We on/off was born on April the 10th, 1870 in Cim Biersack,
a small provincial city on the Volga River.
The Ulyanovsk were an upwardly mobile family, not rich by any means, but fine specimens
of a respectable and prosperous provincial middle class.
Vladimir's paternal grandfather had been a serf who managed to transcend his status
sometime around eighteen hundred.
His son, Alia Ulanoff, Vladimir's father, had then received a good education and
graduated in 1854, joining the civil service as an inspector of schools, an energetic and
reform minded bureaucrat, Elliott Whouley.
Enough entered state service just as Tsar Alexander the Second was ascending the throne
and preparing his period of capital G.
Capital R. Great reform himself, only a generation removed from serfdom.
Will on/off was thrilled by almost everything those our liberator did.
The emancipation of the serfs was a work of profound, enlightened justice, and the
directives to create the zemser and improve local primary education gave his life purpose
settling in some biersack while John F.
traveled the region, setting up and monitoring new primary and grammar schools all
through the 1860s and 1870s, he was happy, fulfilled and respected.
Vladimir's mother, Maria Alexandrovna, came from a good family herself.
Her father was a doctor and her mother, a German, descended Protestant from the Balkans.
Now, given that Vladimir's paternal grandmother was probably of comic descent, the comic
where people who trace back to the Mongolians on the Volga.
Vladimir's ethnic ancestry told the demographic story of the Russian empire after his
death. This demographic story was given additional drama when one of Lenin sisters
discovered that their maternal great grandfather had actually been a Jew who converted to
orthodoxy and then raised his kids Christian.
When Stalin was presented with this revelation, he ordered the information suppressed.
Now, Lenin himself had no real anti-Semitic tendencies to speak of, and his sister
actually wanted to publicize this genealogical revelation to cut down on anti-Semitism in
Soviet Russia. But Stalin was an anti-Semite, so the information was suppressed.
But getting back to his mother, Maria Alexandrovna gave birth to eight babies, six of
whom lived of whom Vladimir was third oldest.
She held small C conservative vish bourgeois values, but insisted that her three boys and
three girls receive equal and equally rigorous educations.
She instilled in them a passion for learning and a competitive spirit to succeed.
And even though she never really understood her children's politics, she was not
surprised that they followed their mind in their hearts into radical revolutionary
action. And whatever happened in the future, she would always support her kids with money
and aid and the necessary begging of forgiveness from the authorities, which there would
be quite a lot of. So the elder Ulyanovsk had a conservative liberal disposition.
Their children really did not.
Young Vladimir was raised by both his parents to work hard, study hard and excel at
everything. And from an early age, he was blunt, sarcastic and arrogant.
But he could always back this up with high marks and superior ability.
A fellow student later said that Vladimir was esteemed, but he wasn't exactly liked.
And he had few real friends.
He was on the verge of his 11th birthday when the Tsar Liberator was assassinated on
March the 1st, 1881.
This was a shocking event that had his father weeping off and on for days.
The emotional blow of his revered tsar getting killed pave the way for professional
setbacks as the new reactionary regime of Tsar Alexander, the third preferred returning
primary education to the church.
So Dad's career of opening more modern secular schools stalled out and became far less
fulfilling. But he kept working as hard as he possibly could and probably working too
hard because his health began to fail him in his early 50s.
In January 1886, he went into his office one day, had a stroke and died.
Vladamir was just 15 years old.
I have yet to read a single biography of Lenin or even the briefest biographical sketch.
Come to think of it, that does not transition out of his father's death with a line like,
but his father's death was immediately followed by an even greater emotional blow.
And you know what? Why reinvent the wheel?
His father's death was immediately followed by an even greater emotional blow.
His older brother Alexander, known to all as Sasha, was the alpha of a brood of Lee
on/off children who were something resembling a little band of prodigies.
A deadly serious student, Sasha always got top marks, was head of his class, and went off
to university in St.
Petersburg, pursuing a degree in the natural sciences.
All his professors agreed they were witnessing the beginning of a brilliant career.
Now, as academic focus was on the biology of worms, but kind of out of nowhere, his real
passion suddenly became radical politics.
Now this is 1886.
And remember, the old people's will network has been broken and the radical
revolutionaries are at their nadir.
So Sasha's move into radicalism was self-directed and pretty self organized.
It was really just him and some friends.
And though they would adopt the name people's will for their group, they had nothing
whatsoever to do with the original people's well.
Their tactics, however, did follow the original group's line.
Sasha and his friends wanted a mass mobilized Socialist Party operating out in the open.
But that was simply not possible under the reactionary repression of the current regime.
Without the opportunity to voice their opinions or even put to work their elite
educations on behalf of the country they loved.
They had no choice but to attack the regime until it either collapsed or allowed for
political freedom. So they followed in the spiritual footsteps of the original people's
will. They formed a small cell of revolutionary comrades and concocted a terrorist plot
to kill the Tsar. Sasha sold the watch he had won as an academic prize and used the money
to buy components and supplies to make bombs to blow up the Tsar.
Now, usually in these days, a half baked plot like this would be uncovered early by the
Irana or just as often the would be assassins would find the job too hard or too risky.
But Sosha followed through.
He succeeded in acquiring the supplies and building the bombs, and he and his fellow
conspirators plan to use them.
On March the 1st, 1887, the sixth anniversary of the assassination of this our liberator.
But it did not work out, though, the assassins were ready.
The tsar did not appear where they thought he was going to appear.
Then one of them was picked up on an unrelated charge of being suspicious in public.
And it wasn't until he was in custody that the police realized he was carrying a bomb.
The guy confessed to everything.
And the other 14 conspirators who were in on this plot were picked up, including Sasha,
who then proceeded to nobly attempt to take responsibility for everything, saying it was
all his idea and all his work.
Back home in some Biersack, the family was shocked at how far and how fast Sosha had
gotten mixed up in such big trouble.
His mother did everything she could to try to get him released or merely exiled or given
some other reduced sentence.
But this isn't like he had been found with banned books or busted, leading a seditious
discussion circle.
By Sasha's own admission, he was a bomb maker who was making bombs to kill the tsar.
This is real life stuff.
So 10 of his fellow accomplices were ultimately sentenced to terms of prison or exile.
But Sasha and four others were sentenced to be hanged.
And right to the very end, his mother thought those hour would commute the sentence.
Now that the boys had had the fear of God and death put in them.
But clemency never came.
On May the 8th, 1887, Alexander well, John off and four of his friends were hanged.
The execution of Sasha was a shock to the Ulyanovsk and their neighbors, though he and
his younger brother Vladimir were very different people and were never exactly friends.
Vladimir had always looked up to to the point of a worshipped his older brother.
Everyone in the family had.
And though he almost never spoke about any of this in the future.
It left Latimer hostile and embittered towards the state that had murdered his brother.
In his mind, soshe is only real crime had been bravely standing up to an evil regime.
So who knows how much of his life and career was personal.
Adding to this resentful bitterness was that after the scandal broke in town, the
respectable and polite families in Bierce iced the Ulyanovsk out.
They stopped coming around, they stopped inviting the family to parties or including them
in anything but whispered gossip behind their backs.
The social treatment was so bad that his only recently widowed mother sold the family
house and they all moved out of town for good.
And it has been remarked on more than one occasion that this treatment may have played a
role in Vladimir's future.
Deep, deep hatred of hypocritical bourgeois liberals, treacherous, two faced bastards who
cannot ever be trusted.
That was his consistent and unshakable belief.
Now, perhaps this reads too much into it.
But then again, deep seated beliefs do have to come from somewhere.
Now, we cannot go on before mentioning the story that Lennon's sister Maria told after
Lennon's death. She said that upon hearing the news of Sasha's execution, that Vladamir
shook his head and said, no, we will go another way, Sasha.
Which then became something of a colloquial aphorism in Soviet Russia.
Now the story itself is for sure.
A later invention, Maria was only nine.
Vladimir was a teenager who had never yet showed any interest in politics.
But while the story and the quote were an invention, it did capture a basic truth.
Lenin would always have a healthy disdain for the kind of elite people's will terrorism
that Sasha had attempted, and in the attempt proved once again how inadequate a strategy
it was. And though he wouldn't necessarily turn his nose up at plots to assassinate
Czarist officials, the future Lenin would never think it was the main work of revolution.
One lesson Vladimír or any of his siblings did not take away from the execution of their
brother was to stay out of politics.
When Vladimír arrived at the University of Cars on in the fall of 1887, he immediately
joined student activist groups and took part in demonstrations, one of which was so big
that more than 150 kids were arrested.
But even though he was not a leader of this demonstration, Vladimír was one of the few to
be expelled for his involvement because holy hell, this guy's early and often he's the
brother of that guy we just hanged for trying to kill.
Those are now kicked out of school.
Vladimir was ordered to confine himself to a country estate owned by his extended family,
where he wound up spending almost the entirety of 1888.
And he spent this time enforced idleness, reading and reading and reading some more.
And it was during this period that he finally came across what is to be done by a
Chayefsky? Vladimir loved what is to be done.
He loved it so much. He read it six times over the summer, and he was enthralled by the
main ultra dedicated revolutionary character, the same character who had once inspired me
life. So Vladimir loved what is to be done.
He loved it so much that in the future he literally carried a small picture of Turness
Chayefsky with him in his wallet, a claim that could not be made by Marx or Engels or
even his wife. And in a very real way, it was Turness Chayefsky more than Marx who turned
Vladimir into Lenin.
But that is not to say he did not also fall in love with marks and angles.
He did. In fact, he does it right now.
His mother managed to get the de facto house arrest lifted and the family moved back to
cars on. And though Vladimir was not allowed to return to university, he continued to
educate himself, though he was assisted by local radical discussion groups that he
continued to slip in and out of.
So in 1889, he got his hands on his first copy of Capital and the Communist Manifesto and
Simple on/off, which he read and which thrilled him from this point on.
He's a full throated Marxist.
Now we will obviously have plenty of time to talk all about Lennon's understanding of
Marxism in theory and in practice.
But suffice it to say that he believed what he was reading gave him a historical
blueprint for a great heroic struggle that would inevitably see the people triumph over
evil despotism.
Now, understandably, his mother was not too keen on the direction he was headed, and she
purchased a country estate, partly in the hopes of turning her son into a productive
landed farmer. But Vladimir did not take to farming and farming did not take to Vladimir.
So instead he managed to get permission to take law exams, even though he was not a
graduate of any university.
And after a year of intensive, self-directed study, he aced the exam in the spring of
1891 with top marks.
Doing on his own in 12 months what it usually took a student about four years of law
school to accomplish.
Say what you want about Lenin.
He was not done.
But this small triumph was knocked down by another tragedy.
His sister Olga, the sibling with whom Vladimir was closest and who I've read was
considered the real genius of the family, which is saying something slowly succumb to
typhoid. Vladimir lived with her at this point and nursed her, but to no avail, and she
died in May of 1891, practically in his arms.
He was devastated. Shortly after passing the law exams and burying his sister came the
great famine of 1891 to 1892.
And here there are conflicting accounts about Vladimir's attitude.
All of these attitudes were reported much later.
And all of them were meant to either attack or defend him.
If you hate Lenin, the story is that he openly opposed relief efforts for the peasants.
But he insisted the famine was a progressive historical force that would help destroy the
archaic villages and drive the rural peasantry into the cities where they would grow the
ranks of his beloved urban proletariat.
This version has Lenin glorying and human suffering in order to have his way.
Now, if you like Lenin, you say all of that is made up and it doesn't actually fit with
his beliefs or his actions.
Because during these same years he would be arguing in debates that any social democratic
party worth its salt must address the daily miseries of the people they were trying to
convert. And it feels off that he would say we should oppose something like famine
relief. Now both sides can point to Lennon's later conduct, both cruel or compassionate.
That backs up their version of the Lenin opposed famine relief story.
Now, do I think it's at least plausible that he saw the failed relief and mass suffering
as politically advantageous?
Sure, because it was.
In 1893, Vladimír finally moved to the big city for good.
He arrived in St. Petersburg in August, got hooked up with a not too difficult associate
lawyer's position that allowed him to spend most of his time around the small but growing
Marxist reading circles.
And in these circles, he quickly earned a reputation for a ruthless debating style,
withering, surgical, sarcastic, a cerebral, blunt and supremely self-confident.
He did not believe the debate was for persuading your opponent.
It was for demolishing your opponent.
Then whether they liked him or hated him, the people in these radical circles started
noticing this guy, Vladimir Ilyich.
This new guy who had just shown up, and one of those who heard of his growing reputation
was a young woman who was already established inside these St.
Petersburg Marxist circles.
Nadia Creep's Gaia.
Now, Des constantly Nova Cripps Gaia was born in St.
Petersburg on February the 14th, 1869, so she was just about a year older than her future
husband. Her family had also been pretty respectable and upwardly mobile, at least at the
time of her birth. Her father Constantine was the orphan's son of landless nobles whose
upbringing had been underwritten by the state.
And so he got funneled into the Army Officer Corps.
In 1863, Constantine was shipped off to help suppress a revolt in Poland that saw him
both perform well and probably emerge with some sympathy for the Poles.
But the serving well part was more important, and he was transferred off to study law in
St. Petersburg, where he met his wife vet to the ceiling of that.
She, too, had been the orphaned daughter of respectable nobility and had gotten a good
education that qualified her to serve as a governess, which is what she was doing for the
ten years before she met Constantine.
And though she would always be a devoutly Orthodox wife and mother, she had little good
to say about the kind of noble family she had lived among.
Certainly she passed on to her young daughter.
A love of hard work and education and a hatred of the casual cruelty of the idle rich.
Graduating with his law degree, Constantine was then shipped back to Warsaw with his wife
and new baby little Najia, to serve in the imperial administration in Poland.
And during his tenure in Warsaw, he operated with something of an enlightened hand.
He helped open a hospital, protect Jews from persecution and lay down rules that
regulated labor practices.
His wife Elizaveta, meanwhile, similarly engaged with the local culture, and she even
wrote a successful children's book in Polish.
All of which seems to have coffee, wary eye of somebody higher up in the bureaucratic
chain of command. Or more likely, the eye of somebody who was complaining about the labor
regulations. Because in 1874, Constantine was brought before an imperial assessor and
officially reprimanded for exceeding his authority.
He appealed the decision, but this appeal took time.
And in that time, his career in the civil service was totally derailed.
So while ages zero to five for a little nÁdya, we're stable and happy.
Ages 5 to 10 were disjointed, difficult and lonely as the family followed her
increasingly bitter and discouraged father from job to job.
Unable to find a place to settle down, all the while nursing a grudge against the state
that had wronged him. Probably during these troubled years of the mid 1870s, Constantine
developed friendly relations with people who were at least adjacent to the radicals and
people as well. Though he never did wind up on anybody's watch list.
As the family moved around chasing jobs, Najia became a lonely bookworm, but she was
first brought out of her growing show in the summer of 1880 when she came into contact
with an energetic and idealistic young teacher.
The eleven year old Nadia latched onto this teacher and was allowed to hang out and sit
in on classes that were above her level.
And it was this teacher who first introduced Nadia to the poet Nikolai across off an
enormously influential and beloved Russian writer who had died just a few years earlier.
Cross off. Did for Nadia what turned a Chesky had done for Lenin.
It was a passion, stirring moment of contact with something special and magical.
And right up until her death, it was no cross off who held pride of place in kripp Skye's
heart. And when she penned her own first political polemic, she opened it with one of his
lines. Vij locked his heart.
A woman's lot, a harder lot can scarce be found.
But knottiest summer in poetic bliss soon ended, the family moved onto St.
Petersburg and shortly thereafter she learned that this beloved teacher had been arrested
for owning subversive literature.
And I have no idea what happened to her.
After arriving in St. Petersburg, though, Nadia found another place to flourish.
The other Lonski gymnasium was a progressive school run by reformist liberals with deep
pocketed patrons with something resembling a permanent home after five years of itinerant
wandering. Not you made friends and started getting pretty good grades.
And it was during this period that she herself read Shawna Chayefsky.
Though it never hit her as hard as some of her contemporaries, including, of course, her
future husband. Her father's health had deteriorated under the strain of his
circumstances, though, and while he eventually did win his appeal after six years
persistent effort, it turns out he was wrongly disciplined.
It was too late to save his career and it was too late to save him.
He contracted tuberculosis and after a long period of wasting away, finally died in 1883
at the age of just 45.
Nadia and her mother were left alone and I hate to keep calling back to Lenin but Nadia
would never forgive the state for humiliating slandering and driving her father to ruin
and then to death. So this is all personal for her to the immediate circumstances for
mother and daughter were not terrible though it Lucy that was always able to get steady
work as a teacher and Nadia herself now picked up money tutoring and they live in a
respectable three room apartment solidly in sparsely.
Middle class eludes you about the continued to instill in her daughter a love of
education and a sense of social obligation to help and improve those around her
especially by passing her education along to others so eventually this mentality is going
to take her towards radical Marxist politics.
But Nadia Cribbs guy up took a bit of a detour through Tolstoy's and narco Christianity.
Now unfortunately we do not have the time nor do I have anything like a firm grasp on
Tolstoy's and Argo Christianity to delve too deep into this but luckily neither did
Nadia. She had no use for Tolstoy's evangelical beliefs his views on women or his disdain
for science. But she did like a lot of his other beliefs most especially his thoughts on
education which stressed spontaneity and curiosity and emotional connection over rigid
memorization and harsh disciplined.
Nadia admired Tolstoy enough that she wrote him what amounts to a fan letter and briefly
participated as a proofreader in a program that Tolstoy spearheaded to publish cheap
editions of great books and she edited an edition of The Count of Monte Cristo.
The possibility of using progressive education to improve the masses was alluring.
And by the time Nadia was 20.
It was poetry and literature and teaching gave direction to her ambitions about how she
could have an impact on the world once she graduated from gymnasium now.
Nadia arrived at her own famous conversion to Marx as a moment and every great Soviet
biography has to have a great conversion to Marx as a moment for Nadia.
This came in 1890 at the age of 21.
She joined a small radical discussion circle and after reading and delivering a report on
Lavrov historical letters she asked about these guys Marx and Engels she had been hearing
about and was given a small bundle of books to read.
Ironically though this bundle was selected by a comrade who happened to be into new road
ism and who hoped to prove to Nadia that Marx was full of beans.
So along with capital she got a critique of Marxism by an a rightist ideologue and a few
other books and even after the revolution Nadia admitted that reading the first two
chapters of Marx's Capital was like reading Greek and she had no background in economics
or philosophy or political science.
But she kept reading and got to the parts that talked about the conditions that the
workers had to endure and that did grab her and by the time she was done she believed
that Marx had effectively laid out an analysis of what was wrong with the world.
What could be done about it and most especially who was to blame.
And it was capitalism.
And in Russia the Tsar and in a straightforward way.
Nadia Cribbs Gaia accepted that they were the enemy and that she needed to spend her life
fighting them on a more practical level in 1891 she found her calling working as a night
school teacher in the very poor working class districts of St.
Petersburg teaching anything from basic literacy to math history literature and
geography. She loved the work and in 1893 she was elected director of the program by her
fellow teachers not given the nature of this work it should come as no surprise that most
of the faculty and administrators were reformist liberals.
A few of them were narrowest populists and a handful like Nadia were Marxists.
Now they could not use the classroom to organize politically but lessons could be steered
in certain directions.
And if a particular worker was interested in learning more than names and addresses could
be surreptitiously passed along Nadia's own education continued through this period as
she both had to learn additional materials to teach her students.
But she also learned from her students what their life was like who they were what their
problems were and it gave her invaluable insight and judgment insight that many of her
bourgeois radical comrades never quite grasped.
As many of them remain the kind of coffee house radicals who never met the people they
supposedly idolized and were fighting for now.
By this point Nadia and a few of her friends had moved into a Reading Circle headed by an
old in the protest turned Marxist name.
Step on red Janko and it was in this group that she first heard about this character
Vladimir. Ilya Juliano half brother of a hanged martyr who was bulldozing his way through
the radical debate circuit and then it was in this wrenching co group that they met for
the first time in February 1894 and it could not have been a more classic meet cute.
He read from passages from a book he was writing called what the friends of the people
are and how they fight the Social Democrats which was an anti-war protest track that
would be the first book published under the pen name Lenin.
No not yet that this was all fine.
But then after the reading he made a sarcastic jab about the value of teaching the
workers literature which was clearly a pointless fool's errand and which happened to be
her great passion in life.
So as we know from every romantic comedy ever written this awkward moment of initial off
putting behavior was only ever going to result in wedding bells but the wedding was still
a while off yet for the next few years Nadia and Vladimir would be merely comrades.
At this stage not fighting a war against the Tsar so much as against other radicals who
were trying to pitch the wrong brand of revolution and so next week we will pick back up
with them as they hook up with another key player in the fight against revolutionary
Philistines Julius Martin.