This week's episode is brought to you, by a way away, it was founded by two friends from
New York who found themselves at JFK with dead phones, delayed flights and a bright idea
luggage with power.
Thus the away carry-on was born.
The approach is simply to create special objects that are designed to be resilient,
resourceful and essential to the way you travel today.
They asked thousands of people how they pack, why they travel, and what bugs them most
about their luggage. And then a way designed a bag to solve a few old problems like
sticky wheels and a few new ones like dead cell phones.
With the way you get to choose from a variety of sizes and colors, there's the carry-on,
the bigger carry-on, the medium or the large, and both sizes of the carry-on are able to
charge all cell phones, tablets, e-readers or anything else that's powered by a U.S.
be called a single charge from an away carry on will charge your iPhone 5 times.
All suitcases are also made from premium German polycarbonate unrivaled and strengthen
impact resistance and also very lightweight.
The interior features a patent pending compression system which is helpful for over
packers'. It has four 360 degree spinner wheels which guarantee a smooth ride and a TSA
approved combination lock is built into the top of the bag to prevent theft.
The away bag also comes with a lifetime warranty if anything breaks.
They will fix it or replace it for life.
And then there is the 100 day trial because you can live with it.
You can work with it. You can travel with it.
And if at any point you decide it's not for you, you can return it for a full refund with
no questions asked.
Our away travel back continues to be great for our world travels.
Lightweight design makes it easy to maneuver around sidewalks on and off the metro and
trains in and out of planes.
Then, on more than one occasion, the u_s_b_ power source has saved me from a dying cell
phone. So for $20 off a suitcase, visit a way, travel dot com slash revolutions 20 and
use the promo code revolutions 20 during checkout that again for $20 off a suitcase.
Visit a way travel dot com slash revolutions 20.
That is 20. The numeral 20 and use the promo code revolutions twenty.
Hello and welcome to revolutions.
Episode ten point three, The Three Pillars of Marxism.
Before we get going this week, I want to thank everyone who came out to Waterstones last
Tuesday night. It was fantastic.
I had a great time. Hope you did, too.
And then I want to remind everybody that I will be flying to New York in a couple of
weeks to take part in a really cool event called Intelligent Speech, which is bringing
together a lot of podcasters and specifically history podcasters to talk about what we
do, why we do it, and maybe how you can do it, too.
This is all happening at the Center for Social Innovation in Chelsea on Saturday, June
the twenty eighth. Twenty nineteen.
The details are an intelligent speech conference dot com and I put a link to it in the
show notes and I hope to see you there because I'll be there all day talking about what I
do and why I do it, and how maybe you can do it too.
But getting back to the show last time we talked through the lives of marks and angles.
Long story short, they were would be revolutionaries whose revolution came and then went
and then deposited them in exile in England.
Marx lived in London, writing articles and continuing his study of political economy.
Engels lived in Manchester working for the family business.
Ostensibly, he had given up his radical ways, but he, too, continued to research and
write. Marx and Engels maintained an almost daily correspondence where they further
discussed and elaborated the basic ideas.
They had come up with me 1840's and their work.
In the 1850s and 1860s and then into the 1870s was about fully developing and proving
those ideas, ideas that coalesced into the philosophic, economic and political system
that is today known as Marxism.
Today we are going to talk through some of Marxism and it will almost certainly wind up
being an inadequate introduction.
But we have to start somewhere.
Now, since we are moving towards the Russian Revolution, I thought I might start by
borrowing an idea that Lenin promoted to frame our discussion of a few of the more
important Marxian ideas.
Lenin says that Marx, quote, was the genius who continued and consummated the three main
ideological currents of the 19th century, as represented by the three most advanced
countries of mankind.
Classical German philosophy, classical English, political economy and French socialism,
combined with French revolutionary doctrines in general.
And quote. So we might call these the three pillars of Marxism, German philosophy,
specifically the German philosophy operating in the aftermath of Hegel, English economics
and the classically liberal tradition, though really it's British economics because the
Scot Adam Smith looms so large, though Marx is most often grappling directly with David
Ricardo. And then finally, French utopian socialism Saltzman and focaccia who were dead
by the time Marx was encountering them in the early 1840s.
But also put on and Louis Baum, who were very much alive and working.
And the thing here is that Marx being Marx, he was not going to build his own philosophy
by simply taking what he had found and then continuing to build in the same direction as
his predecessors. Instead, he would challenge, critique and attack them.
They were the thesis. He was the antithesis.
Marxism was the synthesis.
So first we have the German philosophy component, which, as you know from last week was
Marx's first passion.
He was for sure aiming to become a professor of philosophy until the ideas he embraced
and the friends that he kept.
Made him toxic to the German universities, as we also talked about last week.
Young Marx, like every philosophy student in Germany at the time, was working in the
shadow of Hagel.
But specifically, Marx was working in one part of the shadow amongst the young Hegg
aliens who were rejecting many of the conclusions that had been reached by the great old
man. The biggest conclusion Hagel had reached that Marx thought wrong became the most
basic component of Marxist philosophy.
Hagel was an idealist and Marx was a materialist.
Idealism here does not refer to a belief in lofty morals and ideals, but rather the
philosophic position that what we encounter as existence is not actually a world of
things, but a world of ideas.
Everything comes down to ideas and the ideas we have about those ideas.
The material world, if such a thing even exists, is entirely secondary for an idealist
like Hagel. The mind and objects of the mind are the central subjects, not just a
philosophy, but of existence itself.
That what the thinking mind thinks is real life is really just a manifested projection of
some ideas held by the thinking mind.
But a branch of the young heart galleons started to turn this upside down to say, no,
wait a minute. The material world is really primary and all of our ideas about it are
secondary. They come as sense impressions or reflections on those sent impressions.
Even ideas themselves are the product of matter, acting upon matter in the neurochemistry
of the physical brain. It's all physical, it's all material substance.
They believed in this and travesty of the material world and marks from a very young age
was a confirmed materialist, and it became the great building block upon which he piled a
bunch of other building blocks.
But though he was starting from the opposite conclusion about the very nature of reality
by his own forthright acknowledgment, Marx drew very useful structures and tools and
vocabulary from Hegel, even if ultimately Marx thought Hegel had everything stood on its
head. For example, we have dialectics.
You have probably encountered dialectics at some point, even if you don't know it.
It's an adversarial system of progressive reasoning that passes through three stages,
usually described as thesis, antithesis and synthesis.
It's the formula I use just a minute ago to foreshadow where we were headed.
First, a thesis is presented.
Then comes the antithesis that would seem to negate that thesis.
And then the tension is resolved by a conclusion.
The synthesis, which is the transcended union of the apparent opposites.
Keeping the good shaking loose the bad.
It's a dynamic form of construction, deconstruction and reconstruction.
Now, a few necessary caveats about this.
This dialectical form of reasoning and investigation goes way back to the beginning of
recorded history and enjoyed wide use in both ancient and medieval philosophy.
So dialectical reasoning is not some brand new thing that was invented by Hegel.
The second Hegel himself, nor Marx for that matter, really ever use the terms, thesis,
antithesis and synthesis.
That's just the way we conceive of it today.
And then finally, we must say that Hegel did not think dialectics needed to be
universally applied in rigidly dogmatic ways.
And in fact, he derided those who wanted to rely on mechanical formulas to answer every
problem. But still dialectical reasoning was imported from Hegel to Marx and from Marx
into Marxism. This re innovation and dialectical reasoning was exciting too early 19th
century German philosophers because it seemed unnecessary antidote to what had built up
during the Renaissance and the Enlightenment and the scientific revolution.
When philosophers started relying on different methods of investigation and
experimentation, these new methods isolated and examined individual variables to
understand all the different little bits that made things what they are.
They collected, separated and analyzed.
They arrange things into orders, classified them into complex schemes, and then took the
component parts of the component parts and further isolated and documented those.
Everything was put in a specimen jar and labeled.
This was done not just for things in the material world, but also for ideas and concepts.
They divided them up. Yes and no.
True and false.
Positive and negative cause and effect.
But they struggled because sometimes a thing is not just one thing at a time.
It was many different things and often apparently contradictory things.
Causes were effects.
Effects were causes.
They couldn't be stuck permanently in two separate specimen jars because they were
infused with the essence of many different things.
Then those who supported dialectical reasoning said these metaphysician is made the
further mistake of trying to get everything to stop moving so that properties and things
and ideas could be described once and for all in their rigid, fixed and internal ways.
But nothing is ever rigid, fixed and eternal.
The universe and everything in it is in constant motion.
It's forever changing, evolving, interacting, appearing and passing away.
Grappling with a constantly changing, constantly in motion universe is not a problem for
dialectics, nor was it concerned about the myriad and troublesome contradictions.
In fact, it positively thrived on those contradictions.
Dialectic say yes.
Not only are these things opposite and contradictory, but their opposition brings them
into union. The apparent contradictions are needed to advance, develop, evolve and change
to take this simple and make it complex.
And so we as humans need to understand the dynamic, dialectical process of unfolding
transformative conflict between opposites as the path to understanding the true nature of
existence. Marks then took his materialism and these dialectics and combined them with
another of haggles, big ideas, and then really ran with it, that the confrontations and
conflict between apparently contradictory forces was the driver, not just a philosophical
advancement, but of human history.
So now we have the foundational concepts that allowed Marx to develop the core philosophy
that underlay all of his future research and political activism, dialectical materialism.
Shut out of the ivory tower and forced into the grubby world of being a political
journalist and activist.
Marx took his materialism and these dialectical patterns of reasoning and applied them to
the grubby world within which humans actually lived.
And in so doing, he started having epiphany after epiphany.
First, thanks to his understanding of flux and change, but and passing away, he advanced
beyond the materialism of guys like Newton, who were always trying to fix and pin down
immutable laws for eternal bodies.
Marx's materialism, on the other hand, embraced flux and growth and change.
Birth and death and evolution.
Going to spend a whole episode on this next week.
But Marx believed he had cracked the secret of history that the underlying economic
structure of society.
The means by which humans produce the necessities of life defined everything else.
And that you could not understand the world, and certainly not changed the world unless
you understood how the material economic substructure operated and how conflicts within
it were the fundamental drivers of history.
So armed with these concepts from German philosophy, when Marx arrived in Paris in 1843,
he was ready to start a thoroughgoing investigation of European political economy to
understand that economic substructure.
This is a project that would remain ongoing for the rest of his life until his death in
1883 when he was doing his work in political economy.
Marx was grappling with correcting and expanding the work of the classical liberal
economists Adam Smith and Smith's disciple David Ricardo, as well as contemporaries like
John Stuart Mill.
And though in the modern popular imagination, Adam Smith and Karl Marx are considered
polar opposites, never the two shall meet.
But Marx, for one, did not think of himself as the enemy of Adam Smith.
And most of Marxian economics is working in the tradition of Smith and Ricardo, even if,
as in all things, Marx was aggressively critical of everyone who came before him.
So this transitions us from Marx, the philosopher to Marx, the economist from the German
philosophy pillar to the English economics pillar, as Marx attempted to understand the
material substructure of civilization.
And when you read Marx The Economist, you get hit with a lot of jargony concepts, most of
which sound indistinguishable from some of his other jargony concepts.
Mode of production factor of production means of production, means of labor, subject of
labor, instruments of labor.
How is one to tell all of these things of production and things of labor apart?
Well, Marx himself is never 100 percent consistent in his usage of these terms, but they
can be arranged into what I like to call the Tree of Labors and productions.
And it's important to pick through this mostly.
So you have a clear idea of what Marx means by the umbrella concept mode of production,
which is very important to his historical materialism, and that's very important to the
Russian Revolution. So as the fit Marxian analysis, we will start at the bottom and move
our way to the top and we shall begin with the marriage of the instruments of labor and
the subjects of labor, the instruments of labor are just what you think they might be,
the tools of labor in the ordinary sense, hammers, lathes, needles, just the ordinary
tools that one might need to produce some product.
And in the larger sense, this also include infrastructure and factories.
But those instruments are used on what correct?
They are used on the subject of labor, which you would consider the natural resources or
raw materials, wood, metals, textiles, the stuff a product is made out of.
And if you take the instruments of labor and you use them on the subjects of labor, you
can make a thing. You can produce a product.
And then if you take those two concepts, the instruments of labor plus the subjects of
labor and put them in a box together, you would label that box.
The means of production and spoiler alert.
Who owns the means of production is a very, very, very important question to answer.
But OK. The means of production is just a combination of the instruments of labor and the
subjects of labor. But it does not include the labor.
The means of production are inanimate and are not productive in and of themselves.
You need animate energy provided by a human being to produce the product.
And when you combine those inanimate means of production with the animate human labor,
you get the concept of forces of production or productive forces or sometimes factors of
production. So again, this combined mix of the tools to do the work.
The raw materials, the work will be done on and the workers who will be doing the work
are the forces of production.
We can now really produce a product.
So far, so good. But this does not get us all the way to the top of the Tree of Labors
and productions to get to the top.
We need to combine those forces of production with something called the relations of
production, which can be described and I'm quoting here as the sum total of social
relations that people must enter into in order to survive, to produce and to reproduce
the means of their life.
Now, the relations up production are very important because they don't just include
things like the division of labor in a factory or how a corporation's org chart is drawn
up. It includes the totality of the social relations that swirl around the forces of
production. Some of these relations are entered into voluntarily.
Some of them are compelled and involuntary.
They involve hierarchical relations, political relations, family relations, social and
economic class.
Basically, all the myriad ways humans come to relate to one another.
To employ the forces of production.
To produce the means of their subsistence and then distribute it to the members of
society. No, Marx and Engels themselves mostly deployed this term in service to their
political and economic analysis.
Who owned what specifically the means of production?
What the law said about who owned what?
Who controlled who?
Who was the boss? What were the social classes?
Where was their cooperation?
Where was their competition?
Where was their conflict?
Their totality of all these relations of production constituted a society social
structure. And it was the part that determine how income and products and assets would be
distributed. And according to Marx, this was all ultimately rooted in servicing the
forces of production.
Whatever those happen to be.
But to take a step back for one minute, beyond the economic and political implications,
the analysis of the relations of production was a fairly profound and novel idea, and it
opened up vast exploratory possibilities and made Marx one of the founders of a whole new
field of social science called sociology.
But getting back to it, when you combine the relations up, production with the forces of
production, which remember are just the tools, material subjects and labor of a society's
economic production. We have basically a total description of how society organizes
itself to produce and distribute the means of its subsistence, which is, after all, the
point of all this. Marx called this final concept the mode of production, and it's very
important because there have only been a few modes of production in human history and
we're gonna discuss that at length next week.
But there's the primitive mode, the ancient mode, the feudal mode and the capitalist
mode. The point of Marx's politics was to advance society from the prevailing capitalist
mode of production to a new socialist mode of production.
That is the great historical work to be done.
So how does Mark start coming around to that idea?
Well, as a young man, he really started taking stock of the world he was living in and he
felt that something was very wrong and off about it.
And this is where the third pillar of Marxism comes into the picture, because he started
being introduced to French socialism in studying revolutionary French ideas, because the
French socialists were also very critical of modern society.
And they had developed this social question and we're trying to provide answers for it.
But given his dialectical materialism, Marx was none too impressed with the life of the
mind utopian socialists who were trying to established fixed and eternal laws of justice
and retreating to pure reason to solve all the world's problems.
When really what they needed to be doing is studying history, economics and politics.
How are you going to answer the social question if you don't understand the question?
So Marx took these three pillars, German philosophy and English economics and French
social theory and started to try to build his own answer to the social question.
It was obvious that the capitalist mode of production had serious flaws that needed to be
addressed. But how to address them?
What even needed to be addressed?
What made this new era of modern economics different from previous periods of history?
Now we're going to talk more about this next week.
But clearly, the profit motive as the central organizing principle of economic life was a
defining feature of the new capitalist mode of production.
The idea that the point was not just to produce the necessities of life, but to produce
commodities that can be sold at a higher price than it took to produce them, and then
have this profit seeking commodity exchange not just confined to small local town
markets, but to envelop every aspect of social and economic life.
This led Marx to ask, well, where does profit even come from?
And to answer this question, Marx developed the labor theory of value, which basically
says that the root source of value and thus profit is labor.
Labor is the magical ingredient, which allows one to purchase a bunch of inanimate
instruments of labor and subjects of labor and then later sell the product that those
instruments of labor had turned the subjects of labor into for a higher price for a
profit. And Mark says even more specifically and emphatically that this is a process of
exploitation. Basically, he sees things going like this, at least theoretically, the cost
of securing one day's labor from a worker must at least be equal to the costs necessary
to keep that worker alive for one day.
The food, drink and shelter and clothes, you gotta keep the worker alive.
But let's say you bring a bunch of laborers together to make some shoes.
And let's say that after four hours on the clock, the workers have used the instruments
of labor on the subjects of labor to produce enough shoes that, when sold, will generate
the revenue necessary to supply the workers with the means of that daily subsistence.
This will come to them in the form of wages, but you're not going to blow the whistle and
call it a day after four hours.
No, you're only at the break even point.
This is the capitalist mode of production and you want profit.
So you're gonna keep working them for another four hours, maybe another eight hours,
maybe since this is the 1860s and there are literally no regulations about this stuff.
Another 12 hours and all the shoes produced after those initial first four hours.
This is surplus labor creating surplus value and that is where profit comes from and the
profit goes to the capitalist owner.
Now, granted, that capitalist donor has lots of costs beyond just labor, but according to
the labor theory of value, the source of profit is the exploitation of surplus labor
paying less for the labor than the labor was ultimately worth.
And in Marx's estimation, this exploitation is terrible from a social and humanitarian
perspective. Now it gets really interesting because Marx has this further insight based
off of a reading of John Locke style theories of property that were so central to the
founding of modern liberal economic and political theory.
According to this theory, something becomes your property when you infuse it with your
labor, whether it is literally a craft that you made it some home workshop or a field
that you ploughed. If you worked on it, built it, improved it, shaped it, it became your
property. This is how the abundance of things out in the state of nature can plausibly
and morally and legally be recognized as personal property.
And to take just a recent example from the Revolutions podcast.
At the end of the Mexican Revolution, one of the ways land could be nationalized under
Article 27 of the New Mexican Constitution was if you weren't doing anything with it.
If it was just sitting there, quote unquote, unimproved or quote unquote unproductive.
This is Locky and theories of property at work.
You can't own something if it's just sitting there and you're not doing anything with it.
Well, what Mark saw in capitalism was a contradiction, a bastardization of this
principle, because under old modes of ancient and fuel production, the individual artisan
would take raw materials.
The subject of labor used his tools, which are the instruments of labor, and apply his
individual labor to take those raw materials to a finished product.
In this sense, it was his or her personal property, and not even a Marxist has a problem
with that kind of personal property.
The problem is that in capitalism, many people are being brought together.
They are doing individual little parts of the total and necessary labor, but not every
part. The division of labor inside a factory means that no one person can point to the
finished shoe and say That's mine.
I made it. It is in every way the product of group effort, social labor.
And this includes not just the blue collar workers, but white collar employees in the
marketing department and sales department, accounting, human resources.
But the profits don't come back to these workers.
They are instead held by the owner who claim these profits as his or her individual
property by. Right.
Not because he helped make the shoe or sell the shoe, but because he owned the means of
production. He owned the tools and the raw materials and the factory.
And thus anything that was produced by those tools and factories.
So Mark Soor is the owner still claiming the right of Locky and ownership, even though
the capitalist mode of production had really moved beyond the very thing that made
Lockean ownership comprehensible.
That individual labor created individual property, the capitalist system had replaced
that individual labor with social labor, but the ownership in the property in the profit
still remained individualized.
And this really chapped Marx's hide.
Now, is any of this true?
Is this really how it works?
Is this the final word on how value and profits are created in the marketplace?
Did Marx have everything correct about the relation between labor and profit?
Is this really how the capitalist system works?
The answer is kind of yes.
And kind of no. I am not an economist.
My habits and mindset are of course, focused on political history.
But I know enough to know that a strict interpretation of the labor theory of value would
not just be a controversial position to take, but probably an incorrect position to take
because there's a lot more going on.
Even those working inside a Marxist tradition who are sympathetic to Marxist theories and
want to salvage them as best they can have over the past hundred and fifty years, refined
and updated his ideas, as you would expect.
And as I expect Marx would expect, given that everyone now has one hundred and fifty more
years of data to work from.
But there is definitely still some element of truth to all this.
The point, though, is that politically, these are incredibly powerful ideas.
The pitch here is that you're fat capitalist owner is literally on purpose and by
necessity exploiting you, the worker that the capitalist makes you endure horrible
conditions while you provide all the essential labor, which is remember the only thing
that gives a commodity its value and thus creates profit and then cut you, the worker,
out of that profit.
The capitalist hoards it all for himself.
All you get is these piddly wages and even the notion of the necessary.
Over the stuff that precedes the surplus labor that is supposed to be keeping you alive,
well, that amount that you get is squeezed and squeezed.
Just how little nourishment is enough to keep a human being alive.
What counts as a shelter in the lived experience of the workers?
The plan always seemed to be drive down labor costs as low as humanly possible because
when you add it all up, profit comes from the gap between how low your labor costs are
and how high a price you can charge for the commodity that labor produces.
And the idea is, if you explain it to the workers in just this way, that they will rise
up in revolution.
Now, according to angles, this theory of surplus value and the exploitation of the worker
was one of the two most important discoveries made by his friend Karl Marx.
It's what made his system superior to the French socialist and the utopians who did not
understand the realities of economic life.
They did not understand the nature of economics.
The factors of production.
The relations of production.
And so they would never understand how to change things.
This is what set the scientific socialism of Marx.
Apart from the mere utopian socialism of his predecessors, we will spend next week on the
other great discovery.
Historical materialism.
This is what makes Marx's work not just a guide to understanding the world, but a roadmap
for how to change it.