This week's episode is brought to you by Herries.
Who are you shopping for this holiday season?
And do you know what you are getting them?
That time is already upon us.
And I have a brilliant suggestion that is both thoughtful and practical.
A Harrys holiday set, which is a gift they will actually use.
And right now, Harrys is offering their starter shave kit and a handsome holiday gift box
starting at just $20.
So it will always fall under nearly every Secret Santa limit.
Now, this is either the fifth or sixth holiday season.
I've been through with Harrys and I have always found the holiday boxes to be a great
idea. Simple, elegant, affordable.
So whether you are buying for somebody else or making your own list, I can tell you that
the holiday gift sets really are a great gift and one that will keep on giving in
perpetuity because you'll be able to get a great shave at a reasonable price for the rest
of the year. As a special offer for fans of the show, we have partnered with Harrys to
give you five dollars off any shaved set, including their limited edition holiday sets
when you go to Harrys dot com slash revolutions.
Plus you will get free shipping.
Each Harry set comes with a weighted handle with an option to engrave five blade razor
cartridges, foaming shave gel for a rich lather travel cover to protect your blades, all
packaged in a handsome holiday gift box.
Free shipping ends on December the 16th, so act now just go to Harrys dot com slash
revolutions. That again, Harrys dot com slash revolutions.
Hello and welcome to revolutions.
Episode twenty two point twenty three on agitation.
Last time we did the biographical introduction of Lenin and croup scale.
And though I called them Vladimir and Nadia last week for future clarity, I will be
referring to them by their better known names, Lenin and Crips guy.
Lucky for us, we ended last week with their first meeting in February 1894, where this
man, Vladimir Ilyich, read aloud from a book that would be the first book he published
under the pen name Lenin.
And though he would use a bunch of different nom de plumes in his life in revolutionary
letters, Lenin would be the one that stuck.
And the one that would become his permanent public identity.
So where we left them was in St.
Petersburg in 1894, working in the Revolutionary Underground just about six months before
the ascension of Czar Nicholas, the second who they would in twenty five years ensure
would be the last czar of Russia.
The Revolutionary Underground at the time of Nicholas's ascension was a tug of war,
pitting the reemergence neon to wrote usts, who will wind up forming the Assads against
the Marxists like Lenin and Crips guy'll who will go on to form the Social Democratic
Labour Party of Russia.
These two groups had plenty to disagree about, but also had a lot in common.
And one of the biggest things they had in common was that they were really only talking
to each other. This was coffee house radicalism.
This was salon bickering.
The Assads were arguing in favor of the rural peasants.
The Marxist were arguing in favor of the industrial workers.
But there were no actual peasants or workers involved in this argument.
These discussion circles of young radical members of the intelligentsia were insular.
These people were coming out of the middle and upper classes and they wore suits.
They sported university educations and they had uncap fist hands in the parlance of our
times. They are 100 percent white collar.
Now, when the earlier peoples will type's had faced the problem of how to connect with
the capital P people.
They went to the people and then they got sent back by the people.
And so they concluded that it was hopeless and they simply had to do the revolution for
themselves. But this is not how Lenin and his comrades are going to want to do things.
They don't want to do the revolution for themselves.
They wanted know they needed to get the proletariat involved.
So that left them facing a vexing question how to connect to the working class who are
meant to be the leaders of our socialist revolution.
This was a real problem for Lenin and one that could not just be dismissed because to
reiterate the point I made when we were talking about plan' off and the emancipation of
labor group. Lenin read Marx historical materialism, the nature of class conflict and the
role of the proletariat and the socialist revolution.
And he believed it.
If they were going to follow the scientific program of some future history they believe
Marx and Engels had laid down.
It was going to take the proletariat as a class doing the necessary revolutionary work,
not just a handful of effete coffee house radicals.
And that brings me to another point I need to make about Lenin.
That when he committed himself to Marxism, he also committed himself to the doctrine of
two revolutions as elaborated by plan' off that because Russia was still laboring under a
medieval mode of agrarian production.
They were going to have to undergo a bourgeois capitalist revolution in order to
sufficiently transform the country for a subsequent socialist revolution for Lenin.
Capitalism was not something he liked, but it was something he considered a vital and
inevitable force of history.
Without it, Russia would remain condemned to the stagnant despotism of orthodoxy,
autocracy and nationality for ever without the historical power of capitalism,
modernizing the Russian economy, increasing its productive capacity, and, more
importantly, turning rural peasants into urban laborers.
The socialist revolution was simply not possible.
And then, of course, along with that advance of the capitalist mode of production would
come the first revolution, the democratic revolution led by the bourgeoisie against the
old medieval state that oppressed them under the weight of anachronistic aristocratic
privilege. And that first revolution would be necessary to create the second and far
preferable socialist revolution.
Now, as they waited for this.
That did not mean they were just going to sit around and do nothing.
No, it did not. Lenin believed that they should begin now to make connections inside the
actual working class to forge at least a small skeletal structure of a political party
that would first add weight to the coming democratic revolution.
And second, make them ready to boldly stride towards the next socialist revolution once
democratic reform made open political organizing legal.
Because remember, the goal here is Marx's dictatorship of the proletariat, which was not
understood to mean a small Jacobin style revolutionary committee of public safety.
It was simply meant to express a mass majority now ruling a fully democratic system.
So one way to think about this is that the dictatorship of an aristocracy is a monarchy.
The dictatorship of the bourgeoisie is an oligarchy.
The coming dictatorship of the proletariat would be mass majority democracy.
The first system Marx always noted approvingly where the majority would actually rule.
That's how it's supposed to go anyway.
So the Russian Marxists of the 1890s believe that what they needed to do was build the
skeleton of an organization that would connect the socialist intelligencia to worker
groups inside the factories and in the rather annoying business speak language of our
time to have this organization be scalable.
But as the proletariat inevitably expanded as a result of the advance of capitalism that
this Proteau party they were building now would be able to grow with it and soon become
the party of the mass majority.
Now, one of the great influences on Lennon's thinking at this time was a German Marxist
named Karl Koutsoukis, who I briefly named checked back when we were talking about the
Emancipation of Labour Group because he was friends with Pavel Axlerod.
They were like neighbours in Zurich.
Now, I can't go overboard on Koutsoukis because this is technically a series on the
Russian revolution, not a general history of 19th century European socialism, though you
wouldn't necessarily know that from listening to our past episodes.
But just so you know, counts, he was one of the two or three most important Marxists in
the generation that came up after Marx and Angles themselves.
Koski was a friend, comrade, disciple, correspondant and occasionally wayward protege,
especially of angles.
What Koutsoukis advocated was a merger of the labor movement and the socialist
intelligentsia who were not at that point.
The same thing. Koski was arguing that the educated intelligentsia needed the manpower,
energy and numbers provided by the workers, and the less educated workers needed the
theories, ideas and direction that would be provided by the more educated members of the
intelligentsia. But again, these two groups are not necessarily primed to be bosom
buddies. On the one side, you have blue collar factory workers and on the other you have
the white collar student socialists.
Culturally, personally, there's a lot of mutual side iron going on.
But. He said these two groups must bridge their differences, recognize the advantages of
an alliance. The principal advantage of which was if they did combine, they could
literally take over the state and become Marxist dictatorship of the proletariat.
The merger of the socialists and the workers was the essential feature of the Social
Democratic Party of Germany.
Which is why Lenin and his friends will soon be organizing their own Russian Social
Democratic Labour Party.
And when the early 1890s, the strategy for forging connections between the workers and
the socialists was a process called propagandizing, which is the opposite of what we
usually understand the term propaganda to mean.
These days we are not talking about brief, manipulative messages aimed at a large
population, but rather an intensive course of education aimed at a select few highly
motivated members of the working class.
These potential propagandized workers could be identified in the kind of worker education
programs that Crips Gaia was dedicating her early life to.
If a particular student was eager and motivated, you could just keep feeding them more
and more books and articles and pamphlets about politics and economics and history until
they emerged as a fully enlightened Marxist.
The problem with this approach is that it was time consuming and extremely hit and miss.
It required patience and sustained interest from both teachers and students.
But if they stuck to it and kept to a strict program of propagandizing individual workers
in ten thousand years, they might all be ready for a revolution.
But what happens if you would prefer your revolution to come less than ten thousand years
from now? Well, we will spend the rest of today's episode talking about the new strategy
they would adopt. And the man who would come to St.
Petersburg in 1895 bearing the new gospel.
This guy will be very important to our story going forward as he starts out as Lenin's
great friend, practically Lenin's only friend, and then down the road, his bitterly
disappointed rival if he was never able to quite bring himself to call Lenin an enemy.
And this is Julius Markoff tof.
When it was all over, there's a near death in 1921 and reflected on the revolution, he
had in fact successfully hijacked and led Lenin said that he had one regret that Markoff
is not with us. What an amazing Conradt he is.
What a pure man. So let us talk about Julius Markoff.
Julius marched off, as we know him in the West by his Anglican ized revolutionary name
was born. On November the 24th, 1873, he was the son of a Russian Jewish family then
residing in the Ottoman capital of Constantinople.
Though they moved to Odessa when Mahtob was 4 years old, he had five siblings, one of
whom Lydia would become a revolutionary socialist Conradt in her own right, and she is
known to the history books as Lydia Dawn.
After taking her Conradt husband's name.
Their father, mother, aunts and uncles seem to have been a generation of disillusioned
liberals, once excited by the prospect of the great reforms they were by the 1870s,
disappointed how far short of the mark this our liberator had ultimately fallen.
Though they were Jewish, they were not particularly observant about him and Mahtob lived
experience as a Jew in the Russian empire, had less to do with a strong cultural or
religious identity built from within.
And more to do with the negative experiences of anti-Semitism he had to deal with from
without. Lydia later said that the myriad ways anti-Semitism expressed itself in Russian
society, both big and small, made her brothers sympathetic to any group who found itself
maltreated for ethnic, religious or class reasons.
But it did not push him towards Jewish nationalism or separatism or Zionism, all of which
were options on the table for radical Jews at the end of the 19th century.
When Mahtob was about 15 years old, the family was living in Saint Petersburg and he fell
in with a group of rebelliously progressive friends who clashed constantly with the more
Russian nationalist conservative kids at the school.
And unlike Lenin, who was always a loner, Mahtob found it easy to make and keep friends.
And he later remarked, I have the nasty privilege of being liked by people.
It was at this point that he got super into the French Revolution.
He read everything he could get his hands on by and about Robespierre, Danton, Daimyo La
Mirarr, a bear and Beb off, and he mentally advanced his own beliefs along with the
course of the revolution.
He said Within half a year I had gone through all the phases of revolutionary enthusiasm.
My model at first was Mirabeau and then the gironde discourse, and then Dunton and
finally Robespierre.
Markoff's ideological evolution would then keep following the course of European social
history. He read all the post Revolutionary Socialists like FOTA and Sensi moan and put
on. And then a friend came back from a family holiday to Switzerland loaded with banned
Russian revolutionary writers.
Lavrov and Chernus Chayefsky are among the names that we would recognize, and this
brought him into contact with the Russian revolutionary tradition and gave him a pretty
narrowest point of view.
Though it must be said that he also came across a journalist's account of the 1881 trial
of the assassins of the Czar Liberator, and walked away from that, convinced that mere
revolutionary terrorism was not only an insufficient strategy.
He was downright counterproductive.
Meanwhile, he got his hands on a copy of the Communist Manifesto and was stirred by its
call to the masses to rise up openly.
Let them tremble at our size and strength marched off quite like the sound of that.
In 1891, Markoff graduated and went off to the University of St.
Petersburg. He was originally studying science, but like so many of his contemporaries,
attending class was secondary to his real passion, which was reading dangerous literature
and dreaming dangerous dreams.
He and his friends formed a little radical reading circle and discussed everything they
could get their hands on. And they were idealistic enough that they wanted to reach out
and bring in members of the working class into this circle.
And they did manage to recruit one worker, and they were very proud of themselves.
Unfortunately, this guy allowed himself to be recruited because that was the mission he
had been assigned by his handlers.
He was a police spy.
And after a few meetings, he turned names over to the police.
One of Markoff's best friends was arrested and after a month of interrogation, he coughed
up Markoff's name. So Mahtob was arrested in February 1892 and then held until May.
But as he sat in custody, it turned out he was such a minor priority that he never really
got interrogated too deeply or too harshly.
He was just another student reading banned books.
In May 1892, his grandfather managed to bail him out of detention while he awaited
sentencing. There would be no trial.
Mind you, there would just be a sentence that would get handed down.
And while others may have emerged from this chastized by the experience, Mahtob was
thrilled by it all. His arrest and detention meant that he had received his revolutionary
baptism. He was a real revolutionary now with real credibility.
He was, of course, expelled from university, though his parents did manage to arrange an
interview with school officials to review the case.
If the boy was sufficiently penitent but Markoff was insufficiently penitent, he in fact
refused to attend the meeting.
The expulsion stood and he awaited his final sentence.
It was during this summer of waiting in 1892 that we come to the conversion to Marxism
portion of Markoff's biography.
He got his hands on the writings of on/off and Axelrod and a French translation of
capital, and he was blown away by what he read.
He later said that before this, his revolutionary instincts had been flimsy and
superficial. And now they had weight and heft.
He believed what he was reading was the final stop on the development of his
revolutionary ideology, which had begun with Mirabeau and now ended with Marx.
Whatever lingering Neruda's ideas he held were banished.
The rural peasants would be an apathetic sack of potatoes until they were turned into a
working class proletariat by the inevitable force of capitalist modernization.
Having had this conversion, Markoff received his sentence in December 1892.
Five months. Solitary confinement.
So he was arrested again and tossed in prison again.
And though it was technically solitary confinement, security and oversight in these
prisons was shockingly lax.
And he was able to get books to read and exchange letters and writing with friends that
were never much analyzed or monitored.
We'll talk more about this later.
But though the TSA's police state was aiming for omnipresent totalitarian suppression, it
would always be hampered by limited personnel, limited resources, limited talent and
limited interest at all levels.
If you were a prison guard, you could either pore over every single sentence of every
single letter that came and went or you could not.
Mahtob was hoping his five months in prison would be it.
But when he got out in May of 1893, he received a further sentence two years of
administrative exile.
Now, he would be allowed to choose his destination.
It just couldn't be a city with a university in order to keep him away from other
students. But someone tipped him off that interesting things were happening in what was
then called Vilna and what is today Vilnius, Lithuania.
So he said, I'll go to Vienna.
And in June 1893, he got on a train and left St.
Petersburg for exile.
And it was in this, quote unquote exile that Julius Markoff really found his own
revolutionary potential.
So Vilna was a part of Lithuania, which had once been a part of Poland, Lithuania, and
had come under Russian had Germany during the great partitions of Poland.
So one of the principal reasons that interesting things were happening in Vilna was
because the authorities there were mostly focused on Polish nationalists, not Russian
socialists. The other reason is that these interesting things that were happening were
happening in the Jewish community, which was really off the radar of the local
authorities, Jewish factory workers often worked for Jewish factory owners.
And so the local Russian authorities considered labor relations in those industries to be
an internal Jewish affair.
So Jewish socialists in Vilna operated uniquely unmonitored and en harassed.
And so even though he was in administrative exile and had to check in with those local
Russian authorities, then not yet 20 year old Mahtob was able to jumpstart his
revolutionary career.
Mahtob make contact with the local Jewish socialists immediately.
The most important of these being Arkady Kramer and Kramer gets to go down as the father
of the Jewish Labor Bund.
And if you know what that means, then great.
If you don't, we'll talk all about the Bund when we get to the formation of the Russian
Social Democratic Labour Party.
Now, initially, Markoff was deployed as a teacher of economics and politics and history,
doing propagandizing among the workers to turn them in to fully enlightened Marxists.
But they did find plenty of eager students.
It was always going to be slow going and slow building.
So over the winter of 1893 1894, krammer Ma Tof and a few others strategized and the
conclusion they came to was that they needed a new strategy, but they needed to move from
propagandizing to agitation, and this strategy would thereafter be referred to as the
Vilna program. Now, they started doing it before they wrote about it, but the Vilna
program was summed up by a pamphlet published in 1895 called On Agitation that was
devised by Kramer and the other Vilna veterans and written up by Martos, who they
discovered, much to their delight, was a very good writer on agitation, was not pure
invention. They were not inventing this out of whole cloth and had many sources feeding
into it. Karl Koutsoukis in the German program, of course, but also a piece that on/off
had written in 1891 in response to the famine, saying that socialists should take
advantage of the crisis to set down literary debate and go out among the people to give a
name and a purpose and a direction to their immediate angry suffering.
But on agitation became the touchstone for the new organizing strategy that Russian
Marxists would embrace by agitation.
They meant ditching abstract philosophy for concrete issues.
For starters, do less talking and more listening to the workers.
Find out what they specifically hated about their job.
The long hours, low wages, docked pay, living conditions, safety concerns, whatever.
Piss them off. Find out about it.
Listen to them. Then bring it back.
Review it. Collate it.
Condense it. Draw it up in a crisp declaration that enumerated those complaints and then
publish it on a single leaflet and get it spread around the factory.
Is this what you want? Because if it is, there is a way to get it.
And that way is to go on strike.
This is the heart of agitation.
Taking nebulous resentment and turning it into direct action helped the workers realize
the benefits of group action to achieve what are clearly their shared goals.
The role of the socialist intelligentsia was to give voice and direction through leaflets
and maybe pamphlets, but not much more than that.
And in many ways, the debates over the merits of this strategy is whether the revolution
is going to be won with 500 page books about abstract philosophy or single page leaflets
about better pay.
The group in Vilna was saying leaflets.
Now, I know what you're saying, and you're right.
This strategy is anathema to traditional Russian anarchist and narrowest ideology, which
said we must not engage with such petty concerns that even if you won a shorter work day
or a few more rubles a month, in exchange, you are granting the premise and legitimacy of
an exploitive capitalist system.
More comfortable chains are still chains, plus small material improvements will sap the
revolutionary energy of the workers, make them complacent.
But on agitation argued the opposite.
It's at the very act of going on strike together and demanding better conditions.
Not asking, demanding would enhance the revolutionary class consciousness of the workers,
not diminish it. That coming together to agitate for concrete shared demands.
The experience of going on strike, suffering hardship together, and hopefully winning
concessions together would create solidarity and trust.
Getting an hour knocked off the workday or getting a slight increase in wages would not
be the end of anything.
It would be the beginning. So for starters, yes.
Agitate for small issues related to individual factories or sectors.
Once this organization is up and running to accomplish small goals, it can be turned to
bigger and more political projects and the workers will turn to those projects with
experience and confidence.
If the revolutionary proletariat is necessary for the achievement of a socialist
revolution, then this is one way to start building the revolutionary proletariat.
And it is certainly quicker and easier than waiting for every single life operator to
graduate from propaganda school with the equivalent of a master's degree in Marxist
economics. Now, there was one further aspect to the Vilna program that was specific to
Vilna, but which did have broader applicability as a general theory.
The problem they were having among the Jewish workers is that most of them spoke Yiddish
while the socialist intelligentsia spoke Russian.
So the Vilna socialist came to a conclusion that's kind of obvious.
Let's write our leaflets in Yiddish.
Don't make them come to us.
Let us go to them now in Vilna.
There was literally a language barrier to overcome.
But in broader strategic terms, speaking the language of the worker, whether it be
literally another language or merely dialect or expressions, are relateable references or
simple sentences.
The important thing was to speak their language.
And one of the most persistent complaints that would be lobbed back at the exiled leaders
like Tarnoff is that they produce nothing the average worker could read or understand.
That was going to have to change if we actually want to organize the masses, not just
talk amongst ourselves.
Now, of course, what krammer and Ma Tof and the others in Vilna were doing wasn't just
speaking the language of the worker, they were Jews working among Jews.
And what we're watching right now is something close to the foundation of the Jewish
Labor Bund, the organization of Jewish Socialists who believed in maintaining a separate
organization of Jewish socialists because Jews faced unique Jewish problems that required
unique Jewish solutions.
And this is going to be an issue down the road once the real revolutions get going.
And I do promise eventually there will be real revolutions that get going.
I mean, was there a place for a Jewish identity inside a movement so committed to
defining the world in terms of economic class?
These are questions we will get to later.
So this agitation strategy was outlined and implemented in by May of 1895, Mahtob was
able to give a speech to a group of about 400 Conrads announcing that it had been a
resounding success.
Their organization was bigger than ever.
They were more democratic than ever.
They were more worker focused than ever.
They actually had workers in their organization.
But this success and their desire to spread the idea to other cities face pushback.
There were intelligencia socialists who enjoyed their pamphlets and books and
intellectual debates.
They wanted to talk theoretical forces of history, not a 10 hour workday.
Then there were the propagandize workers who had achieved enlightenment.
For them, their emergence from a previous state of ignorance was the whole point of the
revolution. It's certainly what they personally valued above all and they saw in the
Vilna program and they read in on agitation and abandonment of that effort, a strategy
that would leave their fellow workers in their ignorance in exchange for a few more
rubles in their pockets.
And they were offended by the idea that it was not worth the time or effort to educate
those workers fully.
Then all they were good for was bodies in the street and that down the road they would be
turned into revolutionary cannon fodder.
Dying on behalf of their intelligencia leaders.
The other big objection, an objection that Lenin and Markoff would themselves soon be
making is what happens if the Vilna program becomes an end unto itself.
Agitation for strikes on behalf of factory workers to address their particular grievances
was great as long as it was a step on the way to the political revolution.
But as the years went on, others in the movement would say this focus on improving the
economic status of the workers is practically all that matters.
The people who would take up this argument would later be disparagingly referred to as
the economists and be added to Lenin's very long list of revolutionary Philistines that
he carried around with him in his pocket.
But as we will see next week right here at this moment in 1895, Lenin is going to be
totally on board with this program.
He will read on agitation and embrace it.
He will meet Mahtob and embrace him.
And next week, we will see how well they are rewarded for this change in strategy, which
will be, you guessed it, exile in Siberia.